var questions = [
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"1","question":"What is the name of the science that studies the structure of the animal's body and the relationship of its parts?","answer":"Anatomy"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"2","question":"What is the name of the science that studies the function of the body systems?","answer":"Physiology"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"3","question":"Give ONE other name for the chin area of your horse.","answer":"Curb groove or chin groove"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"4","question":"What is the name of the area on the horse's head where the curb chain rests?","answer":"Curb groove or chin groove (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"5","question":"What is located between the forehead and the muzzle?","answer":"Face"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"6","question":"What do you call the lock of hair falling forward over the horse’s face?","answer":"Forelock"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"7","question":"What is the horse’s forelock?","answer":"Lock of hair that falls forward over the horse’s face"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"8","question":"What do you call the area at the end of the head that includes the lips and nostrils?","answer":"Muzzle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"9","question":"Where is the horse’s muzzle?","answer":"Area at the end of the head that includes the lips and nostrils"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"10","question":"What do you call the top of a horse's head just back of the ears?","answer":"Poll"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"11","question":"Where is the horse’s poll?","answer":"Top of the horse’s head just back of the ears"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"12","question":"Name 3 PARTS of a horse's front leg below the knee.","answer":"Cannon; fetlock or ankle; pastern; coronet or coronary band; hoof (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"13","question":"Where is the horse’s cannon?","answer":"Lower leg (bone) between the knee or hock and the fetlock or ankle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"14","question":"What part of the horse lies between the knee and the fetlock?","answer":"Cannon"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"15","question":"Where is the coronet band located?","answer":"Hairline above the hoof (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"16","question":"What is the band directly above the hoof called?","answer":"Coronet, coronet band, or coronary band (accept any)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"17","question":"2 part question:  Where is the coronary band and why should you be careful with this area?","answer":"Hairline between the top of the hoof and the bottom of the pastern; because the growth of the hoof starts at the coronary band"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"18","question":"What is the name of the joint above the pastern?","answer":"Fetlock or ankle (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"19","question":"What is another name for the fetlock joint?","answer":"Ankle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"20","question":"Where is the horse’s fetlock?","answer":"Between the cannon and the pastern (on the front legs and hind legs)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"21","question":"Name the 6 joints of the foreleg from proximal to distal.","answer":"Shoulder, elbow, knee, fetlock, pastern, and coffin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"22","question":"Name 3 joints on the front leg.","answer":"Shoulder, elbow, knee, fetlock, pastern, coffin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"23","question":"The elbow, knee, and fetlock are all joints on which leg?","answer":"Front leg (FYI: The 6 joints on the front leg are shoulder, elbow, knee, fetlock, pastern, and coffin joint.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"24","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC names for 3 of the following joints on the FRONT leg:  coffin, pastern, fetlock, and knee","answer":"Coffin is the distal interphalangeal joint; pastern is the proximal interphalangeal joint; fetlock is the metacarpophalangeal joint; and knee is the carpus."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"25","question":"What joint is located between the shoulder and the knee?","answer":"Elbow"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"26","question":"Where is the horse’s elbow?","answer":"Between the horse’s arm and forearm (on the horse’s front leg)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"27","question":"The forearm of the horse lies between what TWO parts?","answer":"Elbow and knee (also accept arm and knee or any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"28","question":"What part of the horse is located between the elbow and the knee?","answer":"Forearm"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"29","question":"What joint is located between the elbow and the fetlock?","answer":"Knee (carpus)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"30","question":"Where is the horse’s knee?","answer":"On the front leg between the forearm and the cannon (or between the elbow and the fetlock)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"31","question":"The stifle, hock, and fetlock are all joints on which leg?","answer":"Hind leg (FYI: The 7 joints of the hind leg are sacroiliac, hip, stifle, hock, fetlock, pastern, and coffin joint.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"32","question":"What is the main role of the hindquarters?","answer":"Propulsion"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"33","question":"Do the front or hind legs have the most joints?","answer":"Hind (FYI: Hind legs have 7 joints; front legs have 6 joints.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"34","question":"Name the 7 joints of the hind leg in order from proximal to distal.","answer":"Sacroiliac, hip, stifle, hock, fetlock, pastern, and coffin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"35","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC names for the following 4 joints on the HIND leg:  coffin, pastern, fetlock, and hock.","answer":"Coffin is the distal interphalangeal joint; pastern is the proximal interphalangeal joint; fetlock is the metatarsophalangeal joint); hock is the tarsus."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"36","question":"Name 3 joints on the hind leg.","answer":"Sacroiliac, hip, stifle, hock, fetlock, pastern, coffin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"37","question":"Which muscle helps to pull the hind leg forward and to enable propulsion giving the horse a long, powerful stride?","answer":"Gaskin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"38","question":"What is the horse’s gaskin?","answer":"Muscular part of the hind leg between the stifle and the hock"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"39","question":"What is the name of the muscular part of the hind leg above the hock?","answer":"Gaskin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"40","question":"What JOINT is located between the stifle and the fetlock?","answer":"Hock"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"41","question":"Where is the horse’s hock?","answer":"On the hind leg between the gaskin and the cannon"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"42","question":"What is the name of the pointed area on the hind leg between the gaskin and the cannon?","answer":"Hock"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"43","question":"What JOINT is located between the hip and the hock?","answer":"Stifle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"44","question":"Where is the horse’s stifle?","answer":"On the hind leg between the thigh and the gaskin (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"45","question":"What part of the horse is located directly above the stifle?","answer":"Thigh"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"46","question":"What part of the horse is located between the coronet and the ground?","answer":"Hoof"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"47","question":"What do you call the curved covering of horn over the foot?","answer":"Hoof"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"48","question":"Where is the horse’s pastern?","answer":"Between the coronet band and the fetlock (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"49","question":"2 part question:  How many pasterns does a horse have and what is the best angle?","answer":"4 pasterns; 45 - 50 degree angle (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"50","question":"What is the part of the horse between the fetlock and the coronet band?","answer":"Pastern"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"51","question":"What do you call the curved, upper part of the horse's neck?","answer":"Crest"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"52","question":"On a horse, what is the crest?","answer":"Part of the neck under the mane, the top line of the neck, or the curved upper part of the neck (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"53","question":"Where is the throatlatch on a horse located?","answer":"Between the jawbone and the neck (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"54","question":"On a horse, what do you call the distinct space between the jawbone and the neck?","answer":"Throatlatch"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"55","question":"Starting at the poll, name the 6 parts of the horse that make up the entire topline.","answer":"Poll; crest; withers; back; loin or coupling; croup or rump"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"56","question":"Together, the withers, back, loin, and croup make up what?","answer":"Top line"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"57","question":"What do you call the part of the horse's top line between the withers and the loin?","answer":"Back"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"58","question":"Where is the horse’s back?","answer":"Between the withers and the loin or coupling"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"59","question":"Name the part of the horse's topline that is just in front of the tail.","answer":"Croup or rump (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"60","question":"Where is the croup of the horse?","answer":"Part of the top line just in front of the tail; the area between the loin or coupling and the dock of the tail (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"61","question":"Give TWO names for the area of the horse between the loin and the buttock.","answer":"Croup and rump"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"62","question":"What do you call the base of a horse’s tail?","answer":"Dock or tail head (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"63","question":"What is the horse’s dock of the tail?","answer":"Bony part of the tail"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"64","question":"What is the term for the pivot point of the top line that is located at the area between the last rib and the croup?","answer":"Loin or coupling (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"65","question":"What part of the horse is located between the back and the croup?","answer":"Loin or coupling (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"66","question":"Where is the horse’s loin or coupling?","answer":"Between the back and the croup or rump"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"67","question":"What part of the top line has no bone structure for support other than the lumbar vertebrae?","answer":"Loin or coupling (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"68","question":"What is the name for the part of the horse between the neck and the back?","answer":"Withers"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"69","question":"What part of the horse is important in keeping the saddle in place?","answer":"Withers"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"70","question":"What are the horse’s withers?","answer":"Pointy area between the neck and the back"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"71","question":"What is the name for the rounded trunk area of the horse?","answer":"Barrel"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"72","question":"What is the horse’s barrel?","answer":"Rounded trunk or belly area"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"73","question":"What part of the horse is located between the rump and the quarter?","answer":"Buttocks"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"74","question":"What is the depth of heart?","answer":"Measurement from top of withers to the chest floor"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"75","question":"What is measured from the chest floor to the top of the withers?","answer":"Depth of heart"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"76","question":"Where is the horse known for being ticklish?","answer":"Flank"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"77","question":"Where is the horse’s heart girth?","answer":"Belly area directly behind the front legs; measurement around the body just back of the withers (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"78","question":"What is the term for the measurement around the horse's body just back of the withers?","answer":"Girth or heart girth (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"79","question":"Name 3 parts of the circulatory  or cardiovascular system.","answer":"Heart; arteries; veins; capillaries; blood"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"80","question":"What is the easiest way to determine if the cardiovascular system is working properly?","answer":"Check the pulse or listen to the heart"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"81","question":"Which system in the horse consists of blood, blood vessels, and the heart?","answer":"Circulatory (cardiovascular)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"82","question":"What is the anatomical name of the tubular tissue that generally carries oxygenated blood under high pressure away from the heart?","answer":"Artery"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"83","question":"Which structures carry blood AWAY from the heart?","answer":"Arteries"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"84","question":"Explain the DIRECTIONAL differences between arteries and veins.","answer":"Arteries carry blood AWAY from the heart; veins carry blood to the heart."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"85","question":"Name 3 ways that veins differ from arteries.","answer":"Veins contain a larger volume of blood; veins have thinner walls; veins have valves; veins carry blood to the heart; arteries have thicker walls"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"86","question":"What is the name of the primary vessel that carries blood from the heart to the rest of the body?","answer":"Aorta"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"87","question":"What artery is the main blood supply to the head?","answer":"Carotid artery (FYI:  The left and right common carotid arteries each divide into internal and external carotid arteries.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"88","question":"The coronary arteries are the first branches off the aorta and carry blood to what structure?","answer":"Heart"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"89","question":"What arteries provide blood to the sensitive structures of the foot?","answer":"Digital arteries (medial and lateral digital arteries)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"90","question":"The medial and lateral digital arteries furnish blood to what part of the horse?","answer":"Foot"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"91","question":"The blood supply to the foot is furnished by what TWO digital arteries?","answer":"Medial and lateral digital arteries"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"92","question":"What artery is located under the jaw bone at the last cheek tooth and can be used to take a pulse?","answer":"Facial artery"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"93","question":"Where is the femoral artery?","answer":"Hind leg"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"94","question":"What organ receives oxygenated blood from the left gastric artery?","answer":"Stomach"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"95","question":"Which artery carries oxygen-poor blood from the heart to the lungs?","answer":"Pulmonary artery"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"96","question":"The blood leaving the right ventricle of the heart by the pulmonary artery flows into what organ?","answer":"Lungs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"97","question":"What organ receives oxygenated blood from the renal artery?","answer":"Kidney"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"98","question":"How much blood does an adult horse's body contain?","answer":"About 50 liters or 13.2 gallons (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"99","question":"Name the TWO major components of blood.","answer":"Plasma and blood cells"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"100","question":"Name 3 functions of the blood.","answer":"Transports nutrients; transports gases; transports hormones; removes wastes; fights infections; regulates pH; clots blood; regulates body temperature; regulates blood pressure (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"101","question":"What is the term for low oxygen saturation in the blood?","answer":"Hypoxemia (or arterial hypoxemia)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"102","question":"What is the name of the clear, yellowish fluid portion of blood in which various blood cells are suspended?","answer":"Plasma"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"103","question":"2 part question:  What is the name of the fluid in whole blood and what is the name of the fluid in blood after the cells and clotting factors have been removed?","answer":"Plasma is the fluid in whole blood; serum is the fluid left after the blood cells and clotting factors have been removed."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"104","question":"In what part of the vascular system does the majority of exchange of gases and nutrients occur?","answer":"Capillaries"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"105","question":"Which are the smallest blood vessels?","answer":"Capillaries"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"106","question":"2 part question:  Which are the smallest blood vessels and what do they connect?","answer":"Capillaries; connect arteries with veins"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"107","question":"2 part question:  Give the common names and scientific names for the 3 types of blood \"cells\".","answer":"Red blood cells (erythrocytes), white blood cells (leukocytes), platelets (thrombocytes) (FYI:  Platelets have no nuclei therefore they are not true cells.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"108","question":"What is the common name for thrombocytes?","answer":"Platelets"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"109","question":"What is the main physiological function of thrombocytes?","answer":"Blood clotting"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"110","question":"Which cell-like components of blood aid in clotting?","answer":"Platelets (thrombocytes) (FYI:  Platelets are not considered cells because they have no nuclei.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"111","question":"What is the main function of erythrocytes?","answer":"Transport oxygen (to the tissues and organs)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"112","question":"What are erythrocytes?","answer":"Red blood cells"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"113","question":"Where does formation of red blood cells occur?","answer":"Bone marrow"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"114","question":"What is the main function of red blood cells?","answer":"Transport oxygen (to the tissues and organs)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"115","question":"To what does oxygen attach on the red blood cells?","answer":"Hemoglobin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"116","question":"In order to successfully transport oxygen, hemoglobin must combine with what mineral?","answer":"Iron"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"117","question":"What is the name of the iron-containing protein found in erythrocytes that binds to oxygen?","answer":"Hemoglobin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"118","question":"What are leukocytes?","answer":"White blood cells"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"119","question":"Name 3 of the 5 types of leucocytes or white blood cells.","answer":"Neutrophils, basophils, eosinophils, lymphocytes, monocytes"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"120","question":"What SPECIFIC type of white blood cell is found in the spleen and lymph nodes and is important in fighting infection?","answer":"Lymphocytes"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"121","question":"2 part question:  The heart is composed of how many chambers and what are their names?","answer":"4 (four) chambers; left ventricle, right ventricle, left atrium, right atrium"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"122","question":"You do the math...If the cardiac output is 35 liters per minute and the heart rate is 35 beats per minute, what is the stroke volume?","answer":"1 liter (FYI:  Cardiac Output = stroke volume x heart rate)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"123","question":"What is cardiac output?","answer":"How much blood the heart can pump in one minute (FYI: Cardiac output=stroke volume x heart rate.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"124","question":"You do the math...If the resting heart rate is 32 beats per minute and the stroke volume is one liter, what is the cardiac output?","answer":"32 liters per minute (FYI: Cardiac output = stroke volume x heart rate)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"125","question":"In reference to the heart, what is stroke volume?","answer":"Amount of blood the heart pumps with each beat"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"126","question":"What is the largest muscular organ of the cardiovascular system?","answer":"Heart"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"127","question":"What is the cone-shaped muscular organ located between the lungs that propels blood through the body by muscular contractions?","answer":"Heart"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"128","question":"How many chambers are in a horse’s heart?","answer":"4 (four) (FYI: Left and right atria and left and right ventricles)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"129","question":"To which side of the horse’s heart does blood return from the body?","answer":"Right side (FYI: Blood from the body returns to the right atrium through the cranial and caudal vena cavae.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"130","question":"Simultaneously, blood enters the right atrium from the body and the left atrium from where?","answer":"Lungs (FYI:  Oxygenated blood from the lungs enters the left atrium through the pulmonary vein.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"131","question":"What chamber of the heart does the oxygenated blood from the lungs enter first?","answer":"Left atrium"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"132","question":"Which chamber of the heart is the primary pumping chamber for moving oxygenated blood to the body?","answer":"Left ventricle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"133","question":"Which chamber of the heart does blood returning from the body by the cranial and caudal vena cavae enter first?","answer":"Right atrium"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"134","question":"Correctly organize the blood flow through the following areas starting with the cranial vena cava: cranial vena cava, left ventricle, pulmonary vein, right atrium, pulmonary artery, lungs, and aorta.","answer":"Cranial vena cava, right atrium, pulmonary artery, lungs, pulmonary vein, left ventricle, aorta"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"135","question":"In what organ would Purkinje fibers be found?","answer":"Heart (FYI:  Purkinje FIBERS are specialized cardiac muscle fibers that conduct the electrical impulses that are responsible for the contractions of the ventricles.  Purkinje CELLS are neurons in the cerebellum.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"136","question":"What is the function of the sinoatrial node which is located in the right atrium of the heart? (sign-oh-AY-tree-al)","answer":"Pacemaker of the heart"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"137","question":"In regards to anatomy, why is it best to listen to the heartbeat from the left side of the horse's body?","answer":"Heart is closer to the left side."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"138","question":"Name ONE of the functions of the heart that makes the sounds you can hear with a stethoscope.","answer":"Opening of heart valves; closing of heart valves"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"139","question":"What organ in the abdominal cavity stores red blood cells, filters blood, removes old blood cells, and assists in combating infections?","answer":"Spleen"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"140","question":"What is the MAIN function of the horse's spleen?","answer":"Stores red blood cells (FYI:  Spleen also filters blood and removes old blood cells.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"141","question":"How does the spleen help the race horse increase its level of arterial oxygen and maintain levels of physical exertion?","answer":"Spleen stores red blood cells; when needed, it contracts releasing additional red blood cells to carry oxygen."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"142","question":"What vein in the horse's neck is commonly used to draw blood samples?","answer":"Jugular vein"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"143","question":"Veins from the stomach, spleen, intestines, and pancreas all join to form the portal vein which carries blood to an important organ in the abdominal cavity where essential metabolic functions are performed.  What is the name of this organ?","answer":"Liver"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"144","question":"What is the ONLY vein that carries oxygenated blood?","answer":"Pulmonary vein"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"145","question":"What TWO veins bring unoxygenated blood from the head and body back to the heart?","answer":"Cranial and caudal vena cavae"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"146","question":"What is the term for the process of preparing food for absorption?","answer":"Digestion"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"147","question":"The mouth, esophagus, stomach, and intestines are all parts of what system of the horse?","answer":"Digestive system"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"148","question":"Which system of the horse converts feed into forms that can be used by the body for energy?","answer":"Digestive system"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"149","question":"Give ONE reason why horse owners should have knowledge of the horse's digestive system.","answer":"So you'll know how to feed them correctly or so you know how to look for signs of colic"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"150","question":"What is the name of the tract that consists of a musculomembranous tube that extends from the mouth to the anus?","answer":"Digestive tract,  gastrointestinal tract, or alimentary canal (accept any)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"151","question":"Name 7 parts of the digestive tract.","answer":"Mouth, pharynx, esophagus, stomach, small intestines (duodenum, jejunum, ileum, cecum, large colon (right ventral colon, sternal flexure, left ventral colon, pelvic flexure, left dorsal colon, diaphragmatic flexure, right dorsal colon), rectum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"152","question":"Name 3 functions of the horse's gastrointestinal tract.","answer":"Prehension (grasping food), mastication (chewing food), salivation (moisturizing of food), deglutition (swallowing food), mixing food, digestion, absorption, peristalsis (movement of food), defecation (elimination of food)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"153","question":"Explain how each of the following 4 parts of the horse is involved in the process of digestion:  lips, incisors, molars, and tongue.","answer":"Lips—pick up feed; incisors—bite off grass; molars—chew or grind food; tongue—moves feed in the mouth"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"154","question":"Name 3 mechanical factors in digestion.","answer":"Grasping food (prehension), chewing (mastication), swallowing (deglutition), peristalsis (movements of stomach and intestines), defecation (pooping)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"155","question":"Referring to the digestive system, what does VFA mean?","answer":"Volatile fatty acids (FYI:  VFA's are produced by the cellulose-digesting microbes in the horse's hindgut.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"156","question":"Name 3 parts of the digestive tract.","answer":"Mouth, pharynx, esophagus, stomach, small intestine (duodenum, jejunum, ileum), large intestine (cecum, large colon, small colon, rectum)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"157","question":"Name 3 accessory organs of the digestive system.","answer":"Teeth, tongue, salivary glands, pancreas, liver"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"158","question":"What TWO organs deliver enzymes and products into the duodenum to assist in the digestive process?","answer":"Pancreas and liver"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"159","question":"The salivary glands, pancreas, and liver are accessory organs of what system?","answer":"Digestive system"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"160","question":"Most farm animals have an organ that stores bile, but horses do not.  What is this organ?","answer":"Gall bladder"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"161","question":"What is the name of the dark green-yellow substance secreted by the liver?","answer":"Bile"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"162","question":"What is the largest INTERNAL ORGAN of the horse?","answer":"Liver"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"163","question":"Explain how bile is released in the horse's digestive system.","answer":"Continuously secreted by the liver (into the bile duct which empties into the duodenum) [FYI:  Horses do not have gallbladders to store bile.]"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"164","question":"Name 3 substances that are secreted INTO the duodenum.","answer":"Bile, trypsin, pancreatic lipase"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"165","question":"What does pancreatic enzyme amylase do?","answer":"Digests starch"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"166","question":"Which enzyme assists in the digestion of fats?","answer":"Lipase"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"167","question":"What is the purpose of lipase?","answer":"Digests fats"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"168","question":"Name ONE digestive enzyme that helps break down proteins.","answer":"Pepsin, trypsin, chymotrypsin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"169","question":"What does the enzyme pepsin do?","answer":"Breaks down proteins"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"170","question":"What does the enzyme trypsin do?","answer":"Breaks down proteins"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"171","question":"From cranial to caudal, name the 4 parts of the horse's FOREGUT.","answer":"Mouth, esophagus, stomach, small intestine (Do NOT accept small colon which is part of the hindgut.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"172","question":"Name the parts of the horse's foregut in correct order starting from the mouth and including the 3 parts of the small intestine.","answer":"Mouth, pharynx, esophagus, stomach, duodenum, jejunum, ileum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"173","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse's foregut.","answer":"Mouth, esophagus, stomach, small intestine (Do NOT accept small colon which is part of the hindgut.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"174","question":"What is the esophagus?","answer":"Muscular tube that moves feedstuffs from the pharynx to the stomach"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"175","question":"What is the muscular tube 50 - 60 inches in length that extends from the pharynx to the stomach?","answer":"Esophagus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"176","question":"In reference to digestion, give TWO functions of the horse's mouth.","answer":"Intake food (prehension); chew food (mastication); wet food with saliva (salivation); swallow food (deglutition)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"177","question":"What is the FIRST part of the digestive tract?","answer":"Mouth"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"178","question":"What does deglutition mean?","answer":"Swallowing"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"179","question":"What structure in the horse's mouth is forced up by the tongue during swallowing to keep food out of the nose?","answer":"Soft palate"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"180","question":"What is the medical term for swallowing?","answer":"Deglutition"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"181","question":"What does mastication mean?","answer":"Chewing of food"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"182","question":"What type of movement is necessary for a horse to grind its food?","answer":"Lateral (side to side) movement"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"183","question":"What is the medical term for chewing?","answer":"Mastication"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"184","question":"Because the upper jaw is wider than the lower jaw, how does mastication occur?","answer":"On one side of the jaw at a time (also accept in a circular motion)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"185","question":"What TWO tracts does the pharynx belong to?","answer":"Respiratory and digestive tracts"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"186","question":"What is the short, funnel-shaped tube between the mouth and the esophagus?","answer":"Pharynx"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"187","question":"What is the pharynx?","answer":"Funnel-shaped tube between the mouth and the esophagus (also accept the throat) (FYI:  There's an oropharynx and a nasopharynx.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"188","question":"What are TWO functions of the pharynx?","answer":"Food passage between the mouth and the esophagus; air passage between the nostrils and the trachea"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"189","question":"What is the term for the grasping of food in order to get it into the mouth?","answer":"Prehension"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"190","question":"What is the horse's main structure for grasping food?","answer":"Lips (upper lip)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"191","question":"Which TWO anatomic structures aid the horse in collecting loose feed such as kernels of grain from a feed bucket or manger?","answer":"Upper lips (lips) and tongue"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"192","question":"What does prehension mean?","answer":"Grasping of food"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"193","question":"Where do most of the fats get digested?","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"194","question":"Where is the primary site of protein digestion in the horse?","answer":"Small intestine (FYI:  About 50 – 70% of the protein in grain-based diets is digested and absorbed in the small intestine, but less than 1/3 of the protein in hay is absorbed in foregut.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"195","question":"Soluble carbohydrates are digested and absorbed in what part of the digestive system?","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"196","question":"In which organ does the majority of digestion and absorption occur?","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"197","question":"Give TWO reasons why the horse's small intestines are susceptible to displacement, telescoping, and twisting.","answer":"Great length; loose attachment to the abdominal wall (mesentery)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"198","question":"The small intestine is located between what two parts of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Stomach and large intestine (cecum)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"199","question":"What is the capacity of the small intestine?","answer":"40 – 48 quarts (10 – 12 gallons) (accept any number within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"200","question":"What is name of the material leaving the stomach and entering the small intestine?","answer":"Chyme (pronounced kime)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"201","question":"Give ONE reason why the great length of the small intestine can cause problems.","answer":"Intestine can twist or telescope (FYI: Twisted intestine is called a volvulus; telescoped intestine is called intussusception.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"202","question":"What is the AVERAGE length of the horse's small intestine?","answer":"About 70 feet"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"203","question":"Name the 3 parts of the small intestine.","answer":"Duodenum, jejunum, ileum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"204","question":"Into what part of the digestive tract do the bile duct and pancreatic duct empty?","answer":"Duodenum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"205","question":"What is the name for the terminal portion of the small intestine?","answer":"Ileum (FYI: Ilium is in the pelvis.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"206","question":"Passage of feeds through the small intestine takes approximately how long?","answer":"30 - 90 minutes (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"207","question":"What are the small projections in the small intestine called?","answer":"Villi"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"208","question":"The stomach is what percent of the total capacity of the horse's digestive tract?","answer":"8 - 10% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"209","question":"What is the capacity of the horse's stomach?","answer":"8 - 19 quarts or 2 – 4.75 gallons (accept any number within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"210","question":"How many compartments are in a horse's stomach?","answer":"1 (one) compartment"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"211","question":"The angle at which the esophagus meets the stomach and the powerful sphincter at that junction makes it nearly impossible for feed to do what?","answer":"Re-enter the esophagus once it's deposited in the stomach (also accept vomit)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"212","question":"What powerful, ring-like muscle closes the opening of the esophagus into the stomach?","answer":"Cardiac sphincter"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"213","question":"What SPECIFIC part of the stomach connects to the esophagus?","answer":"Cardia (FYI: There's a tight, ring-like muscle at the cardia called the cardiac sphincter which prevents the horse from vomiting.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"214","question":"Give ONE reason why horses can't vomit.","answer":"Blocking action of the soft palate; angle at which the esophagus meets the stomach; tight cardiac sphincter prevents food from re-entering the esophagus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"215","question":"What ring-like muscle regulates the flow of stomach contents into the duodenum?","answer":"Pyloric sphincter"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"216","question":"What part of the stomach empties into the duodenum?","answer":"Pylorus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"217","question":"What TWO areas of the digestive tract are connected by the pylorus?","answer":"Stomach and small intestine (duodenum)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"218","question":"Of the following 3 organs, where does food stay the LEAST amount of time in the digestive system:  stomach, small intestine, or large intestine?","answer":"Stomach (FYI:  stomach 15 - 45 minutes, small intestine 30 - 90 minutes, large intestine 24 - 72 hours)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"219","question":"Food remains in the stomach for about how long before it starts passing into the small intestine?","answer":"15 - 45 minutes (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"220","question":"Name TWO things secreted by the stomach.","answer":"Hydrochloric acid, pepsin, gastric lipase (FYI:  Lipase is predominantly secreted by the pancreas.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"221","question":"Where in the horse's digestive tract is hydrochloric acid secreted?","answer":"Stomach (lining of the stomach)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"222","question":"What acid secreted by the stomach helps digest food?","answer":"Hydrochloric acid (HCl)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"223","question":"Name 3 sections of the digestive tract where impactions are most likely to occur.","answer":"Cecum, small colon, large colon, pelvic flexure"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"224","question":"From cranial to caudal, name the 4 parts of the horse’s HINDGUT.","answer":"Cecum, large colon, small colon, rectum (Do NOT accept small intestine which is part of the foregut.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"225","question":"2 part question:  How long is the large intestine and what is its capacity?","answer":"25 feet long; 32 gallons or 128 quart capacity"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"226","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse's hindgut.","answer":"Cecum, large colon, small colon, rectum (Do NOT accept small intestine which is part of the foregut.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"227","question":"2 part question:  What is the length and capacity of the cecum?","answer":"4 feet long; 28 - 32 quarts or 7 - 8 gallons (accept any number within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"228","question":"The cecum lies between what TWO parts of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Small intestine (ileum) and large colon"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"229","question":"How long is the cecum?","answer":"4 (four) feet"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"230","question":"What part of the horse's digestive tract functions similar to the rumen in cattle and sheep?","answer":"Cecum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"231","question":"What is the process by which fiber is digested?","answer":"Fermentation (by microbes in the large intestine)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"232","question":"Where in the horse's digestive tract is the primary site of water absorption?","answer":"Large intestine or hindgut (FYI:  The largest percentage of water is absorbed in the large colon, but water is also absorbed in the cecum and small colon.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"233","question":"Hay is digested primarily in what part of the digestive system?","answer":"Cecum (by microbial fermentation)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"234","question":"What part of the large intestine serves as a microbial vat?","answer":"Cecum (FYI: Microbial fermentation of fiber occurs in the cecum.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"235","question":"What part of the digestive system is referred to as a \"blind pouch\"?","answer":"Cecum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"236","question":"Why is the cecum sometimes called a \"blind pouch\"?","answer":"Because feed stuffs both enter and exit at the top"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"237","question":"What causes the intestinal or gut sounds that can be heard with a stethoscope pressed to the horse's abdomen?","answer":"Movement of gas or fluids through the intestines or cecal activity (accept either)  (FYI:  The medical term is borborygmus.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"238","question":"Give ONE reason why the pelvic flexure in the large colon a common site of impaction.","answer":"Tight, upward, hairpin turn; large colon narrows in diameter (FYI: The pelvic flexure is tight turn between the left ventral colon and the left dorsal colon.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"239","question":"The large colon has the largest capacity of the horse's digestive system.  What percent of total capacity is it?","answer":"38% - 40% (accept any percent within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"240","question":"How long is the large colon?","answer":"10 - 12 feet (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"241","question":"Which part of the horse's large intestine has the largest capacity?","answer":"Large colon (FYI: The capacity of the large colon is about 80 quarts or 20 gallons.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"242","question":"What is the FINAL part of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Rectum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"243","question":"The horse's small colon lies between what TWO other parts of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Large colon and rectum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"244","question":"Where are the characteristic balls of feces formed?","answer":"Small colon"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"245","question":"What is the capacity of the small colon?","answer":"4 (four) gallons or 16 quarts (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"246","question":"Name TWO things that occur in the small colon.","answer":"Water is absorbed; fecal balls are formed."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"247","question":"What is the name given to the waste matter of digestion?","answer":"Manure or feces (poop)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"248","question":"The average 1000 pound horse can produce how much manure in one day?","answer":"28 - 50 pounds (accept any number within this range) [FYI: Horses produce about 31 pounds of feces and about 2.4 gallons of urine adding up to about 51 pounds of waste daily.]"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"249","question":"What does defecation mean?","answer":"Pooping"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"250","question":"On average, how many tons of manure does the average 1000 pound horse produce in one year?","answer":"9 tons [FYI: enough to FILL a 12 x 12 stall, 730 cubic feet per, or 2 cubic yards per month (including bedding)]"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"251","question":"What is the lining of the abdominal wall?","answer":"Peritoneum (pair-ih-toe-NEE-um) (FYI:  Visceral peritoneum lines the organs and parietal peritoneum lines the abdominal cavity.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"252","question":"What are probiotics used for?","answer":"To increase the population of beneficial microorganisms in the digestive tract"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"253","question":"What are commercial preparations of dried beneficial intestinal microorganisms?","answer":"Probiotics"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"254","question":"What is the general term for the bacteria and other microorganisms that normally reside in the large intestine?","answer":"Intestinal flora"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"255","question":"What is intestinal flora?","answer":"Bacteria normally present in the intestine"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"256","question":"Name 3 important digestive actions of the bacteria and protozoa in the cecum and colon.","answer":"Digest cellulose or fiber (bacteria, fungi, yeasts); produce volatile fatty acids (protozoa); synthesize B vitamins; synthesize Vitamin K; break down protein into amino acids (proteolytic bacteria); digest starch (lactic acid-producing bacteria)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"257","question":"2 part question:  A normal horse requires how many minutes to eat a pound of hay and how many minutes to eat a pound of grain?","answer":"15 - 20 minutes to eat a pound of hay; 5 - 10 minutes to eat a pound of grain"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"258","question":"Which takes more time to pass from the horse’s stomach into the small intestine, hay or water?","answer":"Hay"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"259","question":"How long is the rate of food passage from the mouth to the anus?","answer":"1½ - 3 days (36 - 72 hours) [accept any number within this range]"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"260","question":"When a horse is fed a balanced hay to grain ratio, it generally takes about how many HOURS for the ingested material to pass through the digestive tract and be passed out as fecal material?","answer":"36 - 72 hours (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"261","question":"What are 3 factors that may affect the rate of passage of feedstuffs through the gastrointestinal tract of the horse?","answer":"Processing of food; how much is eaten; frequency of feeding; exercise; individual differences; time of watering; associative effects; ratio of hay to grain"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"262","question":"Describe a ruminant digestive system.","answer":"Fiber is digested in the rumen, there's enzymatic digestion in foregut, and there's minimal digestion in the hindgut."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"263","question":"Describe a non-ruminant digestive system.","answer":"Carbohydrates, proteins, and fats are digested in the foregut (by enzymes); fiber is digested in the hindgut (by bacterial fermentation) (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"264","question":"Digestively speaking, how is the horse categorized?","answer":"Non-ruminant herbivore"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"265","question":"2 part question:  What makes up 99% of saliva and what makes up the other 1% of saliva?","answer":"99% water; 1% inorganic salts (electrolytes) and proteins (enzymes)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"266","question":"Saliva is produced by what glands?","answer":"Salivary glands (FYI: The parotid, sublingual, and submandibular or submaxillary are salivary glands.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"267","question":"What stimulates the secretion of saliva in the horse?","answer":"Chewing"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"268","question":"Located beneath the ear, what is the largest of the horse's 3 salivary glands?","answer":"Parotid"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"269","question":"How many GALLONS of saliva are produced and swallowed by the horse each day?","answer":"8 - 10 gallons (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"270","question":"What is produced by the salivary glands?","answer":"Saliva (spit)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"271","question":"Besides water, what are the components of saliva?","answer":"Inorganic salts (electrolytes) and proteins (enzymes)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"272","question":"2 part question:  Name TWO pairs of salivary glands in the horse and give their locations.","answer":"Parotid—below the ear; submaxillary or submandibular—between the jaws; sublingual—beneath the tongue"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"273","question":"What is the COMMON term for the vallate, foliate, and fungiform papillae that are found on the tongue?","answer":"Taste buds"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"274","question":"What is an enterolith?","answer":"Stone-like mass (mineralization) that forms around feeds or foreign objects that’ve been ingested (FYI:  “Entero” means small intestine and “lith” means stone.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"275","question":"What is the mesentery?","answer":"Tissue that connects the small intestines to the abdominal wall"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"276","question":"What is the name for the wave-like muscular contractions that move food down the digestive tract?","answer":"Peristalsis"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"277","question":"What is peristalsis?","answer":"Wave-like movements that move food through the digestive tract"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"278","question":"What is the horse's auricle?","answer":"External or outer ear"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"279","question":"What is the external part of the ear called?","answer":"Auricle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"280","question":"Name ONE of the endocrine glands that is attached to the brain.","answer":"Pituitary gland; pineal gland"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"281","question":"What is endocrinology?","answer":"Study of endocrine glands and/or hormones"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"282","question":"Which body system has glands that produce hormones to regulate growth, reproduction, metabolism, and digestion?","answer":"Endocrine"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"283","question":"What system produces chemical substances called hormones?","answer":"Endocrine"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"284","question":"What is the name for chemical reactions occurring in the body?","answer":"Metabolism"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"285","question":"What is a hormone?","answer":"Body-regulating chemical secreted by an endocrine gland into the bloodstream"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"286","question":"Name 3 of the horse's body functions that are controlled by the endocrine system.","answer":"Growth, reproduction, metabolism, digestion"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"287","question":"How does a hormone get to a distant part of the body?","answer":"Through the bloodstream"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"288","question":"What is the study of hormones and their effects called?","answer":"Endocrinology"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"289","question":"Adrenaline is a hormone secreted by the central portion of the adrenal gland that acts primarily as a stimulant. Give another name for adrenaline.","answer":"Epinephrine"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"290","question":"Where in the horse's body is epinephrine produced?","answer":"Adrenal gland"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"291","question":"What structure in the brain controls the release of hormones by the pituitary gland?","answer":"Hypothalamus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"292","question":"What is the function of insulin?","answer":"Controls blood sugar levels"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"293","question":"Insulin controls glucose levels in the horse's body.  Where is insulin produced?","answer":"Pancreas (FYI: in the Islets of Langerhans)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"294","question":"Name ONE function of the horse's pancreas.","answer":"Secretes insulin (endocrine gland); secretes digestive enzymes (exocrine gland)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"295","question":"Explain how insulin and glucagon act.","answer":"Insulin moves extra glucose from blood to storage in body; glucagon moves stored glucose back into the blood when needed."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"296","question":"Which endocrine gland is responsible for the maintenance of calcium levels in the blood?","answer":"Parathyroid gland (also accept thyroid due to the hormone calcitonin)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"297","question":"What is parathyroid hormone?","answer":"Hormone secreted by the parathyroid gland (that increases calcium in the blood)."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"298","question":"Oxytocin and Vasopressin are hormones secreted by the posterior pituitary.  Name 3 hormones produced by the ANTERIOR pituitary.","answer":"FSH (Follicle Stimulating Hormone); LH (Luteinizing Hormone); Prolactin; TSH (Thyroid Stimulating Hormone or Thyrotropin); ACTH (Adrenocorticotropic Hormone); GH (Growth Hormone)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"299","question":"Name ONE hormone produced by the pituitary gland.","answer":"Anterior pituitary—Prolactin, FSH, LH, Growth Hormone, TSH, ACTH; posterior pituitary—Oxytocin and Vasopressin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"300","question":"What is the major function of the thyroid gland?","answer":"Controls metabolic rate [FYI:  Thyroid also helps with protein synthesis and regulation of calcium (through the hormone calcitonin).]"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"301","question":"What gland controls the metabolic rate?","answer":"Thyroid gland"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"302","question":"The cornea, sclera, choroid, iris, and retina are all parts of what?","answer":"Eye"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"303","question":"What is the name of the substance contained in the anterior chamber of the eye?","answer":"Aqueous humor"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"304","question":"What is the fluid-filled space between the iris and the cornea?","answer":"Anterior chamber (FYI: The anterior chamber contains aqueous humor.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"novice","number":"305","question":"What is the usual color of the horse's eye?","answer":"Brown"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"306","question":"In a wall-eyed horse, which specific structure of the eye is light blue or hazel in color?","answer":"Iris"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"307","question":"In a horse, what is a \"glass eye\"?","answer":"When the iris of the eye is clear, white, or blue"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"308","question":"What is the term for a horse whose iris is a light color?","answer":"Glass eye, wall eye, or watch eye (accept any)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"309","question":"Give 3 meanings of the term \"wall eye\" in references to horses.","answer":"Light blue or hazel eye; defective eye; white spot over the eye area"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"310","question":"What does the term \"watch eye\" mean?","answer":"Glass eye (iris is clear or blue)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"311","question":"What term refers both to white on the face covering the eye area or to one defective eye?","answer":"Wall eyed"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"312","question":"What does the term \"watch eye\" mean?","answer":"Eye (iris) is clear, white or blue."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"313","question":"Describe a \"glass eye\" in a horse.","answer":"Eye (iris) is clear, white or blue."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"314","question":"What is the term for the membrane that lines the inside of the eyelid?","answer":"Conjunctiva"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"315","question":"What is the FIRST structure that light entering the horse's eye would pass through?","answer":"Cornea"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"316","question":"What is the name for the outer protective layer of the horse's eye?","answer":"Cornea"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"317","question":"When fluorescein dye is applied to the surface of the eye, it will indicate any damaged areas of what structure of the eye?","answer":"Cornea"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"318","question":"What part of the eyeball allows light to pass through to the lens?","answer":"Cornea (also accept pupil)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"319","question":"Name TWO clear or translucent structures that light must pass through to reach the retina in the horse's eye.","answer":"Cornea and lens"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"320","question":"What structure is the FIRST protection for the horse's eye?","answer":"Eyelid (also accept eyelashes)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"321","question":"This membrane in front of the eye removes foreign bodies.  Give ONE other term for the horse’s third eyelid.","answer":"Haw or nictitating membrane"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"322","question":"Give ONE function of a horse's third eyelid.","answer":"Cleans the eye; removes foreign bodies; prevents foreign bodies from getting into the eye; protects the eye from trauma; keeps the eye moist (by spreading the tear film over the eye)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"323","question":"What is the COMMON name for the membrane that helps remove foreign materials from the eye?   It's also called the third eyelid or nictitating membrane.","answer":"Haw"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"324","question":"In connection with the eye, what does the term \"haw\" mean?","answer":"Third eyelid or nictitating membrane"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"325","question":"Give TWO purposes of the nictitating membrane.","answer":"Cleans the eye; removes foreign bodies; prevents foreign bodies from getting into the eye; protects the eye from trauma; keeps the eye moist (by spreading the tear film over the eye)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"326","question":"The horse's eye is lubricated or moistened by what fluid?","answer":"Tears or lacrimal fluid (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"327","question":"The tear film is necessary for the health of the cornea.  Name TWO things the tear film does for the cornea.","answer":"Supplies nutrition, moisture, and oxygen to the cornea"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"328","question":"What gland secretes tears?","answer":"Lacrimal gland"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"329","question":"What is the COMMON term for the fluid that's produced by the lacrimal glands, collects in the medial canthus, and flows down the nasolacrimal duct?","answer":"Tears (FYI:  Medical term is lacrimal fluid.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"330","question":"In the horse's eye, focused light rays which form the image on the retina are transmitted to the brain by what nerve?","answer":"Optic nerve (2nd cranial nerve)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"331","question":"Research indicates that horses do see in color.  However, they may have more difficulty seeing which color?","answer":"Red"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"332","question":"2 part question:  In the horse's eye, there are TWO main photoreceptor cell types.  What are they called and what type of vision is each used for?","answer":"Rods are used for low light vision and motion detection; cones are used for day and color vision."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"333","question":"In the horse's eye, there are cells known as rods and cones.  Which of these is responsible for day and color vision?","answer":"Cones"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"334","question":"In the horse's eye, there are cells known as rods and cones.  Which of these is responsible for low light vision and motion detection?","answer":"Rods"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"335","question":"What is the term for the opening in the iris of a horse's eye?","answer":"Pupil"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"336","question":"2 part question:  How is the shape of the horse's pupil different in comparison to other mammals and how does the shape of the pupil benefit the horse?","answer":"Pupil is more horizontal; enables the horse to see predators more easily (by increasing their visual field)."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"337","question":"The lens focuses the light rays to form an image on what structure?","answer":"Retina"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"338","question":"The body of an adult horse is approximately what percent water?","answer":"60% - 75% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"339","question":"Name 3 of the horse's body fluids.","answer":"Feces, urine, tears, sweat, saliva, blood"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"340","question":"Name 3 functions of the horse's skin.","answer":"Protection; sensation; thermoregulation; controls water loss; absorption (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"341","question":"The integumentary system refers to what part of the body?","answer":"Skin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"342","question":"What do a horse's chestnuts and a human's fingerprints have in common?","answer":"Both have unique patterns that can be used to identify individuals"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"343","question":"What is a common name for a horny growth on the inside of the legs, sometimes referred to as night eyes?  It's also a term used to describe a coat color.","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"344","question":"Night eyes are another name for what structures on the horse?","answer":"Chestnuts"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"345","question":"Being specific, where are chestnuts located on a horse?","answer":"Front legs— inside surface above the knees; hind legs—inside surface at the bottom of the hocks"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"346","question":"What is another name for the chestnuts on a horse’s leg?","answer":"Night eyes"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"347","question":"The horny growths on the insides of horses' legs are called what?","answer":"Chestnuts or night eyes"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"348","question":"What part of the horse has a distinctive pattern that can be used to positively identify a particular horse?","answer":"Chestnuts"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"349","question":"2 part question:  How many chestnuts do donkeys have and where are they located?","answer":"2 (two); on the insides of the front legs only"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"350","question":"What are chestnuts?","answer":"Horny growths on the inside of a horse's legs (above the knees and at the lower part of the hocks)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"351","question":"What is the name of the structural protein in the extracellular space of connective tissues that forms the basic framework of body tissues and gives the skin elasticity?","answer":"Collagen"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"352","question":"What is the term for the horny growth found at the back of the fetlock?","answer":"Ergot"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"353","question":"What is an ergot?","answer":"Horny growth behind the fetlock joint"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"354","question":"What is the name of the layers of loose, dense fibrous connective tissue that's found superficially under the skin and deep covering the muscles?","answer":"Fascia"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"355","question":"Name 3 areas of the horse's skin that are NOT covered with hair.","answer":"Underneath tail; inside of thighs; around genitals; udder"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"356","question":"Why do horses have hair in their ears?","answer":"To prevent dirt or insects from entering the ears"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"357","question":"What causes horses to grow their winter coat?","answer":"Shorter length of daylight"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"358","question":"How does a horse's coat keep him warm in the winter?","answer":"Traps heat between the hair fibers"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"359","question":"Name TWO areas of hair on the horse that do NOT shed.","answer":"Mane, tail, eyelashes, tactile hairs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"360","question":"2 part question:  For a horse, what is the first line of defense against the cold and what is the second line of defense?","answer":"First line of defense is the hair coat; second line of defense if fat (which provides insulation)."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"361","question":"Name ONE part of the horse where cowlicks or whorls occur.","answer":"Face, head, neck, throatlatch, flank"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"362","question":"2 part question:  What are guard hairs and where are they commonly found?","answer":"Long, individual hairs that often mix with the dense undercoat of the horse; usually seen on the underside of the belly, underside of the jaw and neck, or between the cheeks of the buttocks (accept any location)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"363","question":"What is the name for the long, individual hairs that often mix with the dense undercoat of the horse, especially under the belly?","answer":"Guard hairs or cat hairs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"364","question":"What are the coarse, feeler hairs that protrude from around the nostrils, lips, and eyelids?","answer":"Tactile hairs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"365","question":"What are tactile hairs?","answer":"Coarse \"feeler\" hairs around the muzzle and eyes"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"366","question":"Name TWO locations on the horse where you would find tactile hairs.","answer":"Around the eyes, nostrils, lips, muzzle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"367","question":"What is the purpose of the long feeler hairs around the muzzle?","answer":"Help the horse make contact with its surroundings (especially in the dark) [FYI:  The long “feeler” hairs are called tactile hairs.]"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"368","question":"What is a tufted tail?","answer":"Tail that has short hair (somewhat like a cow) towards the top with a tuft of longer hair beginning about halfway down the tail"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"369","question":"What are the TWO layers of the horse's skin?","answer":"Epidermis and dermis"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"370","question":"What is the outermost layer of skin?","answer":"Epidermis"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"371","question":"The mucous membranes are evaluated as part of the vital signs of the horse.  Name 4 places you can find them.","answer":"Inner surface of eyelids; inside nostrils; inner surface of lips; gums; inner surface of vulva; inner surface of rectum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"372","question":"2 part question:  Describe the location and function of the sebaceous glands.","answer":"Located at the base of the hair follicles; produce sebum (which is an oily, waxy substance that protects and insulates the skin)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"373","question":"Where are each of the 3 following serous membranes found in the horse:  pleura, peritoneum, pericardium?","answer":"Pleura covers the lungs and lines the thoracic cavity; peritoneum covers the abdominal organs and lines the abdominal cavity; and pericardium is the outer lining of the heart."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"374","question":"Name 3 areas of the horse's body that readily sweats.","answer":"Base of the ears, chest, neck, flank (Do NOT accept back.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"375","question":"Where on the horse are there NO sweat glands?","answer":"Legs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"376","question":"What is the COMMON name for the apocrine tubular glands of the horse?","answer":"Sweat glands"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"377","question":"What organ in the thoracic cavity that produces lymphocytes is at its largest in the 6 - 8 week old foal and decreases in size with age becoming difficult to find in older horses?","answer":"Thymus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"378","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse's body that belong to the immune system.","answer":"Lymph nodes; lymph vessels; spleen; bone marrow; thymus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"379","question":"What are the filters found in the horse's body that remove bacteria, cancer cells, and foreign materials from circulation?  They are connected to the vascular system by the thoracic duct.","answer":"Lymph nodes"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"jr bonus","number":"380","question":"Name 3 of the horse's body systems.","answer":"Skeletal, muscular, respiratory, circulatory (cardiovascular), digestive, reproductive, nervous, endocrine, integumentary (skin), urinary, lymphatic"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"381","question":"What does the term \"viscera\" describe?","answer":"Internal organs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"382","question":"What is the largest TISSUE MASS in a horse’s body?","answer":"Muscles"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"383","question":"During exercise, body heat is primarily produced by what system?","answer":"Muscular system"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"384","question":"What provides the energy for muscle contraction?","answer":"ATP (adenosine triphosphate)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"385","question":"When a horse’s muscle shortens, is the muscle contracting or relaxing?","answer":"Contracting"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"386","question":"When a horse’s muscle lengthens, is the muscle contracting or relaxing?","answer":"Relaxing"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"387","question":"What is the basic contractile unit of skeletal muscles?","answer":"Sarcomere"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"388","question":"What is the name of the muscles located between the ribs that are involved in respiration?","answer":"Intercostal muscles"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"389","question":"Which TWO muscles expand the chest during breathing?","answer":"Diaphragm and intercostal muscles"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"390","question":"Where are the intercostal muscles located?","answer":"Between the ribs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"391","question":"What is the name of the widest muscle in the horse's body?","answer":"Latissimus dorsi (FYI: Longissimus dorsi is the longest muscle.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"392","question":"2 part question:  Name and give the function of the large muscle located on either side of the face that sits beneath the ears and covers the mandible.","answer":"Masseter muscle; used for chewing (opens and closes the jaw)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"393","question":"2 part question:  Where is the panniculus muscle and what is its function?","answer":"Muscle under the skin; enables the horse to flick flies off its skin."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"394","question":"What muscle lies under the horse's skin and enables the skin to twitch and shake flies off the body?","answer":"Panniculus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"395","question":"Where is the trapezius muscle located in the horse?","answer":"On each side of the withers"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"396","question":"Muscles that work together to accomplish a movement are called synergists.  What is the term for muscles that oppose each other and limit movement?","answer":"Antagonists"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"397","question":"Why is it difficult for cuts and bruises below the knees or hocks to heal?","answer":"There are no muscles below the knees and hocks; therefore, the blood supply is limited."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"398","question":"The muscles that control leg movement end where?","answer":"At the knees and hocks"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"399","question":"Muscles are attached to bones by what?","answer":"Tendons"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"400","question":"The forces exerted by muscles in the foreleg are transmitted by tendons.  Generally, muscles are NOT found below what joint of the foreleg?","answer":"Knee (carpus)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"401","question":"What controls cannon, pastern, and foot actions?","answer":"Tendons (also accept ligaments)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"402","question":"What is the purpose of the extensor tendon?","answer":"Extends (or straightens) the hoof and leg"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"403","question":"What tendon is responsible for the extension of the horse's toe and hoof?","answer":"Digital extensor tendon (extensor tendon)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"404","question":"What is the purpose of the deep digital flexor tendon?","answer":"Flexes (or bends) the hoof and leg"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"405","question":"What tendon connects the deep muscles of the back of the leg to the coffin bone?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon (also accept deep flexor tendon)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"406","question":"The navicular bone and bursa are associated with which tendon?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon (also accept deep flexor tendon)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"407","question":"Name the 3 types of muscles found in a horse's body.","answer":"Smooth, cardiac, and skeletal"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"408","question":"Name the 4 types of skeletal muscles.","answer":"Type 1, Type 2A, Type 2B, Type 2C"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"409","question":"Give 3 characteristics of Type I skeletal muscle fibers.","answer":"Slow twitch; low glycolytic activity; provide endurance"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"410","question":"Which type of skeletal muscle is used for long-term, non-strenuous work and provides endurance?","answer":"Type 1 or slow twitch (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"411","question":"Type 2B muscles are used for what?","answer":"Quick bursts of speed for short distances"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"412","question":"2 part question:  Name the 3 subtypes of type 2 muscle fibers and explain their uses.","answer":"Type 2A—speed at long or intermediate distances; Type 2B—quick bursts of speed for short distances; Type 2C—training can recruit them to either type 2A or type 2B"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"413","question":"Which type of skeletal muscle is fast twitch and fatigues easily?","answer":"Type 2"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"414","question":"Which breed has the largest number of type 2A muscles, Arabian, Thoroughbred, or Quarter Horse?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"415","question":"Name 3 systems in the horse's body that use smooth muscles.","answer":"Digestive, circulatory or cardiovascular, respiratory, reproductive, urinary"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"416","question":"Are skeletal muscles voluntary or involuntary?","answer":"Voluntary"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"417","question":"2 part question:  The muscles of a horse's body are classified as smooth, cardiac, and skeletal.  Which are voluntary and which are involuntary?","answer":"Skeletal muscles are voluntary; smooth and cardiac muscles are involuntary."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"418","question":"Name 3 places in the horse's body where you will find involuntary muscle action.","answer":"Digestive system, respiratory system, circulatory system, urinary system, reproductive system"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"419","question":"What system in the horse's body includes the brain, spinal cord, and nerves?","answer":"Nervous system"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"420","question":"What 3 items make up the central nervous system?","answer":"Brain, brain stem, and spinal cord"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"421","question":"What part of the brain controls basic body functions such as respiration and heart rate?","answer":"Brain stem (also accept medulla oblongata)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"422","question":"Which part of the brain controls the coordination of movement?","answer":"Cerebellum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"423","question":"Where is the hypothalamus located?","answer":"Base of the brain"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"424","question":"Where is the pituitary gland located?","answer":"Base of the brain"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"425","question":"The central nervous system consists of the brain and the spinal cord.  What does the peripheral nervous system consist of?","answer":"Nerves that branch off the brain and spinal cord (such as cranial, spinal, and peripheral nerves)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"426","question":"The autonomic nervous system regulates many of the internal operations of the body and also regulates unconscious responses to external stimuli.  What are the TWO divisions of the autonomic nervous system?","answer":"Sympathetic and parasympathetic (FYI: Sympathetic is the fight or flight part and parasympathetic is the breed and feed part.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"427","question":"Would the parasympathetic or sympathetic nervous system be stimulated with the fight or flight instinct?","answer":"Sympathetic nervous system"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"428","question":"To what structure does the 12th cranial nerve, the hypoglossal nerve, provide motor control?","answer":"Tongue"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"429","question":"What cranial nerve provides the horse with a sense of smell?","answer":"Olfactory nerve (1st cranial nerve)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"430","question":"Name 3 cranial nerves.","answer":"Olfactory, optic, oculomotor, trochlear, trigeminal, abducens, facial, vestibulocochlear, glossopharyngeal, vagus, accessory, hypoglossal"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"431","question":"What is the name of the largest nerve in the horse's body?","answer":"Sciatic nerve"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"432","question":"What type of nerves brings sensations of pressure, pain, heat, and cold from the nerve endings?","answer":"Sensory nerves"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"433","question":"How many pairs of spinal nerves does a horse have?","answer":"22 pairs of spinal nerves"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"434","question":"The nose, ears, and eyes are referred to as what type of organs?","answer":"Specialized sensory organs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"435","question":"Name the 3 primary specialized sensory organs of the horse's nervous system.","answer":"Eyes, ears, and nose"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"436","question":"The sense of taste in the horse is similar to that of humans.  What 4 tastes is the horse capable of sensing?","answer":"Bitter, sweet, sour, salty"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"437","question":"What is the name of the tiny air sacs in the lungs where oxygen and carbon dioxide are exchanged?","answer":"Alveoli (al-VEE-oh-lie)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"438","question":"Which muscle has the LARGEST increase in blood flow during exercise?","answer":"Diaphragm"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"439","question":"What is the name of the muscle that separates the abdominal and thoracic cavities?","answer":"Diaphragm"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"440","question":"What is the function of the epiglottis?","answer":"Prevents food or water from entering the respiratory system (larynx and trachea)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"441","question":"What is the name of the cartilaginous flap that prevents food or water from entering the larynx?","answer":"Epiglottis"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"442","question":"What structure equalizes air pressure in the ear?","answer":"Eustachian tube (you-STAY-shun)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"443","question":"In the gallop, when does the horse exhale?","answer":"When the front legs touch the ground"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"444","question":"Give ONE secondary purpose of the respiratory system.","answer":"Temperature regulation; phonation or vocalization"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"445","question":"What is the primary purpose of the respiratory system?","answer":"To oxygenate blood"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"446","question":"The primary function of the respiratory system is to oxygenate the blood.  What are the TWO secondary functions?","answer":"Temperature regulation; phonation or vocalization"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"447","question":"Name ONE gas that is exhaled when breathing.","answer":"Carbon dioxide, oxygen, nitrogen"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"448","question":"What anatomical structure of the horse is described as a diverticulum of the auditory tube?","answer":"Guttural pouch"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"449","question":"Name 3 functions of the larynx.","answer":"Controls air flow; protects the airway; phonation (vocalization)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"450","question":"Why can’t a horse breath through its mouth?","answer":"Blocking action of the soft palate"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"451","question":"What is an obligate nasal breather?","answer":"Animal that breathes only through the nose (animal that can't breathe through the mouth)."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"452","question":"Why is it important for a horse to have large nostrils?","answer":"So it can breathe better (to allow for maximum intake of air)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"453","question":"Explain how the pharynx functions with the RESPIRATORY tract.","answer":"Connects the nasal passages to the trachea or windpipe"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"454","question":"What is another name for the respiratory rate?","answer":"Respiratory frequency"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"455","question":"What is respiratory frequency?","answer":"Number of breaths taken per minute"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"456","question":"At a gallop, respiration rate and stride rate are almost always coupled in what ratio?","answer":"1 : 1 (one to one)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"457","question":"What is the COMMON name for the trachea?","answer":"Windpipe"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"458","question":"What is the medical name for the windpipe?","answer":"Trachea"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"459","question":"What is the term for the amount of air inspired in one minute?","answer":"Minute volume"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"460","question":"If the horse increases its movement, does the minute volume go up or down?","answer":"Up (FYI: Minute volume is the amount of air inspired in one minute; minute volume = tidal volume x respiratory rate.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"461","question":"In measuring respiratory capabilities of the horse, tidal volume and respiratory rate are used to determine what respiratory parameter?","answer":"Minute volume (FYI:  Minute volume is the total amount of air inspired or expired in one minute.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"462","question":"What is the term for the total amount of air inspired in one breath?","answer":"Tidal volume"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"463","question":"What is the name of the structure that protects the vital organs?","answer":"Skeleton"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"464","question":"Name TWO components of the skeletal system.","answer":"Bones; cartilage; ligaments (also accept tendons which are part of the musculoskeletal system)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"465","question":"Name 3 functions of a horse's skeleton.","answer":"Provides framework; protects internal organs; locomotion or movement; stores minerals; produces blood cells (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"466","question":"How many bones are in the horse's body?","answer":"205 (FYI:  There are 54 bones in the spine, 36 ribs, 34 bones in the skull, 80 bones in the legs, and 1 sternal or breast bone.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"467","question":"What is the anatomical name for a natural passageway or opening in the body that blood vessels and nerves pass through?","answer":"Foramen (fore-AY-men)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"468","question":"2 part question:  What do the terms fossa and tuberosity mean when used to describe bones?","answer":"Fossa is a hollow or depressed area; tuberosity is a prominence or projection."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"469","question":"Name ONE place in the horse's skeleton where an interosseous ligament is found.","answer":"Between the radius and ulna; between the cannon and splint bones"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"470","question":"What does interosseous mean? (in-ter-AH-see-us)","answer":"Between bones"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"471","question":"What are osteoblasts?","answer":"Bone forming cells"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"472","question":"Osteoblasts form a protein matrix that ultimately forms what tissue?","answer":"Bone"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"473","question":"What structure begins the healing process when a bone fracture occurs?","answer":"Periosteum (pair-ih-AHS-tee-um)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"474","question":"What is the name of the membrane that covers non-articulating surfaces of bone?","answer":"Periosteum (pair-ih-AHS-tee-um)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"475","question":"2 part question:  What is the periosteum and what does it do?","answer":"Bone-producing membrane that covers the bones except at the ends; it protects the bone and is a site of healing."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"476","question":"Name 3 classifications of bones.","answer":"Long, short, flat, irregular, sesamoid"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"477","question":"Which type bones enclose the body cavities containing vital organs and also provide large areas for muscle attachment?","answer":"Flat bones (FYI:  Examples are ribs, sternum, scapula, skull bones, and pelvic bones.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"478","question":"What classification of bone protects the spinal cord?","answer":"Irregular bones"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"479","question":"2 part question:  Where are the irregular bones located in the horse's skeleton and what is their purpose?","answer":"Spinal column; protect the spinal cord"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"480","question":"What is the diaphysis of a long bone? (die-AA-fiss-siss)","answer":"Shaft"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"481","question":"What is the COMMON name for the epiphyseal plates? (eh-pih-FISS-ee-al)","answer":"Growth plates"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"482","question":"Where on a long bone would you NOT find the periosteum? (pair-ee-AH-stee-um)","answer":"At the ends, points of articulation, or epiphyses (accept any)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"483","question":"Give ONE purpose of the long bones in the horse's body.","answer":"Act as levers; support weight; provide locomotion; store minerals; (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"484","question":"At what age do the epiphyseal plates on the distal end of the cannon bones close? (eh-pih-FISS-ee-al)","answer":"9 - 12 months (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"485","question":"2 part question:  Where are the short bones located and what is their main purpose?","answer":"In complex joints such as the knee and hock; shock absorption"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"486","question":"What 3 bony structures form the thoracic cavity?","answer":"Spine (vertebrae), ribs, and sternum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"487","question":"How many ribs does a Percheron have?","answer":"36 or 18 pairs (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"488","question":"What is the difference between true and false ribs?","answer":"True ribs connect to the sternum (by costal cartilages); false or floating ribs do NOT connect directly to the sternum. (FYI: False ribs connect to each other through the costal arch.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"489","question":"The head of each rib of a horse is attached to what structure?","answer":"Vertebrae (specifically thoracic vertebrae)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"490","question":"How many PAIRS of ribs does a horse have?","answer":"18 pairs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"491","question":"What is the term for the ribs that do NOT connect directly to the sternum?","answer":"Floating ribs or false ribs (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"492","question":"What is the general term for the last 10 pairs of ribs—those that are NOT connected to the sternum?","answer":"False ribs or floating ribs (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"493","question":"The costal cartilages of the first 8 ribs articulate with what bony structure?","answer":"Sternum"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"494","question":"What 3 body systems do the true ribs protect?","answer":"Respiratory, circulatory, and digestive"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"495","question":"Which pairs of ribs are fastened to the sternum by cartilage and are called \"true ribs\"?","answer":"First 8 pairs of ribs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"496","question":"Where are the manubrium and xiphoid process found in the horse's body? (man-OOH-bree-um) (ZIE-foid)","answer":"Sternum (FYI: They are cartilaginous attachments to the sternum.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"497","question":"Where on the horse is the sternum?","answer":"Chest (FYI: The sternum is the breast bone.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"498","question":"How many bones are in the sternum?","answer":"1 (one) (FYI: Manubrium and xyphoid are cartilaginous attachments.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"499","question":"What is the structural basis for the ears and nostrils?","answer":"Cartilage"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"500","question":"Where is the horse's occipital crest located?","answer":"Poll area (top of the head between the ears)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"501","question":"How many bones are in the skull?","answer":"34 bones in the skull"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"502","question":"Name 3 bones found in the horse’s head.","answer":"Premaxilla or incisive; nasal; maxilla; mandible; frontal; temporal; parietal; occipital; zygomatic; pterygoid; presphenoid; vomar; palatine; hyoid; lacrimal; palatine; sphenoid; turbinates; malleus (hammer); incus (anvil); stapes (stirrup)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"503","question":"Name the 3 passages of the facial portion of the skull.","answer":"Orbital, nasal, and oral"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"504","question":"What bony structure separates the oral cavity from the nasal cavity?","answer":"Hard palate"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"505","question":"Name ONE of the structures that the hyoid bone supports.","answer":"Larynx; base of tongue; guttural pouches; pharynx (FYI: Guttural pouches are diverticula of the auditory tube and are present only in some animals such as equines.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"506","question":"What is the correct term for the lower jawbone?","answer":"Mandible"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"507","question":"What is the largest bone in the horse's head?","answer":"Mandible or lower jaw (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"508","question":"What is the mandible?","answer":"Lower jawbone"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"509","question":"What is the name of the upper jawbone?","answer":"Maxilla"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"510","question":"What is the orbital cavity?","answer":"Bony socket that surrounds and protects the eye"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"511","question":"In the skull, what is protected by the orbital cavity?","answer":"Eyes"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"512","question":"What is the name of the bony socket that surrounds and protects the eye?","answer":"Orbital cavity"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"513","question":"How many turbinates are in each nasal cavity?","answer":"2 (two) (FYI: Turbinate bones warm and filter the air.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"514","question":"2 part question: Where are the turbinate bones and what is their purpose?","answer":"Bones in the nasal passages; they filter and warm inspired air."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"515","question":"Which TWO joints in the hind leg have reciprocal action?","answer":"Stifle and hock"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"516","question":"What is the term for an area where two or more bones meet?","answer":"Joint"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"517","question":"What does the prefix “arthro” mean?","answer":"Joint"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"518","question":"2 part question:  Which leg joint is subjected to the GREATEST strain and why?","answer":"Fetlock; it may support the full weight of the horse during certain gaits or movements such as jumping"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"519","question":"What is the COMMON name for the coxofemoral joint?","answer":"Hip joint"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"520","question":"Which joint of the horse is similar to the human ankle?","answer":"Hock or tarsus (FYI: The pointy part of the hock is the calcaneus which is our heel bone.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"521","question":"What is the hardest working joint in the horse's legs?","answer":"Hock"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"522","question":"What is the LEAST moveable joint in the horse’s leg?","answer":"Pastern"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"523","question":"What joint of the horse is like the human knee?","answer":"Stifle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"524","question":"What is the largest joint in the horse?","answer":"Stifle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"525","question":"What is the joint between the femur and the tibia?","answer":"Stifle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"526","question":"In what joint would you find a fibro-cartilage structure called a meniscus that's located between the articulating surfaces of that joint?","answer":"Stifle"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"527","question":"What is the purpose of synovial fluid?","answer":"To lubricate joints"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"528","question":"What is the name of the fluid that fills the sheaths around tendons and lines the inside of joints?","answer":"Synovial fluid"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"529","question":"Synovial joints are classified on the basis of the type of motion.  Name 3 types of synovial joints.","answer":"Ball and socket; hinge; pivot; ellipsoid; sliding or gliding"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"530","question":"What kind of joint is the horse's elbow?","answer":"Hinge joint"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"531","question":"Name TWO of the bones in the fetlock joint.","answer":"Cannon, long pastern, and two proximal sesamoid bones"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"532","question":"What 4 bones make up the fetlock joint?","answer":"Cannon, long pastern, and two proximal sesamoid bones"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"533","question":"What are the 3 main bones of the foot?","answer":"Coffin, navicular, and short pastern"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"int bonus","number":"534","question":"Name 3 bones of the lower leg below the knee or hock.","answer":"Cannon, splint, long pastern, short pastern, coffin, navicular or distal sesamoid, proximal sesamoids"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"535","question":"What are the COMMON names of the 3 phalanx bones?","answer":"Long pastern (1st or proximal phalanx), short pastern (2nd or middle phalanx), and coffin (3rd or distal phalanx)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"536","question":"From proximal to distal, name the 3 joints of the horse's leg that are common to all 4 legs.","answer":"Fetlock, pastern, and coffin"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"537","question":"What TWO sets of bones serve as pulleys to change the direction of the deep digital flexor tendon?","answer":"Proximal sesamoids and distal sesamoid (navicular)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"538","question":"The cannon, long pastern, and proximal sesamoid bones make up what joint?","answer":"Fetlock or ankle (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"539","question":"How many bones form the basis of locomotion in the horse?","answer":"80 bones (20 bones in each leg)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"540","question":"The first phalanx is just below what long bone?","answer":"Cannon bone (3rd metacarpal or 3rd metatarsal)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"541","question":"What bone is located at the lowest point in the hoof?","answer":"Coffin bone (also called pedal bone, distal phalanx, or 3rd phalanx)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"542","question":"Where is the coffin bone?","answer":"In the foot (lowest bone in the foot)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"543","question":"The rear third of the coffin bones does not attach directly to the hoof wall.  What elastic structures are the bridges for this attachment?","answer":"Lateral cartilages"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"544","question":"What is the anatomical term for the coffin joint?","answer":"Distal interphalangeal joint (DIP joint) (en-ter-fay-LAN-gee-al)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"545","question":"Where are the lateral cartilages located?","answer":"On the sides or wings of the coffin bone"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"546","question":"Identify this bone:  This bone is very porous.  Blood vessels pass in and out of the pores.  Lateral cartilages are attached to the wings of this bone.","answer":"Coffin bone (also called pedal bone, 3rd phalanx, or distal phalanx)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"547","question":"What COMMON name is given to the 3rd phalanx bone of the foot?","answer":"Coffin bone (also accept pedal bone)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"548","question":"What bone is located between the cannon bone and the short pastern?","answer":"Long pastern (1st or proximal phalanx)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"549","question":"Which bone of the horse's foot serves as a pulley for the deep digital flexor tendon?","answer":"Navicular bone (also called distal sesamoid or shuttle bone)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"550","question":"Where in the foot is the navicular bone located?","answer":"Behind the coffin bone or behind and below the short pastern (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"551","question":"What is another name for the distal sesamoid bone?","answer":"Navicular bone (also called shuttle bone)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"552","question":"Describe ONE function of the distal sesamoid or navicular bone.","answer":"Protects the coffin; provides a bearing surface or support for the deep digital flexor tendon"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"553","question":"What TWO bones articulate with the distal sesamoid bone?","answer":"Short pastern and coffin bone"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"554","question":"Where are the proximal sesamoid bones located?","answer":"At the rear of fetlock joint (FYI:  The distal sesamoid or navicular bone is in the hoof.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"555","question":"In today's modern Equus, vestiges are still present of the two outside toes that disappeared from the prehistoric horse Mesohippus. What are these vestiges called?","answer":"Splint bones (also accept chestnuts and ergots)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"556","question":"What is the COMMON name of the largest metacarpal?","answer":"Cannon bone (3rd metacarpal) (FYI: Splint bones are the 2nd and 4th metacarpals.  MetaCARPALS are on the front legs and metaTARSALS are on the hind legs.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"557","question":"What is the proper anatomical name for the bones between the horse's knee and fetlock?","answer":"Metacarpal bones (FYI: Cannon is the 3rd metacarpal; splint bones are the 2nd and 4th metacarpals.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"558","question":"2 part question:  How many carpal bones are there in the knee and how are they arranged?","answer":"8 carpal bones; arranged in 2 rows"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"559","question":"What is anatomical term for the horse's knee?","answer":"Carpus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"560","question":"The elbow joint in the horse is the articulation site of what 3 bones?","answer":"Ulna, radius, and humerus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"561","question":"2 part question:  If the horse has a fracture of the olecranon, what bone and joint would be involved?","answer":"Bone is the ulna; joint is the elbow."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"562","question":"The radius and ulna comprise what structure of the horse?","answer":"Forearm"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"563","question":"2 part question:  How many bones comprise the forearm and what are their names?","answer":"2 (two) bones; radius and ulna"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"564","question":"What is the MAIN bone of the forearm?","answer":"Radius"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"565","question":"What is unique about the horse's ulna?","answer":"Ulna has no bone marrow cavity."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"566","question":"What bone extends from the shoulder to the elbow?","answer":"Humerus"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"567","question":"What is another name for the scapula?","answer":"Shoulder blade"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"568","question":"What is another name for the horse's shoulder blade?","answer":"Scapula"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"569","question":"Name 4 of the bones in the horse's hind leg from the stifle distally.","answer":"Tibia; fibula; tarsal bones; cannon; splint bones; long pastern; short pastern; coffin bone; navicular bone or distal sesamoid; proximal sesamoids"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"570","question":"Name the 4 bones that form the stifle joint.","answer":"Femur, patella, tibia, and fibula"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"571","question":"What is the anatomical name for the bone that forms the point of the hock?","answer":"Calcaneus (cal-CANE-ee-us)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"572","question":"What is the anatomical term for the HIND cannon bone?","answer":"3rd or large metaTARSAL (Do NOT accept metaCARPAL which is on the front leg.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"573","question":"What is the heaviest and strongest bone in the horse's body?","answer":"Femur"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"574","question":"What is the SPECIFIC location of the metatarsophalangeal joint?","answer":"HIND fetlock or ankle (Must specify hind.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"575","question":"What is the COMMON term for the tuber coxae?","answer":"Hip"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"576","question":"Which bone in the horse is similar to the human kneecap?","answer":"Patella (of the stifle joint)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"577","question":"What is the triangular sesamoid bone that's situated at the front of the stifle?","answer":"Patella"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"578","question":"What is the track-like structure on which the patella rides?","answer":"Trochlea"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"579","question":"In the hind legs, what is the anatomical term for the short pastern bone?","answer":"Middle phalanx or 2nd phalanx (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"580","question":"What is the MAIN bone between the stifle and hock?","answer":"Tibia"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"581","question":"What does the prefix “desmo” mean?","answer":"Ligament"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"582","question":"In the horse's body, what connects bones to bones?","answer":"Ligaments"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"583","question":"Why do injuries to ligaments heal slowly?","answer":"Ligaments have limited blood supplies."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"584","question":"What is the difference between ligaments and tendons?","answer":"Ligaments connect bones to bones; tendons connect muscles to bones.  (FYI:  Ligaments also connect bones to cartilage, connect cartilage to cartilage, and help hold joints together.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"585","question":"2 part question:  What is the stay mechanism and what is its purpose?","answer":"Locking mechanism of the joints of the legs (by muscles and ligaments); allows the horse to sleep standing up; also prevents over-extension and decreases concussion of the legs"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"586","question":"Why can a horse rest standing up?","answer":"Stay apparatus (locking mechanism of the legs)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"587","question":"Name ONE function of the stay apparatus.","answer":"Locks the horse’s legs so the horse can sleep standing up; prevents overextension; reduces concussion"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"588","question":"The stay apparatus is a mechanism that enables the horse to do what?","answer":"Sleep standing up (FYI: Stay apparatus also locks the legs, prevents overextension, and reduces concussion.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"589","question":"What is the primary function of the suspensory ligament?","answer":"Prevent overextension of the fetlock joint (FYI: Suspensory ligament starts at the upper back of the cannon, splits, and inserts on the proximal sesamoid bones behind the fetlock.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"590","question":"What is the largest ligament in the leg?","answer":"Suspensory ligament (FYI: Suspensory ligament starts at the upper back of the cannon, splits, and inserts on the proximal sesamoid bones behind the fetlock.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"591","question":"The ilium and ischium are two of the bones that make up what structure of the horse?","answer":"Pelvis (pelvic girdle)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"592","question":"Name 3 of the bones that make up the horse's pelvic girdle.","answer":"Ilium, ischium, pubis, sacrum, and caudal  or coccygeal vertebrae"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"593","question":"The os coxae of a horse is also known as what? (ahs COX-ee)","answer":"Pelvis (pelvic girdle)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"594","question":"Where are the ischium and pubis located?","answer":"Pelvis (pelvic girdle)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"595","question":"How many TOTAL vertebrae do horses have?","answer":"51 - 57 (accept any number within this range) [FYI: 7 cervical, 18 thoracic, 6 lumbar, 5 sacral, 15 - 21 (average is 18) coccygeal or caudal]"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"596","question":"Name 4 regions of the spinal column and give the number of vertebrae in each of those regions.","answer":"Cervical 7; thoracic 18; lumbar 6; sacrum 5; coccygeal or caudal 15 - 21 (average is 18)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"597","question":"2 part question:  What are the names and functions of the first and second vertebrae of the horse's spinal column?","answer":"Atlas—flexion and extension of the neck (up and down movement); axis—lateral movement of the neck (left and right movement)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"598","question":"What joint is commonly referred to as the yes-no joint?","answer":"Atlas-axis joint, atlantoaxial joint, or joint between the 1st and 2nd cervical vertebrae (accept any)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"599","question":"What are the first TWO cervical vertebrae called?","answer":"Atlas and axis"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"600","question":"How many cervical vertebrae does a horse have?","answer":"7 (seven)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"601","question":"What is the most flexible portion of the horse's spine?","answer":"Neck or cervical area (accept either)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"602","question":"Where are the cervical vertebrae located?","answer":"Neck (FYI: There are 7 cervical vertebrae.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"603","question":"Where in the spinal column are the coccygeal or caudal vertebrae?","answer":"Tail (FYI: There are 15 - 21 coccygeal or caudal vertebrae. The average is 18.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"604","question":"The coupling is the pivot point of the horse's back and is supported by which section of the horse's vertebrae?","answer":"Lumbar"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"605","question":"The terms transverse process, spinous process, foramen, and arch are used to describe which bones?","answer":"Vertebrae (spinal bones)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"606","question":"What term refers to the upper surface of the vertebrae?","answer":"Spinous process"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"607","question":"Which region of the spinal column is joined securely to the hipbone?","answer":"Sacrum (at the sacroiliac joint)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"608","question":"The increased height of the 3rd, 4th, and 5th thoracic vertebrae make up what part of the horse?","answer":"Withers"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"609","question":"Over which section of the vertebral column does most of the saddle sit?","answer":"Thoracic"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"610","question":"2 part question:  What directional term refers to a structure located closer to the head and what term refers to a structure closer to the tail?","answer":"Cranial means closer to the head; caudal means closer to the tail."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"611","question":"To what part of the horse's body does the term \"cranial\" refer?","answer":"Skull or head (FYI: The directional term cranial means towards the head.)"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"612","question":"2 part question:  Define the directional terms proximal and distal.","answer":"Proximal means closer to body; distal means furthest from body."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"613","question":"Describe the difference between adduction and abduction as it applies to the movement of the horse's limbs.","answer":"Adduction is movement toward the body; abduction is movement away from the body."},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"614","question":"In general, what does the prefix “cysto” refer to?","answer":"Bladder"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"615","question":"Name 4 parts of the urinary system.","answer":"Kidneys, ureters, bladder, urethra"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"sr bonus","number":"616","question":"Name 3 functions of the horse's kidneys.","answer":"Remove wastes; control water balance; control pH; control electrolyte levels; regulate blood pressure; hormone production; absorb minerals; regulate red blood cells"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"617","question":"What substance produced by the horse contains nitrogen, sulfur, inorganic salts, and pigments?","answer":"Urine"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"618","question":"What organ provides a blood filtering system that is responsible for the excretion of many waste products from the body?","answer":"Kidney"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"619","question":"In the horse's urinary system, what structure connects the kidney to the bladder?","answer":"Ureter"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"medium","number":"620","question":"When the bladder is full, urine is discharged through what?","answer":"Urethra"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"intermediate","number":"621","question":"What system is responsible for collecting and removing the fluid waste materials from the body?","answer":"Urinary system"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"easy","number":"622","question":"Where is urine stored in the horse?","answer":"Bladder"},
{"category":"Anatomy","level":"hard","number":"623","question":"2 part question:  How many times a day do horses urinate and how much urine do they produce?","answer":"5 - 7 times daily; produce from 4 - 7 quarts (accept any numbers within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"624","question":"Name ONE behavior that may happen when two strange horses stand nose to nose.","answer":"Striking, grunting, squealing, biting, nipping (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"int bonus","number":"625","question":"Give 3 ways to avoid aggressive behavior when group feeding horses.","answer":"Use separate feeders, ensure open space, space feeders far apart, use extra feeders (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"626","question":"Aggression is one of the most common behavioral problems in horses.  Name 3 aggressive behaviors.","answer":"Lunging, biting, kicking, crowding, striking, snapping, baring teeth, pinned ears, swishing tail (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"627","question":"When is a horse most apt to strike at another horse?","answer":"When in nose to nose contact with another horse"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"628","question":"What is the term for the \"boss mare\" or most dominant mare in a herd?","answer":"Alpha"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"629","question":"How is a pecking order established in a herd of horses?","answer":"Through aggression (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"630","question":"When the dominant horse in a group makes a threat, less aggressive horses will do what?","answer":"Retreat or get away (accept either)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"631","question":"Name ONE way a horse shows its dominant position within the herd.","answer":"Pinning ears, baring teeth, biting, turning rear toward other horse, kicking, threatening to kick, aggression (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"632","question":"Horses in a group are likely to run simply because another horse is running.  If the running is NOT in response to fright, what type of behavior is it?","answer":"Mimicry or allelomimetic behavior (accept either)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"633","question":"In herds, the mimicking of another horse's actions is called what?","answer":"Mimicry or allelomimetic behavior (accept either)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"634","question":"Give ONE name for the type of behavior when horses huddle together during inclement weather.","answer":"Contactual behavior; social behavior; herding"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"635","question":"How does a horse show that it's willing to cooperate with the trainer?","answer":"Lowers head, licks lips, and makes chewing motions (accept any)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"636","question":"When a horse lowers its head, licks, and makes chewing motions, it is showing what?","answer":"Cooperation or submission (accept either)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"637","question":"If a horse has the ability needed to work cattle, the horse is said to possess what?","answer":"Cow sense"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"638","question":"What does it mean if a horse is said to have \"a lot of cow\"?","answer":"Horse has mental abilities needed to work cattle (has cow sense)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"639","question":"What is epimeletic behavior?","answer":"Giving of care and attention between two horses  (FYI: Et-epimeletic behavior is when the foal asks for attention.)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"640","question":"What is the proper name of the behavior when a mare gives attention and care to her foal?","answer":"Epimeletic behavior (FYI: Et-epimeletic behavior is when the foal asks for attention.)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"641","question":"Name 3 fight or flight vices of the horse.","answer":"Lunging, bolting, aggression, biting, nipping, kicking, striking, exaggerated alarm reaction, balking, snapping, shying, startle reaction, crowding, rearing, charging"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"642","question":"What is a horse's primary defense?","answer":"Flight (running away)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"643","question":"The horse has TWO choices in response to fear.  What are they?","answer":"Fight or flight"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"644","question":"If a horse is afraid of something and is unable to run away from the source of fear, what two options does he have?","answer":"Flight or submission"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"645","question":"What prompts the horse's immediate instinct to kick or run?","answer":"Fear"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"646","question":"What does the horse's instinct tell it to do when afraid?","answer":"Kick or run (accept either)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"647","question":"The horse's first reaction to strange and frightening objects is to what?","answer":"Panic and/or run away"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"648","question":"Why do horses want to stay together and not leave other horses?","answer":"Herd instinct (Horses feel safer in groups.)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"649","question":"Horses have a very strong desire for the company of what?","answer":"Other horses (or animals)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"650","question":"What is \"ingestive behavior\"?","answer":"Any behavior associated with eating or drinking"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"651","question":"What does the term \"body language\" mean?","answer":"Way horses use their bodies to show other horses or people how they feel"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"652","question":"Name 3 things that will tell the mood of a horse.","answer":"Eyes, ears, nostrils, mouth, teeth, muscles, tail, licking, chewing (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"653","question":"What does it mean if a horse has its ears pricked forward?","answer":"That it's interested in something (interest or suspicion)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"654","question":"What is the term for the way horses use their bodies to show other horses or people how they feel?","answer":"Body language"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"655","question":"How do you read your horse's mood or intentions as you approach it?","answer":"By watching its head and ears (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"656","question":"What does it mean if a horse has its ears pinned back?","answer":"That it's mad (anger or aggression)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"657","question":"Eyelids wide open, flared nostrils, snorting, tail tucked between legs, balking, shying, and a whinny of distress are all signs of what?","answer":"Fear"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"int bonus","number":"658","question":"Give 3 physical signs that a horse is afraid.","answer":"Eyelids wide open, snorting, whinny of distress, nostrils flared, tail tucked between legs, flight, raising head (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"659","question":"In problem solving intelligence tests, does the horse place high, medium, or low?","answer":"Low"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"660","question":"What does a nervous handler cause?","answer":"Nervous or unsafe horse"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"661","question":"Why should you NEVER punish your horse when you're angry?","answer":"Your punishment will be too severe"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"662","question":"Why shouldn't you punish a horse for shying?","answer":"Because with its power of association, it would blame the object for the punishment and it might develop the habit of shying at every strange object (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"663","question":"Why is it important when you have to punish a horse, that you do it immediately?","answer":"He won't understand why he's being punished if you wait"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"664","question":"How soon should you punish a misbehaving horse?","answer":"Immediately (within 3 seconds)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"665","question":"Name 3 sensitive places on a horse.","answer":"Eyes, ears, nose, mouth, feet, legs, neck, shoulders, withers, belly, ribs, flank (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"666","question":"Name 5 senses of the horse.","answer":"Sight, smell, hearing, touch, taste"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"667","question":"Name 3 stimuli that trigger the response of shivering.","answer":"Cold, fear, excitement, illness, pain, fever (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"668","question":"Horses have very good hearing.  What can they do with their ears to help localize the source of the sounds they hear?","answer":"Turn their ears toward the direction of the sound"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"669","question":"Give ONE reason why a horse might react to a sound that a person can't hear.","answer":"Horses can hear sounds that people can't; horses can move their ears; horses can hear in almost any direction (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"670","question":"Which sense of the horse is better, sight or hearing?","answer":"Hearing"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"novice","number":"671","question":"Who has better hearing, you or your horse?","answer":"Your horse"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"int bonus","number":"672","question":"Name 3 things the horse uses its sense of smell for.","answer":"Locate food, locate water, ensure quality of food or water, identify other horses, identify people, identify objects, smell predators or other dangers, identify marked territory of other horses or herds, initiate sexual or breeding behavior"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"673","question":"Name 3 things for which the horse uses its olfactory sense.","answer":"Locate food, ensure quality of food or water, identify other horses, identify people, identify objects, smell predators or other dangers, identify marked territory of other horses or herds, initiate sexual or breeding behavior, accept any correct answers"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"674","question":"What is the term for the curling of the upper lip by stallions when teasing mares?","answer":"Flehmen reflex"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"675","question":"What is the Flehmen response?","answer":"Horse raises its head and curls its upper lip back"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"676","question":"2 part question:  What is the common name for the olfactory reflex and describe it?","answer":"Flehmen response; horse smells something and then extends its neck or head and curls its upper lip"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"677","question":"What is the tactile sense?","answer":"Sense of touch"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"678","question":"The horse has a hard time focusing clearly on objects, but VISUALLY they are very good at detecting what?","answer":"Movement"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"679","question":"What is the term for the type of vision where the horse sees the same scene with both eyes?","answer":"Binocular vision"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"680","question":"Which type of vision is a horse using when he looks at something head on?","answer":"Binocular vision"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"681","question":"To judge distance, the horse uses which type of vision?","answer":"Binocular vision"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"682","question":"Name TWO areas where a horse does NOT see anything.","answer":"Directly in front, directly behind, over its head/neck/back, under head, directly downward "},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"683","question":"A horse cannot see directly BELOW what part of its body?","answer":"Head (also accept neck and body)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"684","question":"A horse cannot see directly BEHIND what part of its body?","answer":"Hindquarters (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"685","question":"Name 3 of the horse's blind spots.","answer":"Directly in front, directly behind, over its head/neck/back, under head, directly downward"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"686","question":"2 part question:  Describe where the object is that a horse is focusing on when he raises his head and when he lowers his head.","answer":"Raises head—focusing on a nearby object; lowers head—focusing on a faraway object"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"687","question":"An object must be at what distance in front of a horse for the object to be seen?","answer":"4 (four) feet"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"688","question":"What must the horse do with its head to see faraway objects?","answer":"Lower its head"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"689","question":"What must the horse do to see close objects?","answer":"Raise its head"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"690","question":"In reference to behavior, what is the \"menace reflex\"?","answer":"Horse closes its eye when a hand or object moves toward the eye."},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"691","question":"What is the ability to see separate objects with each eye at the same time?","answer":"Monocular vision"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"692","question":"What is monocular vision?","answer":"Ability to see separate objects with each eye at the same time"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"693","question":"What has been a prime feature of the horse's ability to survive?","answer":"Monocular vision (its ability to see objects on either side at the same time)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"694","question":"What survival advantage does the horse have because of its monocular vision?","answer":"Monocular vision allows horse to detect predators from either side without turning its head (which is particularly important while grazing)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"695","question":"Explain the difference between monocular and binocular vision.","answer":"Monocular vision—horse sees different objects with each eye; binocular vision—horse uses both eyes to see the same object."},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"696","question":"What is a horse's TOTAL degree of vision?","answer":"Approximately 350 degrees"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"697","question":"Name 3 things that determine the front and rear vision of the horse.","answer":"Size of eye, position of eye, width of head, width of body"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"698","question":"What is the range of a horse's BINOCULAR vision?","answer":"65 degrees (directly in front of its head)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"699","question":"What makes it possible for a horse to have more forward and rear vision than other animals?","answer":"Large, wide-set eyes"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"700","question":"What is the loud, prolonged call of a horse?","answer":"Neigh"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"701","question":"What is the soft, welcoming noise made by a content horse?","answer":"Nicker"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"702","question":"What sound acts as a warning signal between horses?","answer":"Snort"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"703","question":"What sound does a horse make in response to anger?","answer":"Squeal"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"704","question":"Give ONE reason why stabled horses develop vices.","answer":"Boredom, lack of exercise, lack of long stem forage or \"chew time\", copying other horses (accept any)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"705","question":"What is the common negative BEHAVIORAL consequence for failing to provide your horse with adequate roughage?","answer":"Horse will develop vices."},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"706","question":"In general, what is the most effective way to stop a vice before it becomes a habit","answer":"Determine and remove the cause"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"707","question":"What is the general term for a bad or annoying habit that may affect a horse's health, usefulness, or dependability?","answer":"Vice"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"708","question":"Teasing a horse may cause it to do what?","answer":"Develop dangerous habits (bite, kick, etc.)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"709","question":"What is the definition of a vice?","answer":"Bad or annoying habit (that may interfere with the health or usefulness of the horse)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"710","question":"Under natural conditions, horses do not spend long periods of time in what general type of area?","answer":"Enclosed areas"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"711","question":"There are few vicious horses.  What may cause a horse to become vicious?","answer":"Abuse"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"712","question":"What is a barn sour horse?","answer":"Horse that doesn't want to leave the barn (and acts up when being ridden away from the barn)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"713","question":"What is the term for a horse that acts up because it doesn’t want to leave the barn?","answer":"Barn sour"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"714","question":"Explain the difference between bolting and shying.","answer":"Bolting—horse goes forward; shying—horse goes to the side"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"715","question":"In reference horse behavior, what are TWO ways the term \"bolting\" can be used?","answer":"Eating too fast; running off or charging forward"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"716","question":"What term describes the habit horses have of eating too fast?","answer":"Bolting their feed"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"717","question":"The placement of several large, round rocks in a horse's feed tub helps to decrease the incidence of what vice?","answer":"Bolting its feed"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"intermediate","number":"718","question":"When a saddled horse stands with its back pushed up or bowed upward, what may this indicate?","answer":"That it's going to buck when the rider mounts"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"719","question":"What movement is being described? The horse leaps into the air, keeping his back arched, and lands with his forelegs stiff and his head held low.","answer":"Bucking"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"720","question":"Charging is seen most commonly in what sex of horse?","answer":"Male (stallions)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"721","question":"What is a cinch bound horse?","answer":"Horse that doesn't like being cinched up"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"722","question":"Give ONE term for when a horse doesn't like its cinch tightened.","answer":"Cinchbound, girthbound, cold-backed, cinchy"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"723","question":"Describe a cow kick.","answer":"Horse kicks with a forward and sidewards motion"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"724","question":"What is it called when a horse kicks with a forward and sideward motion?","answer":"Cow kick"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"725","question":"Which vice is characterized by biting or setting the teeth against a fence or some other object while sucking air?","answer":"Cribbing"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"726","question":"What is cribbing?","answer":"Biting or setting the teeth against an object while sucking air"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"727","question":"A strap buckled around the neck in a way that will compress the larynx when the head is flexed is a common remedy for what vice?","answer":"Cribbing"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"728","question":"In reference to horses, what are \"crow hops\"?","answer":"Mild bucking motions"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"729","question":"What are mild bucking motions called?","answer":"Crow hops"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"730","question":"In reference to vices, what is the term used when a horse consciously squeezes the handler against the stall wall?","answer":"Crowding"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"731","question":"Name 3 vices that are dangerous to man.","answer":"Biting, nipping, striking, charging, crowding, rearing, bucking, shying, bolting or running away, halter pulling (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"732","question":"Name 3 vices that are dangerous to the horse.","answer":"Cribbing (aerophagia), wood chewing (lignophagia), mane or tail chewing, eating dirt (geophagia), eating feces (coprophagia), bolting food, fighting, shying, halter pulling"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"733","question":"In reference to a horse's behavior, what does the term “freezing” mean?","answer":"Horse refuses to move (horse becomes stiff or immobile)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"734","question":"What practice may prevent a horse from becoming a halter puller?","answer":"Untying the lead rope before taking the halter off"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"735","question":"What vice is often associated with head nodding?","answer":"Weaving"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"736","question":"Describe the vice \"head nodding\".","answer":"Horse rhythmically nods its head (either up and down or back and forth)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"737","question":"What does \"head shy\" mean?","answer":"Horse doesn't like to be touched on the head"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"738","question":"What does \"herd bound\" mean?","answer":"Horse refuses to leave a group of other horses"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"739","question":"What do you call a horse that refuses to leave a group of other horses?","answer":"Herd bound"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"740","question":"Name 3 nuisance vices.","answer":"Weaving, stall walking, head nodding, tongue displacement, pawing, mane or tail rubbing"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"741","question":"What is the most important thing for you to provide your horse in order to prevent him from stall kicking, cribbing, and wood chewing?","answer":"Regular exercise (also accept plenty of forage)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"742","question":"2 part question:  Describe an escape vice and give TWO examples.","answer":"Horse is unhappy in a certain place and would like to escape; examples: pawing, pacing, trying to jump out of stall or paddock, weaving, head nodding, accept any correct answer"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"743","question":"Name TWO vices that are often copied by other horses.","answer":"Cribbing, weaving, wood chewing, pawing (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"jr bonus","number":"744","question":"Name 3 stable vices.","answer":"Cribbing, weaving, stall walking, wood chewing, pawing, crowding, mane or tail chewing (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"sr bonus","number":"745","question":"Name 3 oral vices in horses.","answer":"Cribbing, windsucking, wood chewing, tail or mane chewing, eating feces or bedding, accept any correct answers"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"746","question":"What is indicated by the behavioral term pica?","answer":"Eating unnatural substances such as dirt, feces, bones, wood, and hair  (FYI:  geophagia, coprophagia, osteophagia, lignophagia, and trichophagia)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"747","question":"Name ONE dietary deficiency that may cause the act of pica in horses.","answer":"Sodium chloride (salt), potassium, phosphorus, protein"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"748","question":"What is coprophagia? (coe-pro-FAY-shah)","answer":"Eating feces (FYI:  Coprophagia is common in foals and young horses, but it’s considered to be abnormal behavior for adult horses.)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"hard","number":"749","question":"What is the term used to describe a horse that eats dirt because of a mineral deficiency?","answer":"Geophagia (also accept pica)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"750","question":"What type of behavior would be exhibited by a gelding that is described as a “rig” or “proud-cut” horse?","answer":"Stallion-like behavior"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"751","question":"What is the name of the vice where the horse constantly paces or circles around its stall?","answer":"Stall walking"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"752","question":"What is the term for the action when a horse lashes out with a front leg when mad?","answer":"Striking"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"753","question":"What GENERAL age horse is usually involved in tail chewing?","answer":"Foals or young horses (accept either)"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"754","question":"What is the name for the oral vice in which a horse sticks its tongue out the side of the mouth?","answer":"Tongue displacement"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"medium","number":"755","question":"2 part question:  In reference to vices, what is weaving and where is it commonly seen?","answer":"Moving the head or body from side to side; seen in the stall or along a  fence line"},
{"category":"Behavior","level":"easy","number":"756","question":"Describe the stable vice called weaving.","answer":"Horse moves its head and upper body from side to side; horse rocks side to side or back and forth; accept any reasonable wording"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"757","question":"What is a written record of an animal's ancestry?  It may or may not be used to refer to a registration certificate.","answer":"Pedigree"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"758","question":"What does an asterisk in front of a horse's registered name mean?","answer":"Horse is imported."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"759","question":"What is the term for a group of horses having common origin and possessing certain traits that are passed on to their offspring?","answer":"Breed"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"760","question":"Name ONE basic difference between breeds of horses.","answer":"Body type, coloring, markings, gaits, size, location and amount of muscling (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"761","question":"Body type, color patterns, gaits, and way of going are all examples of what type characteristics?","answer":"Breed characteristics"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"762","question":"What is the term for the characteristics that are unique to a particular breed?","answer":"Breed characteristics"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"763","question":"What is the difference between the terms breed characteristics and sex characteristics?","answer":"Breed characteristics are characteristics that are unique to a breed (such as body type, color patterns, and gaits); sex characteristics refers to masculinity males and femininity in females"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"764","question":"What is a breed standard?","answer":"Standard of excellence set up by an association for its breed"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"765","question":"What is \"breed type\"?","answer":"Characteristics commonly accepted as ideal for a particular breed"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"766","question":"What is the nickname for a horse with a heavy, coarse tail?","answer":"Broomtail or bang tail"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"767","question":"In reference to breed types, give ONE definition of a broomtail.","answer":"Horse with a heavy, coarse tail; a Western range horse; or an ill-kept horse of inferior quality"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"768","question":"What is the term for a short-legged horse that's built like a heavyweight hunter and is capable of carrying a substantial weight?","answer":"Cob"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"769","question":"In reference to breed types, what is a \"cob\"?","answer":"Short-legged, heavy-weight hunter (that is capable of carrying substantial weight)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"770","question":"2 part question:  What is meant by the term \"cob tail\" and in what type of horses is it commonly seen?","answer":"Docking the horse's tail to 6 (six) inch length; seen in Hackneys and draft horses"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"771","question":"What is the term for a horse that has parents of different breeds?","answer":"Crossbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"772","question":"What is a crossbred?","answer":"Horse with parents of two different breeds"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"773","question":"What term refers to the female side of the pedigree?","answer":"Distaff"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"774","question":"What is the term for a group of animals within a breed, all of which trace directly to a common ancestor?","answer":"Family"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"775","question":"What term is used to identify the original horses used in a breeding program?","answer":"Foundation stock"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"776","question":"What is the term for a horse of unknown breeding or ancestry?","answer":"Grade"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"777","question":"What is a grade animal?","answer":"Unregistered horse or horse with unknown ancestry"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"778","question":"What is the term for a horse ridden to a hunt meet?","answer":"Hack"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"779","question":"In reference to breed types, what is a hack?","answer":"Horse ridden to a hunt meet"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"780","question":"What is the term for a horse used to chase foxes and jump over fences?","answer":"Hunter (also accept hack)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"781","question":"What is a pedigree?","answer":"Written record of an animal's ancestry"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"782","question":"What is the term for a horse whose parents are recorded in the same breed association?","answer":"Purebred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"783","question":"What is the term for recording an animal from registered parents in a breed association?","answer":"Registration"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"784","question":"What do you call a written record of an animal's ancestry that's issued by the registry association?","answer":"Registration certificate"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"785","question":"What is a registry association?","answer":"Organization formed for the purpose of keeping records of the ancestry of individuals within a breed and to promote the breed"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"786","question":"What is a studbook?","answer":"Register of all horses foaled for a breed (record book published by the breed registry association for purebred horses, ponies, or jacks)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"787","question":"What part of a pedigree is referred to as the \"top line\"?","answer":"Stallion side (FYI: The female side is the distaff side.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"788","question":"What is recognized as the universal birthdate for many breeds?","answer":"January 1st (FYI: The universal birthdate in the southern hemisphere is August 1st.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"789","question":"What is a \"light\" horse?","answer":"Horse used primarily for riding or driving; all breeds except draft; a saddle horse (accept any)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"790","question":"Any horse used primarily for riding, all breeds except draft breeds, is called what?","answer":"Light horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"791","question":"What is a \"combination horse\"?","answer":"Horse used for both riding and driving"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"792","question":"In reference to horse breeds, what does the term \"hot blooded\" mean?","answer":"Horse of Eastern or Oriental blood"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"793","question":"What do you call a horse of Eastern or Oriental blood?","answer":"Hot blooded"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"794","question":"Name ONE breed used as a foundation for developing many modern breeds.","answer":"Arabian, Thoroughbred, Morgan "},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"795","question":"Name the breed associated with 3 of the following horses: Figure, Hambletonian, Black Hand, Black Allan, and Janus.","answer":"Figure—Morgan; Hambletonian—Standardbred; Black Hand—POA; Black Allan—Tennessee Walking Horse; Janus—Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"796","question":"What is generally considered the minimum height for a horse?","answer":"Over 14.2 hands"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"797","question":"Name 3 US breeds for which the Thoroughbred provided foundation stock.","answer":"Standardbred, Quarter Horse, Morgan, American Saddlebred (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"798","question":"Identify this breed: able to withstand severe weather in its countries of origin Turkmenistan and Russia; known for its stubbornness, speed, jumping ability, and metallic coat sheen.","answer":"Akhal-Teke"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"799","question":"In which country were horses with the colorful characteristics of the Appaloosa first seen?","answer":"China"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"800","question":"Mottled skin, striped hooves, and sclera around the eye are all characteristics of which breed?","answer":"Appaloosa or POA (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"801","question":"What breed characteristically has vertically striped hooves?","answer":"Appaloosa or POA (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"802","question":"Name 3 characteristics of Appaloosas.","answer":"Mottled skin, white sclera around the eyes, striped hooves, approved coat pattern"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"803","question":"One of the characteristics of the Appaloosa is a striped hoof.  Which way do the stripes run on their hooves?","answer":"Vertical (up and down)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"804","question":"What breed was developed by the Nez Perce Indians?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"805","question":"What breed has its headquarters in Moscow, Idaho?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"806","question":"Which Indian tribe is believed to be the first to practice selective breeding?","answer":"Nez Perce"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"int bonus","number":"807","question":"In what 3 western states was the Appaloosa developed?","answer":"Oregon, Washington, Idaho"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"808","question":"What breed was formerly known as the \"Palouse Horse\"?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"809","question":"What is the origination of the name \"Appaloosa\"?","answer":"Slurring of the words \"a Palouse\" (refers to the Palouse region where the breed was developed)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"int bonus","number":"810","question":"Name 3 color patterns of the Appaloosa.","answer":"Leopard, blanket or snowcap, blanket with spots, few spot leopard, snowflake, frost, mottled, varnish roan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"811","question":"What breed of horse is sometimes called \"rat-tailed\" because of its characteristic sparse mane and tail?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"812","question":"Which breed consistently outlives other breeds?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"813","question":"What is the oldest purebred breed?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"814","question":"What is an Anglo Arab?","answer":"Horse that's half Arabian and half Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"815","question":"Where did the Arabian horse originate?","answer":"Arabia"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"816","question":"Who were the Bedouins? (BED-oh-wins)","answer":"Arabian tribesmen (who were the first breeders of the Arabian)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"817","question":"Who were the first breeders of Arabians?","answer":"Arabian tribesmen [Bedouins (BED-oh-wins)]"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"818","question":"The Arabian's Arabic name is Kohl-ani.  Where did it get this name?","answer":"Arabian's skin is the same blue-black color as the kohl that Arabian women wear as eyeliner."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"819","question":"Which breed excels in distance riding?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"820","question":"Which breed is noted for its great endurance?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"821","question":"What are 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Arabian?","answer":"Beautiful head; dished face; fine muzzle; large nostrils; arching neck; high tail carriage; free way of going; great endurance; short coupling; small build; docility"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"822","question":"What is a jibbah?","answer":"Bulge between the eyes of an Arabian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"823","question":"What color skin does the Arabian always have?","answer":"Dark"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"824","question":"In reference to the evolution of the breed, why is it believed that for their body size, Arabian horses have large hooves?","answer":"Enables them to travel more easily over the desert sands"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"825","question":"Name 3 colors of the Arabian.","answer":"Black, bay brown, chestnut, gray, occasional roan and white (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"826","question":"Around 1906, Homer Davenport was responsible for the major expansion of which breed in America?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"827","question":"The popularity of Arabians in the US began with the introduction of 45 horses showcased in 1892 at what location?","answer":"Chicago World's Fair"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"828","question":"When was the first purebred Arabian breeding program started in the US?","answer":"Late 1800's (FYI:  Randolph Huntington used Leopard and Linden Tree to in his Arabian breeding program.  Homer Davenport further expanded the breed.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"829","question":"The first purebred Arabian breeding program in the US is linked to what US President who was given two Arabian stallions by the Sultan of Turkey?","answer":"Ulysses S. Grant (FYI:  The two stallions were Leopard and Linden Tree.  These stallions along with “Max” were the foundation sires of the Rangerbred breed.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"830","question":"Which breed must have an ancestry of 50% or higher of Arabian blood?","answer":"Half-Arabian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"831","question":"What organization started the Half-Arabian registry?","answer":"US Calvary (Remount Service)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"832","question":"What is a Morab?","answer":"Cross between a Morgan and an Arabian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"833","question":"What is the name for the breed that resulted from crossing a Morgan and an Arabian?","answer":"Morab"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"834","question":"What is the name of the breed developed in the US that is a cross between a Saddlebred and an Arabian?","answer":"National Show Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"835","question":"Prior to 1908, the American Jockey Club registered what TWO other breeds of horse besides the Thoroughbred?","answer":"Arabian and Anglo-Arab"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"836","question":"Before 1908, Arabians and Anglo-Arabians were registered in which breed association?","answer":"Jockey Club"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"837","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is an Arabian?","answer":"14.1 - 15.1 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"838","question":"What is the average weight of an Arabian?","answer":"800 - 1000 pounds (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"839","question":"Give ONE use of the Arabian.","answer":"Endurance, show, pleasure, stock, racing (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"840","question":"What TWO breeds were combined in the development of the Azteca?","answer":"Andalusian and Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"841","question":"Which breed of horse originated in Mexico as a result of crossing Andalusian stallions with Quarter Horse mares?","answer":"Azteca"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"842","question":"In what area of the world did the Barb originate?","answer":"Northern Africa (Barbary States)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"843","question":"What breed of horse originated in the Ural Mountains of Russia? It's well-adapted to cold weather and it’s noted for its long, curly hair coat.","answer":"Bashkir Curly"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"844","question":"What is the distinguishing characteristic of the Bashkir Curly?","answer":"Curly coat"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"845","question":"Where did the American Bashkir Curly get its name?","answer":"From the curly-coated horses raised in the Bashkir region (of the Ural mountains of Russia)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"846","question":"Where did the American Bashkir Curly originate?","answer":"United States (from feral horses in Nevada)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"847","question":"What breed of horse is ALWAYS bay?","answer":"Cleveland Bay"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"848","question":"What is the reason for disqualification when registering a Cleveland Bay?","answer":"If it's not bay"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"849","question":"What is the most common color of the Hackney?","answer":"Bay"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"850","question":"Which breed originated in England from Norfolk trotters and Thoroughbreds?","answer":"Hackney"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"int bonus","number":"851","question":"Name 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Lipizzan.","answer":"Agility; temperament; good character; docility; intelligence; strength; arched neck; proud carriage (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"852","question":"Describe the coloring of the Lipizzan from birth to maturity.","answer":"Born dark and gets lighter each year (appears \"white\" between 6 - 10 years  of age)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"853","question":"What is the predominant color of the Lipizzan?","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"854","question":"What breed was formerly known as the “Karster” horse?","answer":"Lipizzan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"855","question":"Which breed was developed by the Hapsburg family of Austria?","answer":"Lipizzan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"856","question":"Which breed is world famous because of its connection with the Spanish Riding School?","answer":"Lipizzan (FYI:  The Spanish Riding School is in Vienna, Austria.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"857","question":"Where is the site of the Spanish Riding School?","answer":"Vienna, Austria"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"858","question":"What breed was threatened with extinction during World War II?","answer":"Lipizzan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"859","question":"Who was responsible for returning the Lipizzan mares to Austria during World War II?","answer":"US Army"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"860","question":"During World War II, the Spanish Riding School was saved by the efforts of whom?","answer":"US Army, General Patton, director of the Spanish Riding School (Alois Podhajsky) (accept any)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"861","question":"In addition to the stallion lines, how many dominant female families are recognized by the Lipizzan registry?","answer":"35 female lines"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"862","question":"Name 3 classic Lipizzan stallion lines.","answer":"Conversano, Favory, Maestoso, Neapolitano, Pluto, Siglavy"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"863","question":"In order to be eligible for registration, horses of which breed must trace directly without interruption to the recognized male lines and female families of which official European stud farm?","answer":"Lipizzan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"864","question":"Giving only one number, what is the height of the Lipizzan?","answer":"14.2 - 15.2 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"865","question":"Which breed is the only breed to be named after an individual horse?","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"866","question":"Identify this breed:  essential in the development of other American breeds; USDA had a farm in Middlebury, Vermont; known for its all-purpose abilities on the farm or in the show ring; only breed named after a single horse.","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"int bonus","number":"867","question":"Name 3 breeds of American horses that can trace their foundation back to the Morgan.","answer":"Saddlebred, Tennessee Walker, Standardbred, Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"868","question":"Other than conformation, what are 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Morgan?","answer":"Easy keeper; endurance; docility"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"869","question":"Name 3 colors of the Morgan.","answer":"Black, bay, brown, chestnut, palomino, buckskin, gray, pinto, dun, perlino, smoky cream (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"870","question":"The dark liver or black chestnut color is most common in which breed?","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"871","question":"Name TWO colors or patterns that are ineligible for registration in the Morgan breed.","answer":"White above hocks except for face markings; spotted or pinto patterns; Appaloosa patterns; blue eyes"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"872","question":"In 1894, Colonel Battel founded the registry for what breed of horse?","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"873","question":"Where did the Morgan originate?","answer":"United States (New England, Vermont)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"874","question":"Who is the foundation sire of the Morgan breed?","answer":"Figure (Justin Morgan)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"875","question":"Who was Figure?","answer":"Foundation sire of the Morgan breed (later called Justin Morgan)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"876","question":"What famous foundation sire carried President James Madison on a Muster Day parade ground?","answer":"Justin Morgan or Figure (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"877","question":"2 part question:  The foundation sire for the Morgan breed was Figure.  Figure was later known by what other name and how did he get that name?","answer":"Justin Morgan; it was the custom at that time to give the horse the owner’s name"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"878","question":"The stallion True Britton, who sired Justin Morgan, was also known by what other name?","answer":"Beautiful Bay"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"879","question":"Which breed was the first to represent the US in the World Pairs Driving Competition?","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"880","question":"How much does a Morgan horse weigh?","answer":"1000 pounds (accept any number between 1000 - 1200 pounds)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"881","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is a Morgan?","answer":"14.1 - 15.1 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"882","question":"A horse of Paint breeding who does NOT meet the color requirements may be registered in the division known as what?","answer":"Breeding Stock Paint (FYI: They are now called Solid Paint-Bred by APHA.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"883","question":"What are the TWO basic requirements for registering an American Paint Horse?","answer":"Must have Paint, Thoroughbred, or Quarter Horse breeding; must meet minimum color requirements"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"884","question":"In reference to breed associations, what does APHA stand for?","answer":"American Paint Horse Association (FYI: Headquarters are in Fort Worth, Texas.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"885","question":"In what city and state is the American Paint Horse Association headquarters?","answer":"Fort Worth, Texas"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"886","question":"Giving only one number, what is the average height of the Quarter Horse?","answer":"15 hands (accept any number in the 14 - 17 hand range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"887","question":"How did the Quarter Horse get its name?","answer":"From its ability to sprint a quarter mile"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"888","question":"According to the American Horse Council, what breed of horse is the most popular in the US?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"889","question":"In what city and state is the American Quarter Horse Association headquarters located?","answer":"Amarillo, Texas"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"890","question":"Name 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Quarter Horse.","answer":"Cow sense; compact muscling; speed over short distances; short, foxy ears; short, broad head; large eyes; calm disposition (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"891","question":"Identify this breed: head is short and broad with large nostrils and short, foxy ears; its disposition is calm; muscling is short, compact, and powerful which gives it the ability to gain speed quickly.","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"892","question":"Which breed is noted for its \"cow sense\"?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"893","question":"Which breed of horse is known for its ability to gain speed in a matter of seconds over short distances?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"894","question":"What is the most common color of the Quarter Horse?","answer":"Sorrel (chestnut)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"895","question":"What is the small, short-coupled horse named for an Indian tribe that was an ancestor of the Quarter Horse?","answer":"Chickasaw Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"896","question":"Where did the Quarter Horse originate?","answer":"United States (Eastern US)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"897","question":"Legends say that Paul Revere rode which breed of horse?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"898","question":"Who was the first permanently registered Quarter Horse?","answer":"Wimpy (Wimpy P-1)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"899","question":"Most Quarter Horse foundation sires trace back to which stallion?","answer":"Janus"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"900","question":"The King Ranch of Texas developed a linebreeding program around one Quarter Horse stallion that they felt fit their ideal of the working cow horse.  Who was this stallion?","answer":"Old Sorrel"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"901","question":"Who was Wimpy's famous grandsire?","answer":"Old Sorrel"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"902","question":"What current breed of horse was known as \"Steeldusts\" in the early 1900’s?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"903","question":"The Rangerbred or Colorado Ranger Horse is often confused with which breed?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"904","question":"Name the 3 foundation sires of the Rangerbred horse.","answer":"Max, Leopard, Linden Tree (FYI:  Leopard and Linden tree were the two horses given to Ulysses S. Grant by the Sultan of Turkey.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"905","question":"Linden Tree, Leopard, and Max were the foundation sires for what breed of horse that is often mistaken for an Appaloosa?","answer":"Rangerbred or Colorado Ranger Horse (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"906","question":"Where did the Thoroughbred originate?","answer":"England"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"907","question":"Which breed is known for its use in polo, jumping, and racing?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"908","question":"Which breed is the term \"blood horse\" synonymous with?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"909","question":"Who are the 3 foundation sires of the Thoroughbred?","answer":"Darley Arabian, Godolphin Arabian, Byerly Turk"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"910","question":"What do the Darley Arabian, Byerly Turk, and Godolphin Arabian have in common?","answer":"Foundation sires of the Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"911","question":"What is the name of the horse traditionally regarded as the first Thoroughbred imported to the US in 1730?","answer":"Bulle Rock"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"912","question":"To what famous Thoroughbred, unbeaten in 24 races in 1764, do 90% of all modern Thoroughbreds trace their ancestry?","answer":"Eclipse (FYI: Eclipse’s topline traces back to Darley Arabian and its distaff side traces back to Godolphin Arabian.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"913","question":"Name the 3 main Thoroughbred stallion lines that trace back to the foundation sires.","answer":"Eclipse, Matchem, and Herod  (FYI: Eclipse—Darley Arabian and Godolphin Arabian; Matchem—Godolphin Arabian; Herod—Byerly Turk)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"914","question":"What is the name of the Thoroughbred ridden by General Custer at the Battle of the Little Big Horn?","answer":"Vic"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"915","question":"The Jockey Club maintains the registry of Thoroughbreds for the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.  What is the proper name of the register?","answer":"American Stud Book"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"916","question":"Name ONE country, other than the US, whose Thoroughbred foals are registered with the Jockey Club.","answer":"Canada or Puerto Rico"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"917","question":"Which breed is represented by the breed association known as the Jockey Club?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"918","question":"What organization has responsibility for the American Stud Book?","answer":"Jockey Club"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"919","question":"Which breed of horse would you find in the American Studbook?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"920","question":"The American Stud Book is a register of Thoroughbred horses from what 3 countries?","answer":"US, Canada, and Puerto Rico"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"921","question":"The Thoroughbred exceeds other breeds at racing over what distance?","answer":"6 - 12 furlongs (3/4 - 1 ½ miles) (accept any number within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"922","question":"In addition to Wall Street financier James Keene, what other prominent horseman led the development of the Jockey Club?","answer":"August Belmont, II (may accept Belmont)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"923","question":"What is the measure of performance for the racing Thoroughbred?","answer":"Speed"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"924","question":"Which state was the center for raising and training of Thoroughbreds in colonial America?","answer":"Virginia"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"925","question":"There were two famous Thoroughbred race horses known as \"Big Red\". Who was the ORIGINAL \"Big Red\"?","answer":"Man o' War (FYI: Secretariat was also called Big Red.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"926","question":"What two famous Thoroughbred race horses were both known by the nickname \"Big Red\"?","answer":"Man o' War and Secretariat"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"927","question":"What is the weight of a Thoroughbred?","answer":"1000 pounds (accept any number within 1000 - 1250 pounds)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"928","question":"What is the average height of the Thoroughbred?","answer":"16 hands (accept any number in the 15.2 - 17 hand range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"929","question":"Name 3 breeds developed from the need for a comfortable, ground-covering, smooth-gaited riding, and driving horse.","answer":"American Saddlebred, Tennessee Walking Horse, Missouri Foxtrotter, Rocky Mountain Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"930","question":"Name ONE breed developed from the need for a comfortable, ground-covering, smooth-gaited riding, and driving horse.","answer":"American Saddlebred, Tennessee Walking Horse, Missouri Foxtrotter, Rocky Mountain Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"931","question":"Identify 3 breeds that originated in the US and were developed from crossing other breeds with Canadian pacers.","answer":"Standardbred, American Saddlebred, Tennessee Walking Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"932","question":"2 part question:  Name TWO American horse breeds that have two distinct types based on gait and name the types.","answer":"Standardbred—trotters and pacers; Saddlebred—3-gaited and 5-gaited"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"933","question":"Name TWO breeds that perform the running walk.","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse and Galiceño"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"934","question":"Name 3 colors of the Missouri Fox Trotter.","answer":"ANY COLOR, black, bay, brown, chestnut, palomino, roan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"935","question":"The Missouri Foxtrotter traces its ancestry to what 3 breeds?","answer":"Arabian, Morgan, Plantation horses, Saddlebred, Standardbred, Tennessee Walking Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"936","question":"Which breed was developed from saddle horses by settlers in the Ozarks?","answer":"Missouri Fox Trotter"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"937","question":"What breed of horse is known for its distinctive gait in which the horse performs a brisk walk with the front legs and trots with the back legs?  This breed originated in the Ozark Mountains of Missouri and Arkansas.","answer":"Missouri Fox Trotter"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"938","question":"Name 3 differences between the Peruvian Paso and the Paso Fino.","answer":"Peruvian Paso breed was developed in Peru; Peruvian Pasos must be solid colors; Paso Fino breed was developed in Columbia and Puerto Rica; Peruvian Pasos can be spotted"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"939","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Paso Fino?","answer":"13 - 15.2 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"940","question":"Name 3 breeds from which the Paso Fino was developed.","answer":"Andalusian, Barb, Spanish Jennet, and Friesian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"941","question":"Who brought the Paso Fino to the New World?","answer":"Columbus"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"942","question":"There are two distinct types of Paso horses.  Which type allows pintos, roans, and cremellos in the registry?","answer":"Paso Fino"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"943","question":"Where did the Paso Fino ORIGINALLY come from?","answer":"Spain (FYI: They were developed from horses of Barb, Andalusian, and Spanish Jennet breeding; they were imported later from Puerto Rico and Columbia.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"944","question":"Which breed was first imported from Peru in the mid-1960's?","answer":"Peruvian Paso"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"945","question":"What Paso breed is known for the gaits paso llano and sombreandando and for its characteristic leg motion called the termino?","answer":"Peruvian Paso (FYI: The termino has outward swinging front leg motion originating at the shoulders.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"946","question":"What gaited breed originated in the Appalachian mountains of Eastern Kentucky?  The breed association was formed in 1986.  This breed exhibits a natural ambling 4-beat gait.","answer":"Rocky Mountain Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"947","question":"What breed registry is the oldest for an American breed of horse?  It was founded in 1891 in Louisville, Kentucky, but was later moved to Lexington, Kentucky.","answer":"American Saddlebred Horse Association"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"948","question":"Name 3 colors of the American Saddlebred.","answer":"ANY COLOR, black, bay, brown, chestnut, gray, palomino, buckskin, roan, pinto (FYI:  Chestnut is the most common color.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"949","question":"Who was the foundation sire of the American Saddlebred Horse?","answer":"Denmark (FYI: Denmark was a Thoroughbred)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"950","question":"In what US state did the American Saddlebred originate?","answer":"Kentucky (FYI:  It was originally known as the Kentucky Saddler.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"951","question":"What was the original name of the American Saddlebred?","answer":"Kentucky Saddler (also accept American Horse)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"952","question":"In what city and state is the breed headquarters for the American Saddlebred Horse Association?","answer":"Lexington, Kentucky (FYI:  It’s located at the Kentucky Horse Park.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"953","question":"What are the color restrictions of the American Saddlebred Horse?","answer":"NO color restrictions"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"954","question":"What phrase is commonly used to describe the American Saddlebred?","answer":"Peacock of the Show World or Peacock of the Show Ring (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"955","question":"Who was the 6-time winner of the $10,000 5-gaited championship at the Kentucky State Fair?","answer":"Wing Commander"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"956","question":"Describe the color of the Golden American Saddlebred.","answer":"Body color is yellow or golden; mane and tail are white or flaxen."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"957","question":"2 part question:  Golden American Saddlebreds have TWO predominant families.  Name the TWO families and explain how they are different.","answer":"Peavines have light skin; Belvederes have dark skin."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"958","question":"Name 3 qualifications for registering a Golden American Saddlebred.","answer":"Registered American Saddlebred; palomino coloring; no white spots on body"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"959","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is a Standardbred?","answer":"14.2 - 16.2 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"960","question":"Today's Standardbreds are able to trot or pace at what speed?","answer":"30 miles per hour"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"961","question":"Giving only one number, what is the average weight of the Standardbred?","answer":"850 - 1150 pounds (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"962","question":"What was the original name for the Standardbred?","answer":"American Trotting Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"963","question":"Over 60% of Standardbreds are which color?","answer":"Bay"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"964","question":"Name TWO things which determine the racing gait of the Standardbred.","answer":"Genetic factors, training, shoeing"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"965","question":"99% of all Standardbreds trace to which stallion?","answer":"Hambletonian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"966","question":"The Standardbred is primarily used in what TWO ways?","answer":"Harness racing; driving"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"967","question":"What is the origination of the name Standardbred?","answer":"Horse had to trot or pace a mile in a standard time of 2 ½ minutes or less to be admitted to the studbook."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"968","question":"Name the breed that includes the following famous names in its history:  Messenger, Greyhound, Hambletonian, Dan Patch, and Niatross.","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"969","question":"Messenger, a gray Thoroughbred, is generally considered to be the foundation sire of which breed?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"970","question":"Which breed is used primarily for harness racing?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"971","question":"Which breed does the US Trotting Association represent?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"972","question":"Which breed was developed in the United States from Morgans, Thoroughbreds, Norfolk Trotters, and Canadian Pacers?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"973","question":"What are the TWO racing gaits of the Standardbred?","answer":"Trot and pace"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"974","question":"What is the term for a Standardbred that races with a diagonal gait?","answer":"Trotter (FYI:  80% of Standardbreds are pacers.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"975","question":"In reference to horse breeds, what do the initials USTA stand for?","answer":"United States Trotting Association"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"976","question":"What is the name of the breed association for the Standardbred?","answer":"United States Trotting Association (USTA)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"977","question":"The Trottingbred is a synthetic pony breed developed for sulky racing.  Similar to Standardbreds, some are trotters and other are pacers.  Standardbreds race a distance of one mile.  How far do Trottingbred ponies race?","answer":"½ mile"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"978","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is a Tennessee Walking Horse?","answer":"14.2 - 17 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"979","question":"Name 3 breeds that contributed to the development of the Tennessee Walking Horse.","answer":"Narragansett Pacer, Canadian Pacer, Standardbred, Thoroughbred, Saddlebred, Morgan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"980","question":"Name ONE of the breeds that the Tennessee Walking Horse was developed from.","answer":"Narragansett Pacer, Canadian Pacer, Standardbred, Thoroughbred, Saddlebred, Morgan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"981","question":"Where did the Orlov Trotter originate?","answer":"Russia"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"982","question":"In what US did the Tennessee Walking Horse originate?","answer":"Tennessee"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"983","question":"Which breed nods its head in rhythm with its walk?","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"984","question":"Black Allen (Allen P-1) was the foundation sire of which breed?","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"985","question":"The Tennessee Walking Horse was crossed with what other breed to develop the American Walking Pony?","answer":"Welsh Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"986","question":"Who were responsible for spreading the Spanish horses over the West?","answer":"American Indians (Apaches)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"987","question":"What is the term for a horse that was domesticated and then became wild?","answer":"Feral"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"988","question":"Name TWO feral breeds of horse or pony native to the US.","answer":"Mustang; Chincoteague Pony (MD and VA); Banker Horse (NC); Nakota Horse (SD); Cumberland Island Horse (GA); Shackelford Horse (NC), Corolla Horse (NC)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"989","question":"What is a feral horse?","answer":"Wild horse (FYI:  Feral animals are domesticated animals that live in the wild.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"990","question":"In which country did the Asiatic Wild Horse originate?","answer":"Mongolia"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"991","question":"What is the term for a wild Australian horse?","answer":"Brumby"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"992","question":"What breed of pony is the descendant of the survivors of a shipwreck off the coast of Virginia?","answer":"Chincoteague"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"993","question":"Name 3 registries for the Mustang horse.","answer":"Spanish Mustang; American Indian Horse; Chickasaw Horse; Spanish Barb; American Mustang Association; BLM"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"994","question":"Which mustang registry was started to collect and preserve the records of horses tracing to those the Indians originally obtained from Spanish herds?","answer":"American Indian Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"995","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the Spanish Mustang.","answer":"Chestnuts (small and smooth or missing); big bones; legs join chest in A shape; straight or concave forehead; convex or Roman nose; small to medium ears"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"996","question":"Who was the founder of the Spanish Mustang Registry?","answer":"Robert Brislawn"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"997","question":"What breed registry is attempting to maintain the bloodlines of horses brought to the New World by the Spanish?","answer":"Spanish Mustang Registry"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"998","question":"What is the first and oldest Mustang registry?","answer":"Spanish Mustang Registry"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"999","question":"What is the scientific name of the Przewalski's Horse?","answer":"Equus caballus przewalski"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1000","question":"What small, dun-colored, genuine wild horse was formerly abundant in southern Russia and central Asia?","answer":"Przewalski’s Horse, Mongolian Wild Horse, or Takhi (also accept Tarpan)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1001","question":"What is currently the only surviving species of wild horse native to Eastern Asia?","answer":"Przewalski’s Horse, Mongolian Wild Horse, or Takhi (Do NOT accept Tarpan which is extinct.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1002","question":"Where did the Tarpan originate?","answer":"Central Europe (FYI: The Tarpan is extinct.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1003","question":"Where is the office of the American Horse Council located?","answer":"Washington, DC"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1004","question":"What is the purpose of the American Livestock Breeds Conservancy?","answer":"Promote rare breeds of horses and livestock in the US"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1005","question":"Timeline…Place the following 4 breeds in the correct order of development beginning with the oldest breed:  Thoroughbred, Hackney, Welsh, and Arabian.","answer":"Arabian, Thoroughbred, Hackney, Welsh"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1006","question":"Identify 3 breeds from the following nicknames:  Palouse Horse, Prince of Ponies, and Breed of Blacks and Grays.","answer":"Palouse horse—Appaloosa; Prince of Ponies—Hackney Pony; Breed of Blacks and Grays—Percheron"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1007","question":"Identify 5 breeds from the following nicknames:  Peacock of the Horse World, Prince of Ponies, Breed of Blacks and Grays, Palouse Horse, and Aristocrat of the Show Ring.","answer":"Peacock of the Horse World—American Saddlebred; Prince of Ponies—Hackney Pony; Breed of Blacks and Grays—Percheron; Palouse Horse—Appaloosa; Aristocrat of the Show Ring—Hackney Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1008","question":"Identify the country of origin for 3 of the following breeds:  Bashkir Curly, Haflinger, Hanoverian, and Exmoor.","answer":"Bashkir Curly—Russia; Haflinger—Austria; Hanoverian – Germany; Exmoor—England"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"int bonus","number":"1009","question":"Name the country of origin for 3 of the following:  Connemara, Clydesdale, Hackney, Standardbred, POA, and Welsh Pony.","answer":"Connemara—Ireland, Clydesdale—Scotland, Hackney—England, Standardbred—US, POA--US, and Welsh Pony—Wales"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1010","question":"What group of people were responsible for the development of many of the American horse breeds?","answer":"Early colonists of the East Coast"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1011","question":"Name 3 breeds that are named after different US states.","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse, Missouri Fox Trotter, Colorado Ranger Horse (which is also called the Rangerbred)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1012","question":"Name 3 synthetic breeds and name the breeds they derived from.","answer":"Anglo-Arab (Thoroughbred and Arabian), Morab (Morgan and Arabian), National Show Horse (Saddlebred and Arabian), Thorcheron (Thoroughbred and Percheron), Americana Pony (Shetland and Hackney), Miniature Horse (Shetland and Falabella)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1013","question":"2 part question:  Name TWO European breeds with the leopard spotting pattern and give their countries of origin.","answer":"Noriker—Austria; Knabstrupper—Denmark"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1014","question":"How many types were recognized by the American Albino Club?","answer":"3 (three) types (FYI: white, cremello, and perlino)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1015","question":"What was the original name of the American White Horse?","answer":"American Albino"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1016","question":"Which color horses now registered as cream were originally registered as Albino types A and B?","answer":"Cremello and perlino"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1017","question":"In what US state are the headquarters for the American White and American Cream Horse Registry which was formerly called the American Albino Horse Club?","answer":"Nebraska (Naper, Nebraska)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1018","question":"Who was the foundation sire for the American Albino Horse?","answer":"Old King"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1019","question":"Why was the name of the American Albino changed to the American White Horse?","answer":"There are no true albino horses.  (FYI:  White horses have brown, blue, or hazel eyes; true albinos have no pigment in their eyes causing their eyes to look pink.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1020","question":"What is the MINIMUM height for registering a horse with the International Buckskin Association?","answer":"14 hands"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1021","question":"Name TWO colors registered in the International Buckskin Horse Association.","answer":"Buckskin, dun, grulla, red dun"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1022","question":"Name 3 disqualifications for registration in the International Buckskin Association.","answer":"Draft horse, ponies, palominos with dorsal stripes, spotting, roaning, graying"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1023","question":"What is a Sorraia? (sore-EYE-ya)","answer":"Dun or buckskin breed from Spain"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1024","question":"Which breed organization was formed in 1971 to preserve the pedigrees and promote the activities of buckskin and dun horses?","answer":"International Buckskin Horse Association"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1025","question":"True buckskin and dun horses originated from which TWO breeds?","answer":"Sorraia and Norwegian Dun (sore-EYE-ya)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1026","question":"2 part question:  Are blue eyes allowed for horses registered with the International Buckskin Horse Association and if so, are there any qualifications?","answer":"Yes; as long as conformation and body color are acceptable"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1027","question":"The breed description of a Palomino describes the ideal color to be what?","answer":"Color of a newly minted gold coin"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1028","question":"Palomino horses in Spain at the time of Queen Isabella were known by what name?","answer":"Golden Isabellas"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1029","question":"What is one version of the origination of the name Palomino?","answer":"Named after the California golden grape called a palomino"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1030","question":"In the history of Spain during the reign of Queen Isabella, what current breed of horses was known as Golden Isabellas?","answer":"Palomino"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1031","question":"Into which Pinto breed conformation type would a horse of Thoroughbred breeding fit?","answer":"Hunter"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1032","question":"What is the difference between a Paint and a Pinto?","answer":"Pinto is a spotted horse; Paint can only have Thoroughbred, Quarter Horse, or Paint breeding."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1033","question":"Arabian or Morgan type horses would fit into which Pinto breed conformation type?","answer":"Pleasure"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1034","question":"Which Pinto breed conformation type would be represented by a horse of Saddlebred, Hackney, or Tennessee Walking Horse breeding?","answer":"Saddle"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1035","question":"Which Pinto breed conformation type would be represented by a horse of Quarter Horse breeding?","answer":"Stock"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1036","question":"Name 3 conformation types of the Pinto.","answer":"Stock, pleasure, saddle, hunter"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1037","question":"What do you call a horse with ancestry from the draft breeds?","answer":"Cold blooded"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1038","question":"In reference to horses, what does the term \"cold blooded\" mean?","answer":"Draft horse breeding"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1039","question":"Giving only one number, what is the general height of a draft horse in hands?","answer":"16 - 19 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1040","question":"What is the general weight for the draft breeds?","answer":"1600 - 2000 pounds (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1041","question":"What is the general term for large, heavy-boned work horses that usually weigh 2000 pounds and stand 17 - 18 hands tall?","answer":"Draft horses"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1042","question":"As the colonies developed in the New World, farmers in New York and Pennsylvania needed heavy horses that could till the soil and haul products to market.  Name 3 breeds imported for this purpose.","answer":"Belgian, Percheron, Clydesdale, Shire"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1043","question":"During the early 1900s, there were 21 million horses in the United States.  What type were the majority of these horses?","answer":"Draft or work horses (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1044","question":"Identify this breed:  weighs 1400 - 2000 pounds; 15.1 - 16.3 hands tall; traces back to a foundation mare from Iowa; only draft breed developed in the US; cream in color.","answer":"American Cream Draft"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1045","question":"Which breed is the only draft breed that originated in America?","answer":"American Cream Draft (FYI:  American Cream Draft breed originated in the early 1900’s from a mare named Old Granny who had a champagne dilution gene.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1046","question":"What color is an American Cream Draft horse?","answer":"Cream color with white mane and tail (also has pink skin and amber eyes)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"int bonus","number":"1047","question":"Give 3 characteristics of the American Cream Draft Horse.","answer":"Cream colored body, cream or white mane and tail, pink skin, amber eyes"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1048","question":"Based on registry, which draft breed is the MOST numerous in the US?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1049","question":"Which draft breed is a descendant of the Great Horse of Flanders?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1050","question":"Which of these two breeds does NOT have a long, springy stride with extreme flexion of the knees and hocks, Belgian or Clydesdale?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1051","question":"What is the main color of the Belgian?","answer":"Light sorrel with flaxen mane and tail"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1052","question":"Name TWO colors of the Clydesdale.","answer":"Bay, chestnut, black, brown, occasional roan"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1053","question":"Which draft breed is famous for being used in multi-horse hitches, especially one advertising a brewery?","answer":"Clydesdale"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1054","question":"Identify this draft breed:  has a long stride with extreme flexion; has extensive white face and leg markings; has long, silky hair on the lower legs; originated in Scotland.","answer":"Clydesdale"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1055","question":"Where did the Clydesdale originate?","answer":"Scotland (near the River Clyde)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1056","question":"This type of horse never had a breed registry established, but it was the only heavy type of horse developed in the eastern United States.  What is its name?","answer":"Conestoga Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1057","question":"Where was the Conestoga Horse bred?","answer":"Southern Pennsylvania"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1058","question":"What is the term for the long hair around horses' fetlocks that’s common in draft breeds?","answer":"Feathers or feathering"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1059","question":"What is feathering?","answer":"Long, silky hair on the lower legs"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1060","question":"Which TWO draft breeds do NOT have feathering on their legs?","answer":"Percheron and Suffolk"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1061","question":"Name TWO breeds of draft horses that have feathering on their lower legs.","answer":"Shire; Clydesdale"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1062","question":"What breed of horse was developed in Northern Holland as a war horse, has a distinctive flowing trot, and is described as a black horse with feathering on the legs?","answer":"Friesian (FYI:  Friesians may have small white stars on their foreheads.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1063","question":"Modern draft horses are descendants of what earlier group of horses?","answer":"Great Horses or knights' horses of the Middle Ages (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1064","question":"Name ONE draft breed that is a descendant of the English Great Horse.","answer":"Shire; Clydesdale"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1065","question":"How many MAJOR draft breeds are found in the US?","answer":"5 (five) (FYI: Clydesdale, Shire, Belgian, Percheron, and Suffolk)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1066","question":"Name 3 of the 5 major breeds of draft horses.","answer":"Shire, Percheron, Clydesdale, Belgian, Suffolk"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1067","question":"Name TWO colors the Percheron.","answer":"Black and gray (occasionally bay, sorrel, and roan)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1068","question":"Name 3 characteristics of Percherons.","answer":"Considerable knee action, bold trot, no feathers on legs, speed at the walk"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1069","question":"Where did the Percheron originate?","answer":"France (La Perche, France)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1070","question":"What are TWO uses of the Percheron?","answer":"General draft work, driving, crossbred with Thoroughbreds to produce jumpers"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1071","question":"Name TWO features that made the Percheron a popular draft breed.","answer":"Lack of feathering on legs; speed at the walk; bold trot"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1072","question":"Which draft breed is thought to be the only one with any Arabian or Barb blood?","answer":"Percheron"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1073","question":"Which draft breed is known as the \"breed of blacks and grays\"?","answer":"Percheron"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1074","question":"What is the most common color of the Shire?","answer":"Black (FYI:  Shires can also be brown, gray, and bay.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1075","question":"Where did the Shire get its name?","answer":"English Shires (specifically Lincolnshire and Cambridgeshire)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1076","question":"Which draft breed is generally the tallest?","answer":"Shire"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1077","question":"What is the color of the Suffolk?","answer":"Chestnut or sorrel"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1078","question":"What breed is being described?  This draft breed is a descendant of the medieval charger breed.  Its color is all shades of chestnut.  It originated in Suffolk County, England.","answer":"Suffolk (Suffolk Punch)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1079","question":"Cosmetically speaking, how does the Suffolk differ from the other two British draft breeds?","answer":"Suffolk doesn't have feathering on its legs."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1080","question":"Because of its rounded or \"punched up\" appearance, what was the Suffolk originally called?","answer":"Suffolk Punch (FYI: It's now just called the Suffolk.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1081","question":"Where did the Suffolk originate?","answer":"Suffolk, England"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1082","question":"A horse under 14.2 hands is called what?","answer":"Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1083","question":"You are looking at a sale poster for a pretty chestnut mare.  The information states that the animal is 57 inches tall.  Is the mare a horse or a pony?","answer":"Pony (FYI: The dividing line is 58 inches or 14.2 hands.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1084","question":"Name 3 breeds of pony.","answer":"Shetland, Welsh, Connemara, POA, Hackney, Chincoteague, Exmoor, Dales, Quarter Pony, New Forest, American Sport Pony, Dartmoor, Fells, Gotland (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1085","question":"Name TWO breeds of pony.","answer":"Shetland, Welsh, Connemara, POA, Hackney, Chincoteague, Exmoor, Dales, Quarter Pony, New Forest, American Sport Pony, Dartmoor, Fells, Gotland (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1086","question":"What breed of show pony was produced by crossing Hackney and Shetland ponies?","answer":"Americana"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1087","question":"What TWO breeds were crossed to develop the Americana?","answer":"Shetland Pony and Hackney Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1088","question":"Which breed originated in County Galway, Ireland?","answer":"Connemara"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1089","question":"Where did the Connemara Pony originate?","answer":"Ireland (County Galway)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1090","question":"Connemara ponies are noted for what ability?","answer":"Jumping ability"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1091","question":"What colors are ineligible for registration in the Connemara breed?","answer":"Spotted horses and blue-eyed creams"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1092","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Connemara Pony?","answer":"13 hands to over 15 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1093","question":"Name this breed of pony:  known for its solid build, endurance, and calm, agreeable nature; used as pack ponies in the lead mining industry; originated in the dales of Great Britain.","answer":"Dales Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1094","question":"Which pony breed is often referred to as a \"living fossil\"?","answer":"Exmoor Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1095","question":"From where did the Exmoor Pony get its name?","answer":"Moorlands known as Exmoor (in southwest England)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1096","question":"Name TWO characteristics Exmoor ponies developed that help them survive harsh winter conditions.","answer":"Double layer coat; toad eye (pronounced brow to keep out elements); snow chute tail (short hairs at the base of the tail to keep out elements)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1097","question":"Give 3 characteristics of the Exmoor Pony.","answer":"Primitive coat pattern (buff coloring around eyes, muzzle, belly and flank); broad forehead; toad or hooded eye (pronounced brow); low tail set; double layer coat; snow chute or ice tail (short hairs at the base of the tail); uniformity of appearance"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1098","question":"What is meant by the term \"toad eye\"?","answer":"Pronounced eyebrow of the Exmoor Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1099","question":"Which breed can be traced through archeological records to England over 60,000 years ago, making it a contemporary of the Przewalski’s Horse?","answer":"Exmoor Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1100","question":"Which breed was first recorded in the Doomsday book of 1085?","answer":"Exmoor Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1101","question":"What is the main limitation to the Exmoor Pony Registry?","answer":"Limited to descendants of moor ponies that have not been improved with any other breed additions"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1102","question":"Name 3 things that are considered signs of impurity and will result in denying registration for an Exmoor Pony.","answer":"White markings; white hairs on the body, mane, or tail; hooves with white soles"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1103","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Exmoor Pony?","answer":"11.2 – 12.3 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1104","question":"Describe the coloring of the Fjord.","answer":"Dun with dun characteristics of mane and tail frosting, dorsal stripes,  and zebra stripes"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1105","question":"Which modern breed resembles the wild horse of the Middle Ages?","answer":"Fjord"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1106","question":"Identify this breed: sometimes used as a pack animal; resembles the wild horses of the Ice Age; dun color with black and silver mane and tail and dun markings; country of origin is Norway.","answer":"Fjord"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1107","question":"What are the colors of the Galiceño?","answer":"All SOLID colors (NO spotted horses, pintos, Appaloosa patterns)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1108","question":"Identify the following breed. This pony-sized equine originated in Spain as a result of Spanish Jennet and Barb breeding. It performs four natural gaits that include the walk, trot, canter, and running walk.","answer":"Galiceño"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1109","question":"The Galiceño may naturally trot and/or exhibit which other intermediate gait?","answer":"Running walk (also accept paso gait)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1110","question":"Galiceños have been imported into the US since 1959 from which country?","answer":"Mexico"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1111","question":"Where did the Galiceño originate?","answer":"Spain"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1112","question":"Giving only one number, what is the height of the Galiceño?","answer":"12 - 13.2 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1113","question":"Giving only one number, what is the weight of the Galiceño?","answer":"600 - 700 pounds (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1114","question":"What breed is referred to as \"Skogruss\" in their homeland?","answer":"Gotland"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1115","question":"Which breed served as a mount for the Goths and Vikings and can be traced as far back as the Stone Age?","answer":"Gotland"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1116","question":"Which breed is considered a Swedish national treasure?","answer":"Gotland"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1117","question":"Where did the Gotland Horse originate?","answer":"Sweden"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1118","question":"What percent of Hackney registrations each year are ponies?","answer":"95%"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1119","question":"At breed shows, Hackney ponies are divided into TWO types.  What are they?","answer":"Cob tail and long tail (FYI:  Hackney Pony divisions:  Roadster under 13 hands, Cob Tail 14.2 and under, Harness Pony (Long Tail) 12.2 hands and under, Pleasure Pony 14.2 hands and under and In-Hand Pony for weanlings to 2 year olds.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1120","question":"What is the main use of the Hackney Pony?","answer":"Driving (FYI: Hackney ponies are often too spirited to be used as children's mounts.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1121","question":"Which breed is known as the \"Prince of Ponies\"?","answer":"Hackney Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1122","question":"Which breed was crossed with the Hackney horse to produce the Hackney pony?","answer":"Welsh Pony (also accept Fell Pony)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1123","question":"Where did the Haflinger originate?","answer":"Austria (FYI: Haflingers are from the South Tyrol region of Austria and northern Italy.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1124","question":"What is the small, general purpose mountain horse from Austria that resembles a small Belgian?","answer":"Haflinger"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1125","question":"What is the country of origin for the New Forest Pony?","answer":"England"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1126","question":"What is the primary use of the POA?","answer":"Children's mount (FYI: POA is the Pony of the Americas.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1127","question":"Referring to horse breeds, what do the letters POA mean?","answer":"Pony of the Americas"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1128","question":"What was the principal reason for the development of the POA?","answer":"To develop a medium-sized Western-type pony that's small enough for children to ride and large enough for adults to train"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1129","question":"Where did the POA or Pony of the Americas originate?","answer":"United States (Mason City, Iowa)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1130","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the POA.","answer":"Mottled skin, white sclera around the eyes, striped hooves, approved coat pattern"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1131","question":"Which breed of pony is colored similar to an Appaloosa?","answer":"POA (Pony of the Americas)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1132","question":"Identify the PONY described by the following characteristics.  Mottled skin around the muzzle, eyes, and genital area, white sclera encircling the eyes, striped hooves, and one of 7 approved coat patterns.","answer":"POA (Pony of the Americas)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1133","question":"Who was Black Hand?","answer":"Foundation sire of the POA"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1134","question":"Black Hand, the foundation sire of the POA, was the result of a cross between an Appaloosa mare and what breed of stallion?","answer":"Shetland Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1135","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the POA or Pony of the Americas?","answer":"46 - 56 inches or 11.2 - 14 hands (accept any number within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1136","question":"Give ONE primary use of the Shetland Pony.","answer":"Children's mounts or driving"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1137","question":"The name Shetland came from an old Norse word meaning what?","answer":"Highland"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1138","question":"Where did the Shetland Pony originate?","answer":"Shetland Isles (off the coast of Scotland)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1139","question":"What pony originated in the Shetland Isles?","answer":"Shetland Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1140","question":"2 part question:  What are the TWO body types of the Shetland Pony and describe each?","answer":"Classic, Island, or Draft type are short and chunky; Modern or American type are fine boned, long-necked, and high stepping."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1141","question":"An influx of which breed can be seen in the American type of Shetland Pony?","answer":"Hackney"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1142","question":"What are the colors of the Shetland Pony?","answer":"ALL colors"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1143","question":"What is the UPPER height limit for a Shetland Pony?","answer":"46 inches or 11.2 hands (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1144","question":"What are the disqualifications for registering the Shetland Pony?","answer":"If it's over 46 inches or 11.2 hands in height."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"novice","number":"1145","question":"What is a distinguishing characteristic of the Shetland Pony?","answer":"Its small size"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1146","question":"Where did the Welsh Pony originate?","answer":"Wales"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1147","question":"All horses registered in this breed trace back to horses that roamed free on the hills of Wales before the time of the Romans.  Which breed is it?","answer":"Welsh Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1148","question":"What are the colors of the Welsh Pony?","answer":"All SOLID colors (NO spotted horses or pintos)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1149","question":"What color pattern is NOT permitted in the Welsh Pony breed?","answer":"Any spotted patterns"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1150","question":"Name 3 sections of the Welsh Pony and Cob registry.","answer":"Welsh Mountain Pony (Section A), Welsh Pony (Section  B), Welsh Pony of Cob Type (Section C), Welsh Cob (Section D) (accept either the name or the section)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1151","question":"What is a Welsh Cob?","answer":"Larger version of the Welsh Pony (over 13.2 hands with no upper height limit)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1152","question":"What is the upper height limit for a Welsh Cob?","answer":"No upper height limit"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1153","question":"What is the height limit for registering a section A Welsh Pony or Welsh Mountain Pony?","answer":"12.2 hands"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1154","question":"What is the most common color of the Welsh Mountain Pony?","answer":"Gray (FYI: The Welsh Mountain Pony is a Section A Welsh Pony.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1155","question":"What is another name for the Section A Welsh Pony?","answer":"Welsh Mountain Pony"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1156","question":"Give 3 uses of the Miniature Horse.","answer":"Companions; driving; circus; in-hand jumping; in-hand trail; halter; showmanship (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1157","question":"Which breed was developed from small English and Dutch mine horses?","answer":"Miniature Horse"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1158","question":"Where did the Falabella originate?","answer":"Argentina"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1159","question":"Which one of the following breeds would NOT be considered a pony breed:  Exmoor, Falabella, or Trottingbred?","answer":"Falabella"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1160","question":"What is the small horse breed from Argentina that’s noted for its excellent conformation and its extremely small size?","answer":"Falabella"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1161","question":"Approximately how much does an average mature American Miniature Horse weigh?","answer":"200 - 350 pounds (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1162","question":"What is the maximum height for a horse registered in the American Miniature Horse Association?","answer":"34 inches (FYI: American Miniature Horse REGISTRY Division B horses are 34 - 38 inches tall.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1163","question":"An American Miniature Horse is registered on a temporary basis until it reaches 3 years of age. What requirement must it meet at that time to be permanently registered in the American Miniature Horse Association?","answer":"Not exceed the 34 inch height requirement (FYI:  For the AMHA, height must not exceed 34 inches at 3 years of age.  For the AMHR, Division A Minis are up to 34 inches and Division B Minis are between 34 and 38 inches tall.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1164","question":"How much does a Miniature Horse foal weigh at birth?","answer":"15 - 30 pounds (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1165","question":"What is the average height for a newborn Miniature Horse?","answer":"18 inches"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1166","question":"What would you call the offspring of a mule and hinny?","answer":"A miracle! (impossible because both are sterile)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1167","question":"What is a Spotted Ass?","answer":"Ass (donkey, mule, or hinny) that has a spotted coat (FYI:  must have at least two spots behind the throatlatch and above the knees)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1168","question":"What is the term for the vocal sound made by a jack?","answer":"Bray"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1169","question":"What is the main use of the Mammoth Jack?","answer":"Crossbreeding with horses to produce mules"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1170","question":"What animal is known for a dorsal stripe that is intersected by the arms of a cross at the withers?","answer":"Donkey"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"int bonus","number":"1171","question":"Give 3 differences between a horse and a donkey.","answer":"Donkey has longer ears, sparser mane and tail, stiffer and more upright mane, smaller hooves, rounder hooves, straighter neck and back, less chestnuts, lighter color muzzle and underbelly, shorter gestation period, brays instead of whinnies"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1172","question":"What is the legend associated with the cross on the donkey's back?","answer":"Donkey's reward for carrying Mary to Bethlehem and Jesus to Jerusalem"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1173","question":"Where does the name \"donkey\" come from?","answer":"English word \"dun\" which describes their usual color"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1174","question":"What do you call a male donkey?","answer":"Jack"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1175","question":"What do you call a female donkey?","answer":"Jenny or jennet"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1176","question":"What is the COMMON name for a female of the species Equus asinus?","answer":"Jenny or jennet"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1177","question":"Name 3 of the 5 classifications of donkeys based on size.","answer":"Miniature, Small Standard, Standard, Large Standard, Mammoth"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1178","question":"What is the term used for the feral donkeys of the American Southwest?","answer":"Burro"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1179","question":"The terms donkey and burro historically have often been used synonymously.  What differentiates the use of these terms today?","answer":"Burro is used to describe the feral animal; donkey is used to describe the domesticated animal."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1180","question":"What is a burro?","answer":"Feral donkey or Spanish term for donkey (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1181","question":"The burro's ancestors came to North America with whom?","answer":"Spanish explorers"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1182","question":"What do you call a cross between a stallion and a jennet?","answer":"Hinny"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1183","question":"Where did the Miniature Donkey originate?","answer":"Mediterranean area (Sicily and Sardinia)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1184","question":"What is a mule?","answer":"Cross between a jack and a mare"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1185","question":"Who was the first breeder of mules in North America?","answer":"George Washington"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"1186","question":"What are 3 uses of the mule?","answer":"Saddle, packing, draft or farm work, driving, showing, pets"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1187","question":"Explain the difference in the parentage of a mule and a hinny.","answer":"Mule is a cross between a jack and a mare; hinny is a cross between a stallion and a jenny or jennet."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1188","question":"What is the result of breeding a horse to a donkey?","answer":"Mule or hinny (accept either)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1189","question":"What would be the result of crossing a zebra and a horse?","answer":"Zebrass, zorse, or zebroid (accept any)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1190","question":"The Hanoverian, Trakehner, and Holsteiner breeds developed in which country?","answer":"Germany"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1191","question":"Name 3 German Warmblood breeds that are usually used for dressage.","answer":"Hanoverian, Holsteiner, Trakehner, Oldenburg"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"easy","number":"1192","question":"In reference to horses, what is a Warmblood?","answer":"Horse that is a combination of hot blooded and cold blooded breeds."},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1193","question":"The American Warmblood Society (AWS) is focused on the qualities and/or performance of the sport horse. What are 3 disciplines that the AWS supports?","answer":"Dressage; Show Jumping; Eventing; Combined Driving (FYI:  AWS registers ponies and horses 12.2 hands and over.  AWS focuses on the qualities of sport horses and ponies instead of their sizes and breeding.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"intermediate","number":"1194","question":"What color is the Friesian?","answer":"Black (FYI: Solid black with no white markings is preferred.)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1195","question":"Where did the Friesian originate?","answer":"Holland (Netherlands)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1196","question":"What is the most numerous light horse breed in Europe?","answer":"Hanoverian"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"hard","number":"1197","question":"Which breed was developed by crossing the Thoroughbred and Irish Draft breeds?","answer":"Irish Hunter, Irish Sport Horse, or Irish Warmblood (accept any)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1198","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Trakehner? (tra-KAY-ner)","answer":"16 - 17 hands (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1199","question":"Because of its elegant way of moving, the Trakehner excels in what discipline? (tra-KAY-ner)","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1200","question":"Which breed is a major contributor to all other German warmblood breeds?","answer":"Trakehner (tra-KAY-ner)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"medium","number":"1201","question":"What breed is branded on the left hip with a double moose antler brand?","answer":"Trakehner (tra-KAY-ner)"},
{"category":"Breeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"1202","question":"Because stallions are so important to the breed, 2 ½ year old Trakehner stallions must be inspected and approved for what 3 things in order to be registered?","answer":"Type; conformation; size; bone; temperament; way of going in all 3 gaits(FYI:  Once approved, the stallions must then complete a combined training performance test before the age of 6.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1203","question":"How many basic coat colors are there?","answer":"5 (five) (FYI: black, bay brown, chestnut or sorrel, white)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1204","question":"What is the difference in coloring between a bay and a chestnut?","answer":"Bays have black points (mane, tail, and lower legs); chestnuts have red, reddish brown, or flaxen manes and tails"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1205","question":"How can you tell whether a horse is black or seal brown?","answer":"Black horses have no areas of brown; seal brown horses have tan or brown hairs on their muzzle, flanks, and/or buttocks."},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1206","question":"Name the 5 basic coat colors.","answer":"Black, brown, bay, chestnut or sorrel, white"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1207","question":"You are looking at two horses.  Both are reddish brown.  One has black points and the other does not.  What are the basic colors of these horses?","answer":"Horse with black points is a bay; other horse is a chestnut or sorrel."},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1208","question":"What color is a horse that has a reddish brown body and a black mane and tail?","answer":"Bay"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1209","question":"Describe the color bay.","answer":"Body is reddish brown;  mane, tail, and lower legs (points) are black."},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1210","question":"What color horse has a black body, black mane and tail, and NO areas of brown?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1211","question":"Many brown horses are mistakenly called what color?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1212","question":"What color horse has a black mane and tail and a body color of black with brown areas on the muzzle, eyes, flanks, and buttocks?","answer":"Brown or seal brown (accept either)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1213","question":"What color are the muzzle and the flanks of a brown horse?","answer":"Brown or tan (accept either)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1214","question":"Describe the color chestnut.","answer":"Body is some shade of red or reddish brown; mane and tail are red, reddish brown or flaxen"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1215","question":"What term describes both a horse color and a horny growth found on the inside of a horse's legs?","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1216","question":"What color horse is red or reddish brown with a red, reddish brown, or flaxen mane and tail?","answer":"Chestnut or sorrel (accept either)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1217","question":"A chestnut horse whose mane and tail are lighter in color than the body is called what?","answer":"Flaxen"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1218","question":"Give ONE name for a very dark, chocolate shade of chestnut.","answer":"Liver chestnut or black chestnut"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1219","question":"When referring to chestnut horses, what does the term “tostada” mean?","answer":"Red colored horse with darker red colored points"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1220","question":"When referring to chestnut horses, what does the term \"ruano\" mean?","answer":"Red colored horse with lighter points or a flaxen mane and tail"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1221","question":"In reference to chestnut horses, what does the term “alazán” mean?","answer":"Red colored horse with red mane and tail (FYI:  Old Sorrel from the King Ranch was called El Alazán Viejo.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1222","question":"When referring to color, what is another name for chestnut?","answer":"Sorrel"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1223","question":"Name ONE eye color of white horses.","answer":"Brown, hazel or blue (accept any)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1224","question":"What is a \"true white horse\"?","answer":"Horse that is born white and dies white (also accept a horse with white hair, pink skin, and brown, blue, or hazel eyes)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1225","question":"What color horse is known as the horse of heroes, history, art, and fiction?","answer":"White"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1226","question":"2 part question:  At birth, what color is the coat of a true white horse and what color is its skin?","answer":"White coat; pink skin"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1227","question":"Give 3 characteristics of true white horses.","answer":"White hair; pink skin; brown, blue, or hazel eyes; born white and dies white"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1228","question":"Why are white horses NOT considered albinos?","answer":"White horses have pigmented eyes.  (FYI:  True albino animals have pink eyes with no pigment.  There are no true albino horses.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1229","question":"How many major variations of horse coat colors are there?","answer":"5 (five) (FYI: buckskin or dun, palomino, paint or pinto, roan, gray)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1230","question":"Name the 5 major variations of coat colors.","answer":"Buckskin or dun, palomino, gray, roan, paint or pinto"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1231","question":"Name 3 of the 5 major variations of coat colors.","answer":"Buckskin or dun, palomino, gray, roan, paint or pinto"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1232","question":"Both gray and roan horses are a mixture of white and colored hairs.  What is the difference between these two colors?","answer":"Gray horses get progressively lighter with age; roan horses stay the same color"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1233","question":"Describe the color buckskin.","answer":"Body color is some shade of yellow or gold; mane, tail, and lower legs are black.  (FYI:  Buckskin color resembles the color of a newly tanned deer hide.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1234","question":"Which color is described as the color of a \"newly tanned deer hide\" with black points?","answer":"Buckskin"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1235","question":"Besides a “classic” yellow dun, name 3 types of dun horses.","answer":"Zebra dun, grulla, red dun, brindle dun, claybank, apricot dun, coyote dun, fox dun, bay dun, blue dun, mouse dun, lobo dun"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1236","question":"Identify the following coat color:  body color is yellowish or gold; mane and tail may be black, red, or frosted; has a dorsal stripe; usually has zebra stripes on the legs and transverse stripe over the withers.","answer":"Dun (also called classic or coyote dun) [Buckskins do NOT have dorsal stripes, zebra stripes, and mane and tail frosting.]"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1237","question":"What type of red dun has a body color of light copper and a mane and tail that are a darker shade?","answer":"Claybank dun"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1238","question":"Describe the color claybank dun.","answer":"Very light red or light copper dun (with darker mane, tail, and lower legs and red dorsal stripe)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1239","question":"What canine term, describes a dun horse with black points and a black dorsal stripe?","answer":"Coyote dun"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1240","question":"What is a “coyote dun”?","answer":"Dun horse with black points and a black dorsal stripe"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1241","question":"Identify the following coat color:  body appears smoky or mouse colored; mane, tail, and lower legs are black; has a dorsal stripe; usually has zebra stripes.","answer":"Grulla"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1242","question":"Describe the color grulla.","answer":"Type of dun that is mouse-colored and has black points, dorsal stripe, and may have other dun markings"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1243","question":"What are the TWO most common dorsal stripe colors?","answer":"Black and red"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1244","question":"What is the term for a dark line over the withers from side to side?","answer":"Cross or transverse stripe"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1245","question":"In reference to coat color markings, what is a \"line back\"?","answer":"Dark line running along the back from the mane to the tail (a dorsal stripe)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1246","question":"Describe an \"eel stripe\".","answer":"Dark stripe down the horse's back from the mane to the tail (also called a dorsal stripe or line back)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1247","question":"In reference to horse coat colors, what does the term \"zebra\" mean?","answer":"Dark stripes on the legs and/or withers"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1248","question":"In order to be registered as a dun, a grulla must have what?","answer":"Dorsal stripe (also called line back or eel stripe)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1249","question":"The coat color of a dun and grulla are different, however, they both have what characteristic marking?","answer":"Dorsal stripe (Do NOT accept black points because red duns and have dark red points.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1250","question":"What marking is a continuous black or red stripe running down the horse's back from the mane to the tail?","answer":"Dorsal stripe, eel stripe, or line back (accept any)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1251","question":"Give TWO terms that mean a dark line running down the back from the mane to tail.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, line-back, eel stripe"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1252","question":"Name 3 dun factors.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, zebra stripes, cross or transverse stripe, black ear tips, cobwebbing on face, mane and tail frosting (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1253","question":"Name 4 primitive markings of the horse or ass.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, zebra stripes, cross or transverse stripe, cobwebbing or spider webbing on forehead, countershading, zippers, dorsal or rib bars, neck striping or shadowing, mask, ear tips or edging, guard hairs in mane and tail"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1254","question":"What is a zebra dun horse?","answer":"Dun horse with zebra stripes on the legs and/or withers"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1255","question":"What is a brindle dun horse?","answer":"Dun horse with zebra stripes or teardrop markings on its body"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1256","question":"Be specific:  A red dorsal stripe appears with which coat color?","answer":"Red dun, claybank dun, or apricot dun (accept any)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1257","question":"The unusual markings of a brindle dun can appear as what?","answer":"Teardrops or zebra stripes (accept either)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1258","question":"What do most grulla horses have on their legs and withers?","answer":"Zebra stripes"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1259","question":"What term means dark stripes on the legs and/or withers?","answer":"Zebra stripes"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1260","question":"Describe the color red dun.","answer":"Body color is reddish orange or reddish yellow; mane and tail are dark red; has a red dorsal stripe"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1261","question":"Name 3 color variations of a gray horse.","answer":"Dapple gray, flea-bitten gray, steel gray, rose gray, rosettes, iron gray"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1262","question":"What color does the following describe?   The foal's coat will be a solid color, but with each consecutive hair coat, more white hairs are added.","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1263","question":"Most so-called \"white\" horses are really which color?","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1264","question":"What causes a gray horse's coat to lighten with age?","answer":"More white hairs growing into the coat"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1265","question":"On what coat color is dappling most easy to see?","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1266","question":"Describe a dappled gray horse.","answer":"Gray horse with spots on its coat that are a different shade of gray (can be darker or lighter)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1267","question":"Describe a flea-bitten gray horse.","answer":"Gray horse with small black or reddish specks on a white background"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1268","question":"What is the base color of a rose gray horse?","answer":"Chestnut or bay (accept either)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1269","question":"The gray color pattern on a bay or chestnut horse is called what type of gray?","answer":"Rose gray"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1270","question":"What term refers to bursts of white on a gray coat color?","answer":"Rosettes"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1271","question":"What is the term used for a gray horse that has a lot of black in his coat?","answer":"Steel gray or iron gray"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1272","question":"Dark hairs in the mane or tail of a palomino must NOT exceed what percent?","answer":"15%"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1273","question":"Describe the color palomino.","answer":"Body is some shade of yellow (color of a newly minted gold coin); mane and tail are white"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1274","question":"What color horse has a golden body color and white mane and tail?","answer":"Palomino"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1275","question":"Describe the color pinto.","answer":"Combination of white and colored markings in irregular patches or spots"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1276","question":"The word \"pinto\" is derived from a Spanish word meaning what?","answer":"Painted, paint or spotted   (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1277","question":"Roan horses have a combination of white and colored hairs.  What are the 3 most common BASE colors of a roan?","answer":"Black, bay, and chestnut"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1278","question":"2 part question:  Name the 3 types of roan horses and name the base color for each.","answer":"Blue roan—base color is black; bay or red roan—base color is bay; strawberry or red roan—base color is chestnut"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1279","question":"What are the 3 color variations that describe a roan?","answer":"Blue, red or bay, strawberry or red"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1280","question":"Name TWO areas that are generally darker or more solid colored on a roan horse.","answer":"Head, neck, lower legs, mane, tail"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1281","question":"Describe a roan horse.","answer":"Mixture of white and colored hairs (darker on head, neck, and legs; doesn't get lighter with age)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1282","question":"Red, strawberry, and blue are variations of which color?","answer":"Roan"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1283","question":"What is another name for a bay roan?","answer":"Red roan"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1284","question":"Describe the color blue roan.","answer":"Roan horse with a mixture of black and white hairs (darker on the head, neck, and lower legs; doesn't get lighter with age)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1285","question":"Name this color.  The base color is chestnut with a uniform mix of white hairs on the body.  The head, neck, and legs are darker.  Its color does NOT get lighter with age.","answer":"Strawberry roan or red roan (accept either)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1286","question":"Describe the difference between a stripe and a blaze.","answer":"Blaze is wider (covers the width of the nasal bones)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1287","question":"Name the 5 white FACIAL markings.","answer":"Star, stripe, snip, blaze, bald face"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1288","question":"Name 3 of the 5 white FACIAL markings.","answer":"Star, stripe, snip, blaze, bald face"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1289","question":"What facial marking has white covering most of the flat surface of the face?","answer":"Bald face"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1290","question":"Which of the 5 white face markings has the LARGEST white area?","answer":"Bald face"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1291","question":"Describe the marking bald face.","answer":"White over the entire face (FYI:  White may extend down the sides of the head, over the eyes, and underneath the jaw.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1292","question":"What do you call a wide white stripe running down the face to the lips?","answer":"Blaze (FYI: Blaze is wider than the nasal bones.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1293","question":"To be classified as a blaze, the white must cover the full width of which bones?","answer":"Nasal"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1294","question":"Describe the facial marking blaze.","answer":"Wide white stripe running down the face to the lips (FYI: Blaze is wider than the nasal bones.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1295","question":"Describe the facial marking flame.","answer":"A few white hairs in the middle of the forehead"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1296","question":"The mealy mouthed description is most likely to be found in what color horse?","answer":"Bay or brown/seal brown (accept either)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1297","question":"In references to facial coloration, describe “mealy mouthed”.","answer":"Faded out color around the horse's mouth (brown or tan hairs on the horse’s muzzle)."},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1298","question":"What is the term for faded out color around the horse's mouth?","answer":"Mealy mouth"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1299","question":"Name 3 face markings that have more white than a blaze.","answer":"Bald face, bonnet face, apron face"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1300","question":"Describe the facial marking snip.","answer":"Patch of white hairs on the muzzle"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1301","question":"What facial marking has a patch of white hairs on the muzzle that may include white on the lips?","answer":"Snip"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1302","question":"Describe the facial marking star.","answer":"Patch of white hairs on the forehead"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1303","question":"What is the term for a patch of white located between a horse's eyes?","answer":"Star"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1304","question":"Describe the facial marking stripe.","answer":"Long, narrow band of white from the forehead down towards the muzzle"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1305","question":"What do you call a long, narrow band of white running from the forehead down towards the muzzle?","answer":"Stripe"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1306","question":"Name 3 of the 5 white LEG markings.","answer":"Coronet, pastern, sock or ankle, half stocking, full stocking"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1307","question":"Name the 5 white LEG markings.","answer":"Coronet, pastern, sock, half stocking, full stocking"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1308","question":"Name 3 types of leg markings other than the 5 main white markings.","answer":"Distal or ermine spots, inside heel, outside heel, zebra stripes"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1309","question":"In general, the terms ankle, pastern, zebra stripes, and distal spots share what common characteristic?","answer":"They are all types of leg markings."},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1310","question":"What white leg marking is a narrow band of white just above the hoof?","answer":"Coronet"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1311","question":"Describe the leg marking coronet.","answer":"White covers the coronet band"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1312","question":"What are distal spots?","answer":"Dark spots on a white coronet or pastern"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1313","question":"A chestnut horse has a hind leg with white that extends to the pastern.  In this white area there are liver-colored spots.  What is the term for these spots?","answer":"Distal spots, ermine spots, or Belton spots (accept any)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1314","question":"What leg marking has white extending from the coronet to and including the knee or hock?","answer":"Full stocking"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1315","question":"Describe a full stocking.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to and including the knee or hock"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1316","question":"What leg marking is white from the coronet to the middle of the cannon?","answer":"Half stocking"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1317","question":"Describe a half stocking.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to the middle of the cannon"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1318","question":"What white leg marking extends from the coronet to and including the pastern?","answer":"Pastern"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1319","question":"Describe the leg marking pastern.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to and including the pastern"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1320","question":"What white leg marking extends from the coronet to the fetlock?","answer":"Sock"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1321","question":"Describe the leg marking sock.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to and including the fetlock"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1322","question":"What is the term for a mane that is blonde or straw-colored?","answer":"Flaxen"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1323","question":"What does the term \"flaxen\" mean?","answer":"Mane and tail are \"blonde\", straw-colored, light yellow, or whitish (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1324","question":"Where are the \"black points\" on a horse?","answer":"Mane, tail, and lower legs"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1325","question":"Which term means a mane or tail that is white with a few black hairs?","answer":"Silver"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"novice","number":"1326","question":"Name ONE color of horse that ALWAYS has black points.","answer":"Bay, brown, buckskin, grulla, and “classic” dun, NOT red dun"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1327","question":"A dark colored (usually red or brown) splotch on the base coat color is called what?","answer":"Blood mark or handprint"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1328","question":"On which breed of horse could you find a \"blue zone\"?","answer":"Paint or Pinto"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1329","question":"On a roan horse, scars grow back as small, base-colored spots on the roan background.  What are these dark spots called?","answer":"Corn spots"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1330","question":"In reference to colors, define dappled.","answer":"Circular spots on the coat that are two different shades of the same color; dark spots embossed on some base color; accept any reasonable wording"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1331","question":"What term describes circular or ring-shaped patterns on the coat that are two slightly different shades of the same color?","answer":"Dappled"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1332","question":"What is the name of coat markings or areas of the skin where there is NO pigment?","answer":"Flesh marks"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1333","question":"Referring to markings, what is an ink spot?","answer":"Small dark-colored spot seen on the white area of a Paint or Pinto"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1334","question":"Referring to color, what is the pangare effect? (pan-gu-RAY)","answer":"Light areas of color (on the muzzle, over the eyes, on the flanks, and on the inside of the legs)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1335","question":"Light areas of color over the eyes, on the muzzle, flanks and inside the legs are seen with influence of what color gene?","answer":"Pangare"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1336","question":"2 part question:  The pigment melanin comes in TWO forms.  Name them and give the colors they control.","answer":"Eumelanin—controls black or brown; pheomelanin—controls red or yellow"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1337","question":"What is the name of the pigment that is responsible for the color of the skin, hair, and eyes?","answer":"Melanin"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1338","question":"Which type of melanin controls the expression of red and yellow pigment?","answer":"Pheomelanin"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1339","question":"What do you call the congenital absence of pigment in the skin, hair, and eyes of an animal?","answer":"Albinism (albino) (FYI: There are no true albino horses because white horses have pigmented eyes.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1340","question":"What term means a lack of uniformity in color, a dull dirty tone?","answer":"Ratty"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1341","question":"What is the term meaning a blue tinge to the coat?","answer":"Smokey"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1342","question":"What does the color term \"sooty\" mean?","answer":"Darker hairs intermingled with a base color or dark shading (usually over the topline)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1343","question":"In reference to horse coat color, name 3 dilution genes.","answer":"Cream, dun, silver dapple, champagne, pearl"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1344","question":"Name 4 ways the basic coat colors of the horse can be modified.","answer":"Dilution, roaning, graying, spotting"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1345","question":"Describe the color cremello.","answer":"Body is cream colored; mane and tail are cream or white (skin is pink; eyes are brown, blue, or hazel)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1346","question":"What color horse has a cream-colored body and white or cream-colored mane and tail?","answer":"Cremello"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1347","question":"Describe the color perlino.","answer":"Ivory color body with rusty points"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1348","question":"What color is a horse with an ivory coat color and rusty points?","answer":"Perlino"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1349","question":"Describe the  color silver dapple or blue silver.","answer":"Blueish or chocolate brown body with very light mane, tail, and lower legs (FYI: Silver dapple gene on black; silver dapple gene makes black areas pale and leaves red areas unaffected.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1350","question":"Name ONE breed that can have a silver dapple coat color.","answer":"Shetland pony, Miniature Horse, Rocky Mountain Horseaccept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1351","question":"The Taffy color common to the Australian pony is the same as what color seen in Shetland ponies.","answer":"Silver Dapple"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1352","question":"In general terms, what distinguishes the difference between tovero, overo, and tobiano Paint horses?","answer":"Location of color on the horse"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"jr bonus","number":"1353","question":"Name 3 color patterns of the Paint or Pinto.","answer":"Tobiano, overo, tovero, calico, splashed white, sabino"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"medium","number":"1354","question":"Describe a “medicine hat” or “war bonnet” mustang.","answer":"Almost entirely white except for colored areas over the ears and top of the head (may have a colored “shield” on their chest and/or colored areas over their eyes, flank, and base of the tail)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1355","question":"The Cheyenne Indians thought Spanish mustangs with what color pattern possessed supernatural powers of protection?","answer":"Medicine Hat"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1356","question":"What is the term used for a horse that is almost entirely white except for colored areas over the ears, eyes, chest, and base of the tail?","answer":"Medicine hat or war bonnet"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1357","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the overo color pattern.","answer":"Irregular or jagged spots, white usually does NOT cross the back, spots irregular or splashy, one or more legs are dark, tail is usually dark, have large white facial markings (bald, bonnet, or apron face), can be predominantly dark or white"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1358","question":"Frame, sabino, and splashed white are 3 color patterns within which more general Paint color pattern, overo or tobiano?","answer":"Overo"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1359","question":"Identify this pinto pattern:  two solid legs and two white stockings; wide blaze; white body markings are irregularly spotted; white does NOT cross the back.","answer":"Overo"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1360","question":"Describe the color piebald.","answer":"Black and white pinto"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1361","question":"What is the term for a black and white pinto?","answer":"Piebald"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1362","question":"Which paint or pinto color pattern can be confused with blotchy roaning?","answer":"Sabino (FYI:  Clydesdales often have the sabino pattern.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1363","question":"Describe the color skewbald.","answer":"Pinto that's any color except black with white spotting"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1364","question":"What is the general term for a bay and white pinto?","answer":"Skewbald (FYI: A piebald is a black and white pinto; skewbald is any other color and white pinto.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"hard","number":"1365","question":"In this type of spotted coat pattern the white rises from the bottom side of the horse and the legs are white with clearly defined edges between the colored and white areas.  There is extensive white on the face.  What is this pattern","answer":"Splashed white"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1366","question":"Identify this pinto pattern:  all 4 lower legs are white; horse has a star and stripe; white body markings are regular, oval-shaped, and distinct and they extend down the neck and chest; white crosses the back.","answer":"Tobiano"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1367","question":"What is the most common pinto pattern?","answer":"Tobiano"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1368","question":"Which paint or pinto color pattern has rounded or oval-shaped spots?","answer":"Tobiano"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"sr bonus","number":"1369","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the tobiano color pattern","answer":"White crosses back; head is a solid color (may have white facial markings); all 4 legs are white below knees and hocks; spots are regular, oval shaped, and distinct; one or both flanks are usually solid"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"intermediate","number":"1370","question":"Describe the tovero color pattern.","answer":"Combination of the tobiano and overo patterns (doesn't belong in either one)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1371","question":"What do you call an Appaloosa coat pattern where the horse has a solid colored head, neck, and shoulders and it changes to white on the back or flank?","answer":"Blanket (also accept snowcap) (FYI:  Snowcap is a blanket with no spots.  The blanket pattern covers the hips, haunches, and sometimes the barrel and shoulders.)"},
{"category":"Colors and Markings","level":"easy","number":"1372","question":"Describe a leopard Appaloosa.","answer":"White background with colored spots and Appaloosa characteristics"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1373","question":"Name 3 features of conformation in horses.","answer":"Balance, structural correctness, muscling, form, type, action (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1374","question":"Shoulder, pastern, and hoof should all have approximately what angle?","answer":"45 degrees (also accept 45 - 50 degrees)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1375","question":"Name 3 areas of the horse that should have 45 degree angles.","answer":"Head joined to neck; shoulder; pasterns (front); hoof to the ground"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1376","question":"Give ONE reason why horses should have proper shoulder and pastern angles.","answer":"Shock absorption; length of stride; comfortable ride; less unsoundness; bad angles can cause other conformation faults"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1377","question":"Name TWO ideal conformation traits that are associated with a long, elastic, springy stride.","answer":"Sloping shoulders and sloping pasterns"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1378","question":"Name TWO things that determine whether the slope of a horse’s croup is considered desirable.","answer":"Breed preference; intended use"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1379","question":"At what angle should the head join the neck?","answer":"45 degrees"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1380","question":"What is the ideal angle of the hoof to the ground?","answer":"45 degrees"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1381","question":"Give ONE reason why the pastern should have a 45 – 50 degree angle.","answer":"Shock absorption; incorrect angle predisposes horse to injury or unsoundness such as navicular or laminitis; incorrect angle causes a rough ride"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1382","question":"2 part question:  What is the best angle for the front and for the rear pasterns?","answer":"Front pasterns—45 degrees; back pasterns—50 degrees"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1383","question":"The angle of the shoulder is essential to the overall balance of the horse.  As the slope of the shoulder becomes straighter, what effect does this have on the length of the back?","answer":"Back gets longer"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1384","question":"What is the ideal slope or angle of the shoulder?","answer":"45 - 50 degrees (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1385","question":"How does the slope of the shoulder influence the length of the stride?","answer":"Steeper the shoulder, the shorter the stride"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"int bonus","number":"1386","question":"Name 3 things that are affected by the slope of the shoulder.","answer":"Length of stride; shock absorption; length of back; length of neck; depth of heart; soundness (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1387","question":"Give ONE reason why the back and loin should be short and strong.","answer":"Support the weight of the rider; protect internal organs; transmit propulsion from hindquarters; lift the forequarters when the horse is in motion (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1388","question":"Give 3 reasons why the back and loin should be short and strong.","answer":"Support the weight of the rider; protect internal organs; transmit propulsion from hindquarters; lift the forequarters when the horse is in motion (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1389","question":"What is the most critical conformational factor in the balance of the horse?","answer":"Slope of the shoulder"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1390","question":"What term means that a horse is proportionally as long as it is tall?","answer":"Balanced"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1391","question":"Give ONE reason why balance is the single most important characteristic in equine selection.","answer":"Forms basis for movement (and ultimately performance); affects length of stride; affects length of back; affects shock absorption; decreases injury"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1392","question":"Name ONE way to determine if a horse has balance.","answer":"Forequarters and hindquarters are of equal size and development; height at the withers is the same as the height at the hip; horse is proportionally as long as it is tall (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1393","question":"Give 3 reasons why balance is the single most important characteristic in equine selection.","answer":"Forms basis for movement (and ultimately performance); affects length of stride; affects length of back; affects shock absorption; decreases injury"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1394","question":"Give 3 descriptive terms for the ideal stock horse ears.","answer":"Small, short, pointed, straight, set wide apart"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1395","question":"Name 3 characteristics you want in a horse's eye.","answer":"Large, spaced wide apart, clear, bold, alert, deep, soft or kind expression (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1396","question":"Name ONE characteristic you want in a horse's eye.","answer":"Large, spaced wide apart, clear, bold, alert, deep, soft or kind expression (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1397","question":"What percent of a horse's weight is carried on its forequarters?","answer":"60 - 65% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1398","question":"Name 3 GENERAL parts of the horse's forequarters.","answer":"Head, neck, shoulders, forelegs"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1399","question":"Name 3 purposes of the horse's forequarters.","answer":"Provide propulsion in front; serve as base of support; shock absorption"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1400","question":"What are the TWO most important aspects of ideal conformation of the forelimbs?","answer":"Slope and angle of the bones; straightness of the limbs"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1401","question":"What relationship should there be between a line from the point of shoulder through the shoulder blade and a line through the pastern to the ground?","answer":"They should be parallel."},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1402","question":"When viewed from the FRONT, how do you determine the straightness of a horse's front legs?","answer":"Follow a straight line from the point of the shoulder down the entire leg to the toe"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1403","question":"When viewed from the SIDE, name 3 parts of the forequarters that should be in a straight line with the shoulders.","answer":"Forearm, knee, cannon, and hoof (FYI:  Straight line should run from the center of the scapula to the front edge of the knee and should bisect the hoof.)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1404","question":"Where can you find a description of the ideal horse's head for a certain breed?","answer":"Breed association publications"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1405","question":"3 part question:  Where should the head be a) broad, b) short, and c) deep?","answer":"Broad in the forehead (between eyes); short in length (from eyes to nostrils); deep in the jaws"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1406","question":"Name 3 common characteristics of attractive, well-conformed heads for most breeds.","answer":"Short, well-set ears; large, bold eyes; refined muzzles; large nostrils; short from eye to muzzle; sex characteristics; breed characteristics"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1407","question":"What term describes a face that is concave in appearance?","answer":"Dished face"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1408","question":"In reference to conformation, what is a dished face?","answer":"Face that is concave in appearance (that’s often seen in Arabians)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1409","question":"Name 3 desirable characteristics of a horse's hock.","answer":"Wide, deep, clean, large"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1410","question":"Name 3 characteristics of a good knee.","answer":"Large, broad, flat, wide, clean, capable of great flexion, straight when viewed from side or front"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1411","question":"Give TWO descriptive terms for ideal stock horse pasterns.","answer":"Medium length; strong; clean; sloping at 45 degree angles; angles same as shoulder angles"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"int bonus","number":"1412","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse that should be short.","answer":"Arm, cannon, back, loin"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"int bonus","number":"1413","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse that should be long.","answer":"Shoulder, forearm, croup, gaskin, neck, underline"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1414","question":"On the front leg of a horse, which should be longer, the forearm or the cannon?","answer":"Forearm"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1415","question":"In a balanced horse, the legs are approximately the same length as what measurement?","answer":"Depth of heart"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1416","question":"Ideally, in a balanced horse, what should be the relationship between the height of the horse at the withers and the length of the body from the point of the shoulder to the point of the hip?","answer":"They should be the same (height = length from point of the shoulder to point of the hip)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1417","question":"Name 3 measurements that should be the same in a balanced horse.","answer":"Depth of heart and length of leg; height at withers and height at hips; height at withers and distance from point of the shoulder to buttock; width of shoulders and width of hindquarters"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1418","question":"Tell whether each of the following 4 parts of the forequarters should be short or long:  shoulder, arm, forearm, and cannon.","answer":"Long shoulder, short arm, long forearm, short cannon"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1419","question":"Tell whether each of the following 4 parts of the hindquarters should be short or long:  croup, thigh, gaskin, and cannon.","answer":"Long croup, short thigh, long gaskin, short cannon"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1420","question":"What part of the horse needs to be deep and fairly thick with good V muscling?","answer":"Chest (FYI:  Chest should be deep, wide, and thick, with good V muscling.  Heartgirth should be deep and ribs should be “well-sprung” which help with respiratory and digestive capacities and with athletic potential.)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1421","question":"Name ONE area of the hindquarters that should be deep, thick, and well-muscled.","answer":"Thigh, gaskin, stifle"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1422","question":"When viewed from the side or rear, name ONE desirable characteristic of the hind quarters.","answer":"Thick, deep, well-muscled"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1423","question":"When viewed from the rear, which part of the horse's hindquarters should be the widest?","answer":"Stifle area"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1424","question":"Give 3 reasons why gaskin muscles should be powerful.","answer":"Stride length, propulsion, strength (for turning and pivoting)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1425","question":"Why is the neck an important conformation point?","answer":"Horse uses the neck as a balance arm (also affects length of stride)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1426","question":"The shape of the neck is due largely to the amount and shape of what?","answer":"Muscles"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1427","question":"A horse uses what TWO parts of its body to aid in stability and balance?","answer":"Head and neck"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1428","question":"What is the determining factor in the ratio of the top to bottom line of the horse's neck?","answer":"Slope of the shoulders"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1429","question":"What is the IDEAL top to bottom line neck ratio?","answer":"2 to 1"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1430","question":"Name TWO characteristics of a good neck.","answer":"Long; lean; attached high on shoulders with prominent withers"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1431","question":"The bottom line of a horse's neck is measured from where to where?","answer":"Throatlatch to the junction at chest"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1432","question":"Name 3 desirable characteristics of a horse's ribs.","answer":"Well-sprung, long, close"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1433","question":"Name ONE thing that is greatly improved when a horse has correct skeletal structure.","answer":"Durability; soundness; athletic ability; symmetry; smoothness; quickness (balance to action) (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1434","question":"Name 3 things that are greatly improved when a horse has correct skeletal structure.","answer":"Durability; soundness; athletic ability; symmetry; smoothness; quickness (balance to action) (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1435","question":"The cannon bones should have what appearance when viewed from the side?","answer":"Flat"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1436","question":"Name 3 characteristics of good cannons.","answer":"Short; broad; straight; flat; tendons clearly defined; set well back"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1437","question":"Why should horses have straight legs as viewed from behind?","answer":"To deliver power to the stride"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1438","question":"Why is it extremely important that the skeletal structure of the front limbs be correct?","answer":"Because the horse carries over 60% of his weight on his front legs"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1439","question":"What is meant when it's said that a horse has \"clean legs\"?","answer":"No blemishes or unsoundness of the legs"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1440","question":"Name 3 ideal features in the bones of the legs.","answer":"Flat; clean; free from fleshiness or puffiness; adequate strength or substance to support the horse during activity"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1441","question":"What is the term for a trim throatlatch that allows the horse to flex at the poll without restricting air flow or blood flow?","answer":"“Clean” throatlatch"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1442","question":"Give ONE reason why a trim throatlatch is desirable on a horse.","answer":"Doesn't restrict air flow; doesn't restrict blood flow; aids in balance"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1443","question":"Why should the bottom line of a horse be longer than the top line?","answer":"Allows for a longer stride (also accept so the legs don't interfere)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1444","question":"Should the topline of a horse be shorter or longer than the underline?","answer":"Shorter (FYI: Topline should be short and strong to support the weight of the rider; bottom line should be long to allow for a longer stride.)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1445","question":"What TWO thoracic characteristics are desirable in the broodmare?","answer":"Good spring of rib and deep depth of heart"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1446","question":"Give TWO reasons why a horse should have a deep heart girth with well-sprung ribs.","answer":"Respiratory capacity, digestive capacity, circulatory capacity"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1447","question":"Sharp, prominent, and well-defined describe what part of the horse?","answer":"Withers"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1448","question":"2 part question:  Describe the ideal shape of a horse's withers and explain why this shape is important.","answer":"Shape–sharp, prominent, and well-defined; why–helps hold the saddle in place"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1449","question":"Name 3 features of ideal withers.","answer":"Sharp; prominent; well defined; same height as the hips"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"int bonus","number":"1450","question":"What are 3 normal measurements pertinent to a horse's size?","answer":"Height, weight, girth, bone"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1451","question":"In reference to measurements in horses, how is “bone” measured?","answer":"Circumference of the cannon bone about half way between the knee and the fetlock"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1452","question":"Why are the withers used as the measuring spot for a horse's height?","answer":"Highest, non-movable part of the horse"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1453","question":"Give ONE reason why you shouldn't buy a horse with poor conformation.","answer":"Predisposes horse to unsoundness; rough ride; genetic defects could be passed to offspring (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1454","question":"Conformation is directly related to what?","answer":"Skeletal structure"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1455","question":"Name ONE time when the front feet and legs serve primarily to support the horse.","answer":"At rest; when landing over a jump; when on the leading foreleg at the lope or gallop"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1456","question":"The spring-like action which absorbs concussion during movements is called what?","answer":"Shock absorption"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1457","question":"Which of the following horses will most likely have a longer stride:  a horse with a long, gently sloping croup or a horse with a short, steep croup?","answer":"Horse with a long, gently sloping croup"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1458","question":"In what TWO ways is the angle of the croup important to the stride of a horse?","answer":"Length; efficiency"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1459","question":"Why are the length and the width of the croup important?","answer":"Long muscles are associated with speed and endurance; wide muscles are related to strength and power."},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1460","question":"A flatter and more level croup results in what type of hind leg action, vertical or horizontal?","answer":"More vertical hind leg action"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1461","question":"What happens when the angle of the croup is too steep?","answer":"Stride is shorter"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1462","question":"Describe the ideal motion of a horse.","answer":"Straight, true, long, well-coordinated stride (accept any appropriate answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1463","question":"A horse that travels with a rolling gait and a heavy front end often has what type of conformation?","answer":"Low, flat withers (mutton withers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1464","question":"Describe the motion of a horse that has low, flat withers.","answer":"Rolling gait, heavy on the front end, overall moving poorly (accept any)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1465","question":"If a horse has his front legs set too wide on the corners of his body, what is the resulting action?","answer":"Rolling, labored action"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1466","question":"Name 3 things that determine the length of a horse's stride.","answer":"Slope of shoulder; length of shoulder; length of forearm;  slope of croup; length of gaskin; length of neck (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1467","question":"Why does a steep shouldered horse generally have a short stride?","answer":"Arm can't extend very far forward."},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1468","question":"Name ONE thing that determines the length of a horse's stride.","answer":"Slope of shoulder; length of shoulder; length of forearm;  slope of croup; length of gaskin; length of neck (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1469","question":"What generally determines the length of a horse's stride?","answer":"Angle or length of shoulder (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1470","question":"Name 3 areas of the hindquarters where the muscle should have thickness.","answer":"Thigh, gaskin, stifle"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1471","question":"What is the general term that's used to describe a horse that's closely coupled and stoutly built?","answer":"Cobby"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1472","question":"What is the term for the physical appearance of an animal?","answer":"Conformation (also accept phenotype)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1473","question":"What is the relationship of body parts to performance called?","answer":"Form to function (also accept functional anatomy)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1474","question":"What slang term refers to legs in which the tendons lack definition and do not stand out clearly?","answer":"Gummy legged"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1475","question":"What does the term \"paunchy\" mean?","answer":"Too much belly"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1476","question":"What is the slang term that describes a short, thickset horse?","answer":"Pudgy"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1477","question":"What term means refinement in the horse?","answer":"Quality"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1478","question":"What term describes the condition when all of the parts of a horse blend together well, with long, tapering muscling?","answer":"Smoothness"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1479","question":"In reference to conformation, define symmetrical.","answer":"Proper balance or relationship of all parts"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1480","question":"At a standstill, where is the center of gravity located on a horse?","answer":"6 inches behind the elbow, about the rider's knee, near the outer edge of the 8th rib (accept any)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1481","question":"Which can be altered, the center of motion or the center of gravity?","answer":"Center of gravity"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1482","question":"Name ONE way a horse's center of gravity be altered.","answer":"By the rider shifting his weight; by the horse raising, lowering, or extending his head"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1483","question":"Where is the center of motion?","answer":"Over the 15th vertebrae or 10 inches behind the center of gravity (accept either)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1484","question":"Name 3 conformation faults whose common name refers to another animal species.","answer":"Parrot mouth; monkey mouth; ewe neck; calf knee; pigeon toe; cow hocked; coon footed; pig eye; roach back; cow eyes; goose rump; wasp waist; herring gutted; hound gutted"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1485","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the horse's body EXCLUDING its legs.","answer":"Coarse head; pig eye; cow eye; parrot mouth; monkey mouth; thick throatlatch; short, thick neck; ewe neck; mutton withers; swayback; roach back; goose rump; paunchy; wasp waisted or tucked up; narrow chest; slab sided (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1486","question":"Name 5 conformation faults of the horse's body EXCLUDING its legs.","answer":"Coarse head; pig eye; cow eye; parrot mouth; monkey mouth; thick throatlatch; short, thick neck; ewe neck; mutton withers; swayback; roach back; goose rump; paunchy; wasp waisted or tucked up; narrow chest; slab sided (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1487","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the head.","answer":"Roman nose, pig eye, parrot mouth, monkey mouth, mule ears, lop ears, coarse head (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1488","question":"Give 3 characteristics of a coarse head.","answer":"Large ears, thick muzzle, Roman nose, small eye (pig eye), thick throatlatch, long head"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1489","question":"Describe a horse with lop ears.","answer":"Ears are positioned on the sides of the head (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1490","question":"Explain the difference between the conformation faults mule ears and lop ears.","answer":"Mule ears are long, thick and heavy; lop ears are carried to the side"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1491","question":"What is the term for large, protruding eyes?","answer":"Bug eyed or bovine eyes (accept either)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1492","question":"What is a bug eyed horse?","answer":"Horse with large, protruding eyes"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1493","question":"What is a pig eyed horse?","answer":"Horse with small eyes"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1494","question":"What is the term for a horse with small eyes?","answer":"Pig eyed"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1495","question":"What is Roman nosed?","answer":"Face bows out instead of being flat (convex face)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1496","question":"What is the term for the convex profile of a horse's face?","answer":"Roman nose"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1497","question":"What term refers to an overhanging of the top lip?","answer":"Elk lip"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1498","question":"Name the defect where the upper jaw is SHORTER than the lower jaw.","answer":"Monkey mouth (undershot jaw; also called prognathism)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1499","question":"Describe monkey mouth.","answer":"Upper jaw is SHORTER than the lower jaw (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1500","question":"Describe parrot mouth.","answer":"Upper jaw is LONGER than the lower jaw (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1501","question":"Name the defect where the upper jaw is LONGER than the lower jaw.","answer":"Parrot mouth (also called overshot jaw and brachygnathism)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"jr bonus","number":"1502","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the front legs.","answer":"Base narrow; base wide; camped in; camped out; bench or offset knees; bow legs; buck knee; calf knee; coon footed; straight pasterns; tied in at knee; knock knee; pigeon toe; splay foot (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1503","question":"Describe a base narrow horse.","answer":"Horse's front legs are closer together at the ground than they are at the chest."},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1504","question":"A base-narrow horse is predisposed to landing on what part of the foot?","answer":"Outside hoof wall"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1505","question":"Describe a base wide horse.","answer":"Horse's front legs are further apart at the ground than they are at the chest."},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1506","question":"Base wide, narrow chested horses have feet that are usually what?","answer":"Toed out or splay footed (accept either)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1507","question":"Camped out horses are predisposed to what TWO conditions?","answer":"Navicular and laminitis or founder"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"int bonus","number":"1508","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the horse's knee.","answer":"Calf knee, buck knee, bench or offset knee, knock knee, cut under at knee, bow legged (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1509","question":"Name a conformation fault that increases the possibility of a horse developing splints.","answer":"Bench or offset knees"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1510","question":"What are bench knees?","answer":"Off-set knees where the cannon is not centered on the knee (or carpal bones)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1511","question":"What is the name of the conformation fault where the cannon bones are not centered on the knees?","answer":"Bench or offset knees (accept either)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1512","question":"What is buck knee?","answer":"Knee bent forward"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1513","question":"What is the term for knees bent forward?","answer":"Buck knees"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1514","question":"What is another term for back at the knees?","answer":"Calf knee"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1515","question":"Which condition is more serious, over at the knee or back at the knee?","answer":"Back at the knee (FYI: Back at the knee or calf knee predisposes horses to carpal chip fractures.)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1516","question":"What is calf knee?","answer":"Knee bent backward (FYI:  Calf knee is a serious conformation fault that often causes unsoundness.)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1517","question":"What conformation defect predisposes a horse to carpal chip fractures, especially in young racehorses?","answer":"Calf knee"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1518","question":"What is the term for the front toes pointing inward?","answer":"Pigeon toe (toed-in)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1519","question":"Describe a pigeon-toed horse.","answer":"Front toes turn in (and heels turn out)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1520","question":"What is the difference between splay foot and pigeon toe?","answer":"Splayfoot—front toes turn out (and heels turn in); pigeon toe—front toes turn in (and heels turn out)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1521","question":"Which is a more serious condition, toed in or toed out?","answer":"Toed out (because legs can interfere when they move)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1522","question":"What do you call a horse that toes out in front?","answer":"Splay footed or toed out (accept either)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1523","question":"Describe a splay-footed horse.","answer":"Front toes turn out (and heels turn in)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"int bonus","number":"1524","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the hind legs.","answer":"Stands wide; stands close; bow legged, out at the hock, open behind, or bandy legged; cow hocked; sickle hocked; post legged; camped out; camped under (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1525","question":"Define the term \"camped out behind\".","answer":"Hind legs appear to reach out behind a line drawn from the buttock to the ground"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1526","question":"2 part question:  What are the terms used when there is too little angle in the hock and too much angle at the hock?","answer":"Too little angle—post legged; too much angle—sickle hocked"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1527","question":"What is the slang term for thick, meaty hocks that lack in quality?","answer":"Beefy hocks"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1528","question":"What is the term for a horse whose hocks are too close together, when viewed from the rear?","answer":"Cow hocked"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1529","question":"Describe a cow hocked horse.","answer":"Hocks are too close together (and feet are wide apart) (when viewed from the rear)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1530","question":"What is the most common conformation fault of the hind legs?","answer":"Cow hock"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1531","question":"Which conformation defect interferes with movements that require work off the haunches such as stopping, turning or sliding?","answer":"Cow hock"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1532","question":"When viewed from the rear, name ONE term for a horse whose hocks are too far apart and his feet are set close together.","answer":"Bow legged, out at the hock, open behind, or bandy legged"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1533","question":"Describe the term \"out at the hock\".","answer":"Hocks are too far apart (and hind feet are too close together when viewed from the rear) [also called bow legged,  open behind, or bandy legged]"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1534","question":"What is the term for a horse possessing too little angle in the hock?","answer":"Post legged"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1535","question":"Describe a post legged horse.","answer":"Horse has too little angle in the hocks (hocks are too straight (as viewed from the side)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1536","question":"What are limber or rotating hocks?","answer":"When points of hocks turn outward"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1537","question":"Describe a sickle hocked horse.","answer":"Too much angle at the hock when viewed from the side (horse’s leg stands under its hip from the hock downward) (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1538","question":"When viewed from the side, what is the term for a horse with too much angle in the hock?","answer":"Sickle hocked"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1539","question":"If a horse is sickle hocked, excessive strain will be placed on what ligament?","answer":"Plantar ligament (FYI:  Sickle hocks predispose horses too curbs which are hard swellings of the plantar ligament below the point of the hock.)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1540","question":"What is a common conformation fault in the rear limbs that puts a strain on the plantar ligament leading to a curb?","answer":"Sickle hock"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1541","question":"This conformational problem causes the horse to walk on the toe, resulting in the heel growing long and the toe wearing off. The foot will have an upright appearance.  Name this defect.","answer":"Club foot"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"hard","number":"1542","question":"Describe a club foot.","answer":"An abnormally upright foot"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1543","question":"A coon footed horse has too much slope at what joint?","answer":"Pastern"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1544","question":"Long, sloping pasterns will put strain on what 3 things?","answer":"Tendons, sesamoid bones, suspensory ligaments"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1545","question":"Describe a coon footed horse.","answer":"Too much slope at the pastern"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1546","question":"Describe a coon footed horse.","answer":"Too much slope at the pasterns (long, sloping pasterns where the fetlock may hit the ground as the horse moves)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1547","question":"What term describes too much angle in the pastern joint?","answer":"Coon footed"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1548","question":"Describe a flat footed horse.","answer":"When the angle of the foot is less than 45 degrees"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1549","question":"Steep shoulders are usually associated with what type pasterns?","answer":"Short, steep pasterns"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1550","question":"Short, straight pasterns are associated with what other conformation problem?","answer":"Straight, steep, or upright shoulder (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1551","question":"Describe the conformation defect of the lower leg (not hoof) that predisposes a horse to navicular disease.","answer":"Short, steep pasterns"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1552","question":"A horse with a short, steep pastern will endure more concussion and may be predisposed to what disease?","answer":"Navicular disease (FYI:  also called Navicular Syndrome or Caudal Heel Pain Syndrome)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1553","question":"What is a broken crest?","answer":"When a horse has an excessively thick crest that lops to side"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"medium","number":"1554","question":"What is the term for an excessively thick crest that lops to the side?","answer":"Broken crest or lop neck"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1555","question":"In reference to conformation, describe a horse that is \"built downhill\".","answer":"Height at hips is higher than the height at the withers (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1556","question":"What is the term for when a horse’s height at the hips is higher than the height at the withers?","answer":"“Built downhill”"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1557","question":"Name ONE conformation fault of the neck.","answer":"Ewe neck; short thick neck"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1558","question":"What is the term for a horse’s neck that is concave on top and rounded on the bottom?","answer":"Ewe neck"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1559","question":"Describe a ewe necked horse.","answer":"Upper part of the neck is concave (sags down)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1560","question":"Name an undesirable trait of the croup.","answer":"Goose rump (short, steep croup)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1561","question":"Describe a goose rumped horse.","answer":"Short, steep croup"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1562","question":"What is the term for a short, steep croup on a horse?","answer":"Goose rump"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1563","question":"2 part question:  What is the term for low, flat withers and why is this undesirable?","answer":"Mutton withers; don't hold the saddle very well"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1564","question":"What are mutton withers?","answer":"Low, flat withers"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1565","question":"Describe a roached back horse.","answer":"Back is arched up or convex (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1566","question":"What is the term for a thin, sharp, arched back?","answer":"Roached back"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"novice","number":"1567","question":"Describe a swaybacked horse.","answer":"Back sags down or is concave (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1568","question":"What is the term for a horse’s back that is concave or sags down?","answer":"Sway back (FYI:  The medical term is lordosis.)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"intermediate","number":"1569","question":"Why does a thick neck cause increased shock to the front legs?","answer":"Thick neck adds excess weight to the front legs."},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1570","question":"What is the term for flat ribbed?","answer":"Slab sided"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1571","question":"What does the term slab sided mean?","answer":"When the horse’s ribs are flat (instead of rounded or “well sprung” which allows for a bigger chest capacity)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"easy","number":"1572","question":"In reference to conformation, what is \"tucked up\" or “hound gutted”?","answer":"Thin and cut up in the flank like a greyhound (also called herring gutted, wasp waisted, and lady waisted)"},
{"category":"Conformation","level":"sr bonus","number":"1573","question":"Give 3 common terms used to describe a horse that is weak in the coupling and shallow in the flank.","answer":"Hound gutted, herring gutted, wasp waisted, lady waisted, tucked up"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1574","question":"What is the term for a condition of increased sensitivity to a specific protein, which may result in a rash, hives, sneezing, or respiratory difficulties?","answer":"Allergy"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1575","question":"What substance is produced in the body in response to an allergen?","answer":"Histamine (FYI: Anti-histamines are medicines that treat allergies.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1576","question":"What is the term used for an acute, massive, often fatal allergic reaction?","answer":"Anaphylactic shock or anaphylaxis (accept either)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1577","question":"What is anaphylaxis or anaphylactic shock?","answer":"Acute, massive, often fatal allergic reaction (FYI: It's treated with a shot of epinephrine.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1578","question":"What causes anaphylaxis?","answer":"Severe allergy"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1579","question":"When caused by feed, hives are often referred to as what?","answer":"Protein bumps"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1580","question":"Small swellings or welts on the skin that appear suddenly and are caused by an allergic reaction are called what?","answer":"Hives (also called urticaria or protein bumps)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1581","question":"Name 3 things that can cause urticaria or hives.","answer":"Foods, medications, inhaled pollens, insect bites, parasites, vaccines, chemicals (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1582","question":"Name TWO weather conditions that make arthritis more painful.","answer":"Cold and wet"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1583","question":"What is arthritis?","answer":"Inflammation of a joint"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1584","question":"What problem, characterized by inflammation of a joint, is more common in older horses?","answer":"Arthritis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1585","question":"What is another name for septic arthritis?","answer":"Joint ill"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1586","question":"What is anemia?","answer":"Decreased number of red blood cells (also the lowered ability of red blood cells to transport oxygen)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1587","question":"Name 3 possible causes of anemia.","answer":"Blood loss; increased destruction of red blood cells; decreased production of red blood cells by bone marrow; infection; chronic disease; dietary deficiency; toxins; lack of iron; parasites; incompatible blood types (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1588","question":"What is the difference between a broad spectrum and a narrow spectrum antibiotic?","answer":"Broad spectrum antibiotic is effective against a wide range of bacteria; narrow spectrum antibiotic is effective against only a few types or a single type of bacteria."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1589","question":"What is the purpose of a prophylactic medication?","answer":"Prevents disease"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1590","question":"What is the correct medical term for the long, wavy, non-shedding hair coat associated with Equine Cushing’s Disease?","answer":"Hirsutism (HER-sue-tiz-em or  HERE-sue-tiz-em)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1591","question":"Horses with laminitis and/or Cushing’s disease will benefit from a diet low in what?","answer":"Sugars, starches, or simple carbohydrates (accept any)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1592","question":"A pituitary tumor may cause what disease that's associated with heavy hair growth?","answer":"Cushing's disease"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1593","question":"Cushing’s disease is more common in what GENERAL age of horses?","answer":"Older horses (over 15 years of age)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1594","question":"What disease of older horses has characteristic signs of excessive hair growth and failure to shed?","answer":"Cushing’s disease (FYI: Cushing's disease is also called PPID or Pituitary Pars Intermedia Dysfunction.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1595","question":"Cushing's disease and Equine Metabolic Syndrome are often confused.  Name ONE thing that would visually indicate Cushing’s disease.","answer":"Long, wavy, or non-shedding hair coat (accept any)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1596","question":"Name TWO signs, symptoms, or features of Cushing's disease.","answer":"Long, wavy hair; failure to shed; excessive thirst (polydipsia); excessive urination (polyuria); weight loss; fragile bones; weakness; thin skin; stupor, sweating; loss of muscle mass; chronic lameness (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1597","question":"Name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Cushing’s Disease in horses.","answer":"Long, wavy hair; failure to shed; excessive thirst (polydipsia); excessive urination (polyuria); weight loss; fragile bones; weakness; thin skin; stupor, sweating; loss of muscle mass; chronic lameness (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1598","question":"Compared to other causes of obesity, name TWO areas where fat is deposited in Equine Metabolic Syndrome.","answer":"Crest and tail head"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1599","question":"Explain how insulin resistance in Equine Metabolic Syndrome predisposes horses to laminitis.","answer":"EMS can decrease blood flow to the feet causing laminitis."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1600","question":"What syndrome is characterized by obesity, regional adiposity, insulin resistance, high blood triglycerides, and hyperleptinemia? (aa-dih-PAHS-ih-tee)","answer":"Equine Metabolic Syndrome"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1601","question":"Name 3 management methods for Equine Metabolic Syndrome.","answer":"Exercise horse; maintain body condition (don't let horse get fat!); feed rations low in sugar and starch; feed high forage diet; test hay for sugar content; soak hay for at least an hour before feeding; limit pasture high in fructans"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1602","question":"What is the name of the condition where there is an unusually high level of fat in the blood?","answer":"Hyperlipemia (also accept hyperlipidemia)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1603","question":"What is the term for enlargement of the thyroid gland?","answer":"Goiter"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1604","question":"What is a goiter?","answer":"Enlarged thyroid gland (FYI:  Goiters in horses are usually due to iodine deficiency.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1605","question":"What is hypothyroidism?","answer":"Low thyroid (FYI: Hypothyroidism can be caused by low iodine.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1606","question":"With eye problems in the horse, redness of the eye indicates inflammation.  What does closing the eye indicate?","answer":"Pain"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1607","question":"Name 3 eye problems in horses.","answer":"Trauma; laceration; infection; corneal ulcer; moon blindness (Equine Recurrent Uveitis); glaucoma; cataracts; blocked tear duct; sarcoid; squamous cell carcinoma; aniridia; Equine Night Blindness"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1608","question":"Name 3 signs of eye disease in horses.","answer":"Redness; tearing; squinting; drainage or discharge; color changes; small pupil (ERU); large pupil (glaucoma); scarring; growths; cloudiness; decreased vision; blindness (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1609","question":"What is the COMMON name for inflammation of the conjunctiva resulting in redness or erythema? (con-junk-TIE-vah) (air-ee-THEME-ah)","answer":"Pink eye"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1610","question":"In what breed is Equine Night Blindness most common?","answer":"Appaloosa (FYI:  Equine Night Blindness is not the same condition as moon blindness.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1611","question":"What is the most common infectious agent that causes Equine Recurrent Uveitis or ERU?","answer":"Leptospira"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1612","question":"What is the treatment for Equine Recurrent Uveitis?","answer":"Anti-inflammatory medications"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1613","question":"What is the COMMON name for the eye disease that causes cloudiness of the uveal tract of the eye and may lead to blindness?","answer":"Moon blindness (FYI:  Other names are ERU, Equine Recurrent Uveitis, and Equine Periodic Ophthalmia.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1614","question":"Name 3 INITIAL signs of ERU or moon blindness.","answer":"Tears, redness, and squinting (FYI:  ERU is Equine Recurrent Uveitis.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1615","question":"What is the main sign of a blocked tear duct?","answer":"Wet face (Tears don't drain properly so they spill onto the face.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1616","question":"What is the term for a partial or complete blockage in the esophagus of a horse?","answer":"Choke"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1617","question":"In reference to horse diseases and conditions, what is “choke”?","answer":"Partial or complete blockage of the esophagus"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1618","question":"Name ONE sign of choke.","answer":"Inability to swallow; regurgitation of food or saliva from the nose; coughing; stretching and retracting neck; lump in the neck; shaking head side to side (accept any correct answer"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1619","question":"Name ONE possible cause of choke.","answer":"Bolting food; bad teeth; lack of water; narrowing of esophagus (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1620","question":"What is the number one cause of premature death in horses?","answer":"Colic"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"novice","number":"1621","question":"What is the most common medical emergency in horses?","answer":"Colic"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"novice","number":"1622","question":"What is the common name for abdominal pain in horses?","answer":"Colic"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"novice","number":"1623","question":"What should you do if you think your horse has colic?","answer":"Call the vet"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"novice","number":"1624","question":"What is colic?","answer":"Acute abdominal pain in horses (stomachache)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1625","question":"Name TWO common causes of colic.","answer":"Lack of water; dietary changes; lack of exercise; parasites; bad teeth; buildup of sand; idiopathic; obstructed, twisted, telescoped, displaced, or trapped intestine; letting overheated horse gorge on cold water; riding hard after full feeding"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"jr bonus","number":"1626","question":"Name 3 causes of colic.","answer":"Lack of water; dietary changes; lack of exercise; parasites; bad teeth; moldy feed; overfeeding; letting overheated horse gorge on cold water; riding hard after full feeding; twisted, telescoped, displaced, or trapped intestine"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1627","question":"Name ONE way to prevent colic.","answer":"ALWAYS HAVE FRESH WATER AVAILABLE; good feeding practices—accept any correct answers; parasite control; regular exercise; dental care; keep grain locked up; psyllium for sand ingestion; restrict cold water to hot horse; prevent over-excitement"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1628","question":"Name 3 things horse owners can do to help prevent horses from developing colic.","answer":"ALWAYS HAVE FRESH WATER AVAILABLE; good feeding practices—accept any correct answers; parasite control; regular exercise; dental care; keep grain locked up; psyllium for sand ingestion; restrict cold water to hot horse; prevent over-excitement"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1629","question":"What can be fed daily in order to reduce sand-induced diarrhea or colic?","answer":"Psyllium"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1630","question":"Absence of gut sounds may indicate what?","answer":"Colic (lack of normal cecal activity)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1631","question":"Name TWO signs or symptoms of colic.","answer":"Acting sick; off feed; pawing; rolling; lying down; biting belly; kicking belly; sweating; change in pooping; change in gut sounds; bloating; lying on back; restless; yawning; grinding teeth; change in vital signs—TPR, CRT,  mucous membrane color"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1632","question":"Name 3 things that a horse owner can easily check that will help indicate the seriousness of colic.","answer":"Temperature; pulse; respiratory rate; mucous membranes; capillary refill time; gut sounds (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1633","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of colic.","answer":"Acting sick; off feed; pawing; rolling; lying down; biting belly; kicking belly; sweating; change in pooping; change in gut sounds; bloating of belly; change in heart rate; change in respiratory rate; lying on back; restless; yawning"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1634","question":"Your horse is experiencing recurrent mild colic.  Your veterinarian is listening to the right side of your horse's abdomen for rumbling, gurgling noises.  What specific part of the digestive tract is he listening to?","answer":"Cecum (FYI:  Gut sounds are called borborygmus.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1635","question":"Give 3 signs that indicate severe causes of colic.","answer":"Increasing pulse; pulse higher than 55 bpm; rare or no gut sounds; horse is depressed or irrational; horse has clammy ears or extremities"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1636","question":"Name 3 treatments for colic.","answer":"Walking horse (if directed by vet); pain relievers (Banamine); NG, nasogastric, or stomach tube; laxatives (mineral oil and Epsom salts); IV fluids; psyllium for sand colic; surgery (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1637","question":"Give TWO treatments for SIMPLE colic.","answer":"Walking horse (if directed by vet); pain relievers (Banamine); NG, nasogastric, or stomach tube; laxatives (mineral oil and Epsom salts); IV fluids; psyllium for sand colic (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1638","question":"Name ONE of the most common and mildest types of colic in horses.","answer":"Spasmodic or gas colic"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1639","question":"Name 3 types of colic.","answer":"Gas; spasmodic; impaction; sand; displacement; volvulus or torsion (twist); intussusception (telescope); incarceration (trapped); verminous (worms); exercise induced; ulcers (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1640","question":"What is a common culprit in the development of gas colic?","answer":"Overeating grain"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1641","question":"How long does it generally take for the results of treatment for intestinal impaction to occur?","answer":"24 – 72 hours (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1642","question":"Which type of colic is caused by a blockage in the intestinal tract?","answer":"Impaction colic"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1643","question":"Why is impaction colic more common in winter?","answer":"Horses might not drink enough water."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1644","question":"What is spasmodic colic?","answer":"Colic or abdominal pain caused by muscular spasms of the intestinal tract"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1645","question":"Name TWO types of colic that requires prompt diagnosis and treatment because it can be rapidly fatal.","answer":"Displacement; incarceration (trapped); volvulus or torsion (twisting); intussusception (telescoping)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1646","question":"Name 3 types of colic that require surgery.","answer":"Displacement; incarceration (trapped); volvulus or torsion (twisting); intussusception (telescoping)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1647","question":"What happens with displacement colic?","answer":"Part of the intestine is displaced into an abnormal position (FYI:  Examples are left dorsal colon displacement and right dorsal colon displacement.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1648","question":"What is incarceration colic?","answer":"When a section of intestine gets trapped within the abdominal cavity (FYI: Examples are epiploic foramen entrapment and mesenteric rent entrapment.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1649","question":"What is intussusception? (in-tuss-suh-SEPT-shan)","answer":"Telescoping of the intestines (FYI: It usually occurs in the small intestines of young horses.  In most cases the ileum enfolds into an adjacent area of the cecum.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1650","question":"What is volvulus or torsion colic? (VOLV-you-luss)","answer":"Colic caused by twisted intestines (FYI: It occurs when the mesentery twists resulting in blockage of the intestines. Blood supply can be cut off and intestines can die or become necrotic.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1651","question":"What is verminous colic? (VERM-ih-nuss)","answer":"Colic caused by worms"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1652","question":"2 part question:  What is scours and in what stage of life does it usually occur?","answer":"Watery diarrhea; occurs in foals (under 6 months of age) "},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1653","question":"What is the COMMON term for diarrhea in foals?","answer":"Scours"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1654","question":"What is the term for higher than normal amounts of water in the feces or for an animal defecating too frequently?","answer":"Diarrhea"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1655","question":"Name 3 causes of foal diarrhea.","answer":"Stress; diet; parasites (threadworms); infections (virus, bacteria, protozoa); foal heat (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1656","question":"Give 3 observations that would indicate that a foal with diarrhea would require medical attention.","answer":"Large amount of diarrhea; watery diarrhea; bloody diarrhea; fever; depression; anorexia (loss of appetite)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1657","question":"Continued exposure of the lower part of the stomach to excessive gastric secretions can cause what?","answer":"Gastric ulcers"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1658","question":"Allowing a horse free-choice hay while recovering from gastric ulcers does what?","answer":"Keeps the gastric pH from becoming highly acidic"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1659","question":"What is Equine Gastric Ulcer Syndrome?","answer":"Ulcers of the horse’s stomach (FYI:  EGUS may be caused by stress, stomach acid, bacteria, parasites, or intermittent feeding.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1660","question":"The development of equine gastric ulcer syndrome has been linked with intense exercise.  In what breed is it most prevalent?","answer":"Thoroughbred (FYI: 91% of those in training and 100% of those currently racing)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1661","question":"Overuse of anti-inflammatory drugs and stress may cause what problem for the horse?","answer":"Gastric ulcers (EGUS or Equine Gastric Ulcer Syndrome)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1662","question":"Intense exercise correlates with an increased incidence of EGUS.  What is EGUS?","answer":"Equine Gastric Ulcer Syndrome"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1663","question":"Name 3 uses of horses that increase the incidence of gastric ulcers.","answer":"Racing, endurance, showing training"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1664","question":"Name 3 risk factors for gastric ulcers.","answer":"Intense exercise; stall confinement; stress; feeding high levels of concentrates (grain); disease; medications (such as corticosteroids or NSAIDs)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1665","question":"Give 3 clinical signs that a foal has a gastric ulcer.","answer":"Depression; grinding teeth; colic; diarrhea; poor body condition; pot-belly appearance; lying on back; poor appetite; decreased nursing; excessive salivation; froth around lips"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1666","question":"The equine liver will function at near optimal levels until approximately what percent of it is destroyed?","answer":"80% (accept numbers between 70% - 80%)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1667","question":"Cirrhosis is a chronic disease that affects which organ?","answer":"Liver"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1668","question":"What is the difference between bradycardia and tachycardia?","answer":"Bradycardia is a slower than normal heart rate; tachycardia is a faster than normal heart rate."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1669","question":"What term is used to describe a slower than normal heartbeat?","answer":"Bradycardia"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1670","question":"Endocarditis is an inflammation or infection of the lining of what organ?","answer":"Heart (FYI:  Endocarditis is inflammation of the INNER lining of the heart; pericarditis is the inflammation of the OUTER lining of the heart.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1671","question":"What is tachycardia?","answer":"Rapid heart rate"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1672","question":"What is an arrhythmia?","answer":"Any variation from the normal heart beat or rhythm"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1673","question":"What is the medical term for any variation from the normal heart rate?","answer":"Arrhythmia (FYI: Tachycardia is fast heart rate; bradycardia is slow heart rate.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1674","question":"What is the term that describes the animal's ability to resist a particular organism?","answer":"Immunity"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1675","question":"An annual injection of Tetanus toxoid produces active immunity.  Give ONE example of passive immunity in horses.","answer":"Mare passing antibodies to the newborn foal through colostrum (FYI: In horses, mares do NOT pass antibodies through the placenta.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1676","question":"2 part question:  What is immunity and how do horses develop immunity?","answer":"Immunity—ability to resist a particular disease; get it from vaccinations, previous exposure to disease, or colostrum"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1677","question":"What is the name for the disease-fighting substance produced by the immune system in response to the presence of an antigen?","answer":"Antibody"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1678","question":"What is passive immunity in horses?","answer":"When a newborn foal receives antibodies from the mare through the colostrum (FYI: Antibodies don't cross the placenta in horses.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1679","question":"3 part question:  What is immunity, name two types, and describe each?","answer":"Immunity—animal's  ability to resist a particular organism; permanent—lasts a long time; temporary—only lasts a short time; passive—antibodies are passed through colostrum; active"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1680","question":"How do animals develop ACTIVE immunity?","answer":"Animal actively develops antibodies after being exposed to an antigen.  (They can be exposed to the antigen from exposure to the disease or from vaccinations.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1681","question":"Name ONE disease spread through the air when droplets of moisture are coughed or sneezed.","answer":"Strangles, influenza, rhinopneumonitis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1682","question":"In what season are upper respiratory tract infections more common?","answer":"Winter"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1683","question":"Name 3 ways disease organisms escape from the host.","answer":"Eliminated with blood; eliminated with urine or feces; droplets of moisture; saliva; mucus membranes"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1684","question":"Name TWO specific microorganisms that may be transmitted in horse manure?","answer":"E. Coli; Giardia; Salmonella"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1685","question":"A horse with a potentially contagious disease should be isolated from other horses for how many days after recovery?","answer":"At least 10 days after recovery"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1686","question":"A home-made boot dip can be made using one gallon of water and what else?","answer":"¼ cup bleach"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1687","question":"Name ONE disease that can be contracted from contaminated food or water.","answer":"Strangles or Leptospirosis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1688","question":"Pneumonia is the major cause of mortality in foals.  Name 3 factors that predispose foals to pneumonia.","answer":"Dust; poor sanitation; overcrowding; stress; poor nutrition; parasites; poor ventilation; extreme temperatures and/or humidity; prematurity; foal didn't receive colostrum; secondary to other infections"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1689","question":"Name 3 microorganisms that cause infectious diseases.","answer":"Bacteria, virus, protozoa, fungus, obligate intracellular parasites such as Rickettsia (bacteria), prion (Mad Cow Disease)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1690","question":"Name 3 diseases caused by soil-borne, spore-forming bacteria.","answer":"Tetanus, Botulism, Anthrax"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1691","question":"Name 3 bacterial diseases that affect both humans and horses.","answer":"Tetanus, Botulism, Anthrax, Brucellosis, Lyme Disease"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1692","question":"Identify this disease:  all suspected or confirmed cases must be reported to the state veterinarian; this disease is listed as a bioterrorism alert in the US.","answer":"Anthrax"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1693","question":"What disease is caused by the bacterium Bacillus anthracis?","answer":"Anthrax"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1694","question":"Name ONE way a horse gets infected with anthrax.","answer":"Ingestion of bacteria spores (by grazing contaminated pastures); inhalation of bacteria; skin penetration (biting flies or open wounds exposed to infected soil or carcasses)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1695","question":"Give ONE reason why Anthrax bacteria can live in the soil for decades.","answer":"Low nutrient requirements, ability to survive temperature extremes"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1696","question":"Name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Anthrax.","answer":"Fever; colic; bloody diarrhea; difficulty breathing; muscle tremors; discharge of blood from body openings after death; abortions; blood-stained milk (FYI: Anthrax can be inhaled, ingested, or can enter through the skin!)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1697","question":"Name TWO diseases caused by the bacteria Clostridia.","answer":"Tetanus, Botulism (Shaker Foal Syndrome and Forage Poisoning), Enterotoxemia (Overeating Disease), foal septicemia (umbilical cord infection), gangrene"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1698","question":"What is another name for Enterotoxemia?","answer":"Overeating disease (FYI:  Enterotoxemia or overeating disease is a disease caused by the bacterium Clostridium perfringens.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1699","question":"2 part question:  Identify 3 diseases that are caused by a type of Clostridium bacteria and identify the specific type of Clostridium bacteria that causes each disease.","answer":"Tetanus – Clostridium tetani; Botulism (Shaker Foal Syndrome and Forage Poisoning)—Clostridium botulinum; Enterotoxemia or Overeating Disease—Clostridium perfringens; gangrene—Clostridium perfringens"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1700","question":"Why do foals that have just started eating grass and hay get Botulism?","answer":"Foals ingest the bacteria (spores) from the soil (which produces toxins in the foal's intestinal tract)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1701","question":"What is the name for a type of food poisoning that can be caused by hay or silage contaminated by a Clostridium bacterium?","answer":"Botulism (Shaker Foal Syndrome or Forage Poisoning)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1702","question":"Which type of hay bales is associated with a higher risk of Botulism?","answer":"Round bales"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1703","question":"Why is Botulism in foals sometimes called \"Shaker Foal Syndrome\"?","answer":"Foals have muscle tremors, weakness, and difficulty standing."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1704","question":"Which bacterial disease is called Shaker Foal Syndrome when it affects foals?","answer":"Botulism"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1705","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of Shaker Foal Syndrome or Botulism in foals.","answer":"Muscle weakness; decreased muscle tone (eyelids, tongue); difficulty swallowing (dysphagia); difficulty nursing; drooling after nursing; nasal discharge; difficulty breathing (dyspnea); dilated pupils; muscle tremors; colic, lying down (recumbency)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1706","question":"Name 3 ways horses can contract Botulism.","answer":"Eating feed containing the bacteria; eating feed containing the spores or toxins; wounds contaminated by bacteria"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1707","question":"“Forage Poisoning” is a form of Botulism in adult horses.  The neurotoxin blocks acetylcholine, an important neurotransmitter.  Name 3 signs or symptoms of Forage Poisoning.","answer":"Muscle weakness (can’t hold head up); decreased muscle tone (eyelids, tongue, anus, tail, etc.); difficulty swallowing (dysphagia); drooling; difficulty breathing (dyspnea); dilated pupils; abnormal gait; colic; lying down (recumbency)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1708","question":"What disease could most likely follow the infection of a deep puncture wound?","answer":"Tetanus"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1709","question":"What is a slang term for Tetanus?","answer":"Lockjaw"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1710","question":"What system of the horse does Tetanus affect?","answer":"Nervous system"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1711","question":"Which animal is considered the most sensitive to the Tetanus toxin?","answer":"Horse"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1712","question":"What specific microorganism causes Tetanus?","answer":"Clostridium tetani"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1713","question":"Identify this disease: prolapse of the third eyelid, trismus (spasms of the masseter muscle), muscle stiffness, high mortality rate, and sawhorse stance.","answer":"Tetanus"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1714","question":"Name 3 common wounds that serve as port of entry for Tetanus.","answer":"Puncture wounds (hoof, etc.); lower limb wounds; castration wounds; lacerations (head or tail); contaminated surgical sites; injection abscesses; infected umbilical stump structures (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1715","question":"What is the descriptive term of the stance of a horse with Tetanus?","answer":"Saw horse stance"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1716","question":"What bacterial disorder involves the production of toxins that result in paralysis, rigidity of muscles, and often death?","answer":"Tetanus"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1717","question":"Approximately how long does Tetanus antitoxin give protection?","answer":"1 – 2 weeks (7 – 14 days) [accept any number within these ranges]"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1718","question":"Trismus is a symptom exhibited in a horse with Tetanus.  The definition of trismus is the same as the common term for this disease.  What is trismus?","answer":"Lockjaw"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1719","question":"How long after a wound is sustained are symptoms of Tetanus likely to appear?","answer":"2 (two) days to 1 (one) month (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1720","question":"What is the name for the disease caused by Clostridium tetani?","answer":"Tetanus (also accept lockjaw)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1721","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Tetanus.","answer":"Lock jaw; sawhorse stance; elevated tail carriage; protrusion of 3rd eyelid (flashing); flared nostrils; muscle rigidity; inability to eat; constant excitement; stiff gait; hypersensitivity; fast heartbeat; fast respiratory rate; difficulty breathing"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1722","question":"Horses who recover from Potomac Horse Fever develop an immunity which lasts how long?","answer":"Up to 2 years"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1723","question":"What specific type of microorganism causes Potomac Horse Fever?","answer":"Parasite (Neorickettsia ristici formerly called Ehrlichia risticii) (FYI: Rickettsia are obligate intracellular parasites that are bacteria-like organisms that must live in the host’s cell to survive. Aquatic insects contain the parasite.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1724","question":"Name 3 treatments for Potomac Horse Fever.","answer":"Supportive care (IV fluids, anti-inflammatory medications); ice boots to prevent laminitis; antibiotics (Oxytetracycline) (FYI:  Antibiotics should be given early in the illness.  Symptoms quickly improve once antibiotics are started.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1725","question":"In reference to horse diseases, what does PHF stand for?","answer":"Potomac Horse Fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1726","question":"What disease, first recognized in Maryland in 1979, is characterized by fever, laminitis, colic, and diarrhea?","answer":"Potomac Horse Fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1727","question":"Besides depression and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Potomac Horse Fever.","answer":"Fever; laminitis; diarrhea (mild to profuse); colic (mild);  dehydration; shock; darkened gums"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1728","question":"What is the name of the bacterial infection that causes abscesses in the pectoral region, face, neck, and legs?  The lesions initially appear as small bumps.  House flies and stable flies may help spread this disease.","answer":"Pigeon fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1729","question":"Why is it difficult to eradicate Salmonella bacteria?","answer":"They are very resistant and are adaptable to environmental conditions. (They can survive long periods of time in the environment.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1730","question":"What is the treatment for Equine Salmonellosis?","answer":"Symptomatic treatment or supportive care (including IV fluid administration)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1731","question":"What is Equine Salmonellosis?","answer":"Infection with Salmonella bacteria (that causes profuse, watery diarrhea)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1732","question":"What is a common clinical symptom of horses infected with Equine Salmonellosis?","answer":"Diarrhea"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1733","question":"What bacteria is the most common cause of infectious enterocolitis in adult horses?","answer":"Salmonella"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1734","question":"Name 3 risk factors for Equine Salmonellosis.","answer":"Transportation; crowded conditions; abrupt change in diet; intense physical exercise; antimicrobial treatment; gastrointestinal tract disorders; surgery"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1735","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of Equine Salmonellosis.","answer":"Fever; depression; loss of appetite; profuse, watery diarrhea; foul-smelling diarrhea; blood in manure; dehydration; tachycardia (fast heart rate); septicemia; death; no symptoms"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1736","question":"What is purpura hemorrhagica?","answer":"Serious complication of Strangles or Strangles vaccine (that results in inflammation and hemorrhaging that is caused by an exaggerated immune response)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1737","question":"What SPECIFIC lymph nodes of the horse does Strangles affect?","answer":"Submaxillary and parotid lymph nodes (lymph nodes in the throatlatch area)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1738","question":"Give ONE other name for a Streptococcus equi infection.","answer":"Strangles, Equine Distemper, or Shipping Fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1739","question":"What is \"Bastard Strangles\"?","answer":"Form of Strangles that affects other areas of the body besides the head and neck (abdomen, brain, liver, kidneys, lungs, spleen, and internal lymph nodes)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1740","question":"Which bacteria is the cause of Strangles in horses?","answer":"Streptococcus equi"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1741","question":"Besides depression and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Strangles.","answer":"Fever (102 – 106); sore throat; swollen, hot lymph nodes;  abscessed or draining lymph nodes; nasal discharge (cloudy and thick); pain with eating; stands with neck stretched out, increased respiratory rate; increased heart rate"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1742","question":"What severely contagious bacterial infection causes abscessed lymph nodes under the jaw?","answer":"Strangles (also called Equine Distemper, Shipping Fever, and Streptococcus equi)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1743","question":"Give ONE other name for Shipping Fever.","answer":"Strangles, Equine Distemper, or Streptococcus equi"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1744","question":"Name ONE thing that happens to the lymph nodes of horses with Strangles.","answer":"Lymph nodes become hot, swollen, and painful and they may abscess"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1745","question":"Name ONE way Strangles is spread.","answer":"Direct contact (touching other horses); indirect contact (contact with infected secretions on tack, equipment, or handlers, water troughs, feed) (FYI:  Strangles bacteria can survive in the environment for several weeks.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1746","question":"Give ONE other name for Strangles.","answer":"Distemper, shipping fever, or Streptococcus equi"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1747","question":"What characteristic makes Strangles easy to identify?","answer":"Swollen and/or abscessed lymph nodes in the throatlatch area"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1748","question":"Why should the Strangles vaccine only be given to at risk horses?","answer":"Because horses can get serious complications from the vaccine (purpura hemorrhagica)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1749","question":"Name TWO systemic fungal diseases that affect horses.","answer":"Aspergillosis, Blastomycosis, Coccidiomycosis, Histoplasmosis (Do NOT accept ringworm because it is not systemic or occurring throughout the body)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1750","question":"Name 3 ways you can help prevent infectious diseases in horses.","answer":"Vaccinate; avoid sick animals; isolate sick animals; isolate new animals; keep barn clean; wash hands; disinfect boots; provide boot dip; disposable boots; clean trailer; disinfect trailer; don’t re-use needles (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1751","question":"Name TWO equine diseases that are caused by protozoa.","answer":"Giardia (Giardiasis); Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis (EPM); Equine Piroplasmosis (Babesiosis)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1752","question":"In reference to horse diseases, what do the initials EPM stand for?","answer":"Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis (FYI: EPM is an infection of the brain and spinal cord caused by the protozoan Sarcocystis neurona.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1753","question":"What animal is the reservoir host for Sarcocystis neurona?","answer":"Opossum (FYI: Sarcocystis neurona is the protozoan that causes EPM or Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1754","question":"What is the definitive host for Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis?","answer":"Opossum (FYI: EPM is caused by the protozoan Sarcocystis neurona.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1755","question":"Diagnosis of EPM or Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis is difficult and will require the vet to do what test?","answer":"Spinal tap (lumbar puncture)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1756","question":"The protozoan Sarcocystis neurona causes what disease?","answer":"EPM or Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1757","question":"What is the COMMON name for the bacterial infection that causes the skin to crust and the hair to come off in clumps?  The skin underneath the crust is pink and irritated.  This condition is more common in hot and/or humid weather.","answer":"Rain rot or rain scald (accept either) (FYI:  The scientific name is dermatophilosis and it’s caused by the bacterium Dermatophilus congolensis.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1758","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of septicemia.","answer":"Fever; depression; loss of appetite; excessive sleeping; hot, swollen, or painful joints; hot or swollen navel; navel discharge"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1759","question":"Describe ONE early symptom of neonatal septicemia.","answer":"Fever; depression; loss of appetite; excessive sleeping;  weakness; weak sucking reflex; diarrhea"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1760","question":"An untreated umbilical cord can cause a bacterial infection known as what?","answer":"Septicemia or sepsis (accept either)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1761","question":"With septicemia, infection spreads throughout the horse’s body causing multi-organ problems.  How does this infection spread?","answer":"Through the bloodstream"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1762","question":"What is another name for \"blood poisoning\"?","answer":"Septicemia or sepsis (accept either)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1763","question":"What is the general term for inflammation of the skin?","answer":"Dermatitis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1764","question":"What is the condition known as grease heel or scratches?","answer":"Inflammation or infection of the skin on the back of the heel or pastern (also called mud fever)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1765","question":"Give ONE term used to describe a bacterial or fungal infection of the skin on the heel or back of the pastern.","answer":"Grease heel, scratches, or mud fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1766","question":"What is an acute infection?","answer":"Infection where symptoms appear quickly (also accept any infection that lasts a short time)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1767","question":"In reference to diseases, what is a \"carrier\"?","answer":"Animal who carries and transmits a disease (who may or may not show any symptoms for the disease)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1768","question":"What is a chronic infection?","answer":"Infection that lasts a long time"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1769","question":"What is a contagious disease?","answer":"One that may be transmitted from one animal to another by direct or indirect contact"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1770","question":"What is the general term for a disease that is communicable or transmissible from one individual to another?","answer":"Contagious"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1771","question":"What is a dead end or terminal host?","answer":"Host from which infectious agents are not transmissible"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1772","question":"A reservoir host is an animal in which a virus lives before it causes disease in other animals.  Name ONE of the most common types of animals which serve as reservoir hosts.","answer":"Birds, rodents, reptiles"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1773","question":"What is the term for the time period between exposure to an infection and the onset of clinical signs?","answer":"Incubation"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1774","question":"Define incubation period.","answer":"Period between exposure and first signs or symptoms of an infectious disease"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1775","question":"What do you call the type of disease that is caused by pathogenic microorganisms such as bacteria, viruses, and fungi?","answer":"Infectious"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1776","question":"Ideally, to help prevent disease transmission, how long should a new horse be isolated before introducing it into an established group?","answer":"14 - 21 days (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1777","question":"What is an insect vector?","answer":"Insect that carries and transmits disease-causing organisms"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1778","question":"What are the TWO most important factors that determine whether a disease-causing organism will produce disease in an exposed animal?","answer":"Virulence (strength of the organism) and animal's resistance"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1779","question":"Disease-causing organisms vary greatly in their ability to produce disease.  What is the term used when the ability to produce disease is great?","answer":"Virulent"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1780","question":"What is a zoonotic disease?","answer":"Disease that is transmissible from animals to humans"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1781","question":"Name TWO tick-borne diseases in horses.","answer":"Lyme Disease; tick-bite paralysis; Equine Piroplasmosis; Equine Ehrlichiosis (Anaplasmosis); African horse fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1782","question":"What is the vector for Lyme disease?","answer":"Ticks (specifically Ixodes ticks such as deer ticks, bear ticks, and Western black-legged ticks)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1783","question":"Name the disease carried by deer ticks that's caused by the bacterium Borrelia burgdorferi.","answer":"Lyme disease"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1784","question":"What is the COMMON name for Borreliosis?","answer":"Lyme disease (FYI: Lyme disease is caused by the bacterium Borrelia burgdorferi.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1785","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Lyme Disease in horses.","answer":"Arthritis; dermatitis; uveitis; lameness; sweating; difficulty swallowing (dysphagia); glazed eyes; head tilt; tail paralysis; wandering aimlessly (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1786","question":"2 part question:  What is Equine Piroplasmosis and how is it transmitted?","answer":"Equine protozoal infectious disease; transmitted by ticks"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1787","question":"What SPECIFICALLY causes tick-bite paralysis?","answer":"Salivary neurotoxin produced by ticks (American dog tick and Rocky Mountain Wood Tick)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1788","question":"What is a slang term for Western and/or Eastern encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Sleeping sickness"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1789","question":"What is encephalitis?","answer":"Inflammation of the brain"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1790","question":"Name ONE external parasite that spreads Equine Encephalomyelitis.","answer":"Mosquitoes, horse flies, deer flies"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1791","question":"Viruses that cause Eastern, Western, and Venezuelan Encephalomyelitis are arboviruses.  What is an arbovirus?","answer":"Virus transmitted by bloodsucking insects (arthropod borne virus)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1792","question":"Name 3 types of Equine Encephalomyelitis.","answer":"Eastern, Western, Venezuelan, West Nile (FYI: Encephalomyelitis is inflammation of the brain and spinal cord.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1793","question":"Name ONE of the equine encephalomyelitis viruses that is communicable to people.","answer":"West Nile, VEE (Venezuelan Equine Encephalomyelitis)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"intermediate","number":"1794","question":"What term means an inflammation of the brain?","answer":"Encephalitis (FYI: Encephalomyelitis means inflammation of the brain and spinal cord.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1795","question":"Where do mosquitoes contact Eastern, Western, and Venezuelan Encephalomyelitis viruses?","answer":"From a wild host (birds) (FYI:  Rats, bats, and opossums may also serve as reservoir hosts for VEE.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1796","question":"Why are WEE, EEE, and VEE called \"sleeping sickness\"?","answer":"Infection causes profound depression or sleepiness."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1797","question":"Which type of equine encephalomyelitis has the LOWEST mortality rate?","answer":"WEE (Western Equine Encephalomyelitis)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1798","question":"Which type of equine encephalomyelitis can be transmitted horse to horse?","answer":"VEE (Venezuelan Equine Encephalomyelitis)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1799","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Sleeping Sickness or Equine Encephalomyelitis.","answer":"Weakness; incoordination; irregular gait; seizures; hanging head low; head pressing; unable to swallow; circling; staggering; paralysis; lying down (recumbency); stupor; tongue may hang out; drooping lower lip; swollen eyelids; stiffness"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1800","question":"Give ONE other name for Equine Infectious Anemia.","answer":"EIA or swamp fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1801","question":"What is the test for Equine Infectious Anemia?","answer":"Coggins test (FYI:  The \"gold standard\" test is the Coggins test which is an AGID (agar gel immunodiffusion) test.  ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay) tests are also available.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1802","question":"A Coggins positive horse is a threat to whom?","answer":"Other horses (FYI: Once horses have EIA, they have it for life so they must be isolated or euthanized.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1803","question":"Name ONE insect that transmits Equine Infectious Anemia to horses.","answer":"Horse flies, deerflies, mosquitoes"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1804","question":"The Coggins test is used to detect what disease?","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia, EIA, or Swamp Fever (accept any)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1805","question":"Identify this disease: virus attacks red blood cells causing anemia and jaundice; no effective treatment or vaccine; once infected horse is a carrier for life; diagnosed by Coggins test.","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia or EIA (accept either)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1806","question":"What is a SLANG name for EIA or Equine Infectious Anemia?","answer":"Swamp fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1807","question":"What is a troublesome feature of Equine Infectious Anemia?","answer":"Once a horse is infected, it’s infected for life"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1808","question":"Equine Infectious Anemia viruses can only live in which animals?","answer":"Equines (horses and their close relatives like donkeys and mules)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1809","question":"In reference to horse diseases, what do the initials EIA stand for?","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1810","question":"What protein molecules does the Coggins test SPECIFICALLY check for in the horse’s blood?","answer":"Antibodies against the EIA virus"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1811","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Equine Infectious Anemia.","answer":"No signs; weight loss; anemia; fatigue; swelling (edema); weak pulse; irregular heartbeat; jaundice; enlarged spleen; once infected, the animal is infected for life"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1812","question":"In reference to horse diseases, what does EVA stand for?","answer":"Equine Viral Arteritis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1813","question":"What sex of the horse can become a long-term carrier of Equine Viral Arteritis?","answer":"Male"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1814","question":"What virus that affects horses also affects swine?","answer":"EAV or Equine Arteritis Virus (accept either)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1815","question":"Name ONE way to prevent outbreaks of EVA.","answer":"Identify the carrier stallions; use management practices to prevent the introduction of EVA positive horses into a non-infected herd"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1816","question":"Stallions from which TWO breeds are extremely likely to test positive for EVA or Equine Viral Arteritis?","answer":"Standardbreds and Warmbloods (especially Austrian Warmbloods)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1817","question":"Why should you test stallions for the presence of EVA antibodies BEFORE you vaccinate them?","answer":"Because it's not possible to differentiate between vaccine- induced antibodies and those caused by an infection"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1818","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Equine Viral Arteritis.","answer":"Asymptomatic; swelling (edema or stocking up); nasal discharge; conjunctivitis; excessive tearing from eyes; stiff gait; abortions; stallions can be carriers; can be transmitted via respiratory droplets or sexually"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1819","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of EVA or Equine Viral Arteritis.","answer":"No symptoms, swelling (edema or stocking up), nasal discharge, conjunctivitis, excessive tearing from eyes, abortions, stiff gait, stallions can be carriers, can have respiratory or sexual transmission"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1820","question":"Name ONE treatment for influenza.","answer":"Rest (one week for every day of fever); supportive care (IV fluids, control fever and discomfort, keep nasal passages clear); antibiotics only for secondary bacterial infections"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1821","question":"What is the most common infectious respiratory disease of the horse?","answer":"Influenza (flu)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1822","question":"Give TWO signs, symptoms, or features of influenza.","answer":"Fever (up to 106); depression; loss of appetite; cough (frequent, dry, harsh); nasal discharge"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1823","question":"Name ONE way influenza spreads rapidly through a group of horses.","answer":"By horses coughing, by moisture droplets traveling through the air, or by contaminated surfaces"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1824","question":"Name TWO equine influenza A viruses.","answer":"Equine 1 (H7N7) and Equine 2 (H3N8)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1825","question":"Besides depression and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Influenza.","answer":"Fever (up to 106); cough (frequent, dry, harsh); nasal discharge"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1826","question":"How far can the influenza virus travel when an infected horse coughs?","answer":"35 yards"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1827","question":"Rest is a primary treatment for horses with influenza.  How long should the horse be rested?","answer":"1 (one) week for each day of fever"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1828","question":"Name TWO wildlife species that serve as reservoir hosts for Rabies.","answer":"Raccoon, skunk, fox, coyote, bat"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1829","question":"What disease of the nervous system is caused by a bite from an infected animal?","answer":"Rabies"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1830","question":"How is Rabies transmitted or spread?","answer":"Bite from infected animal"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1831","question":"How is a diagnosis of rabies confirmed?","answer":"Post mortem examination of an animal's brain (necropsy)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1832","question":"What mammal is considered to be the primary source of Rabies in horses?","answer":"Skunk"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1833","question":"Identify this disease:  caused by a rhabdovirus, infects the nervous system, can be transmitted to any mammal, no treatment, fatal if horse has not been previously vaccinated, transmitted by bites from infected animals.","answer":"Rabies"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1834","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of Rabies.","answer":"Altered behavior (aggressive “furious Rabies” or depressed “dumb Rabies”); inability to swallow; drooling; hyper-responsiveness; head pressing; weakness; uncoordinated gait (ataxia); blindness; hyperactivity; seizures; fear; lameness; colic"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1835","question":"What system of the horse does rhinopneumonitis affect?","answer":"Respiratory system"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1836","question":"Besides depression and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Rhinopneumonitis.","answer":"Fever; nasal discharge; cough; abortion (EHV-1); neurological problems (EHV-1)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1837","question":"What are TWO primary reasons for the Equine Herpes Virus vaccination?","answer":"Prevention of abortion in pregnant mares; prevention of Rhinopneumonitis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1838","question":"For what disease is a vaccine given to broodmares at the 5th, 7th and 9th months of pregnancy?","answer":"Rhinopneumonitis (Equine Herpes Virus)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1839","question":"What virus causes Rhinopneumonitis?","answer":"Equine Herpes Virus (EHV-4, EHV-1)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1840","question":"It's estimated that what percent of horses have been infected with Equine Herpes Virus sometime within their lives?","answer":"90 - 100% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1841","question":"Stable cough is the slang term for which viral equine disease?","answer":"Rhinopneumonitis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1842","question":"How long can horses shed the EHV-1 virus?","answer":"Up to 21 days"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1843","question":"In reference to horse diseases, what does EHV-1 stand for?","answer":"Equine Herpes Virus-1 (FYI:  EHV-1 can cause rhinopneumonitis, abortions, and neurological disease.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1844","question":"What are the TWO most common abortion-causing viral diseases in horses in the US?","answer":"Equine Herpes Virus (EHV-1) and Equine Viral Arteritis (EVA)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1845","question":"What is the most common viral cause of abortions in mares?","answer":"Equine Herpes Virus-1 (EHV-1)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1846","question":"Abortions attributable to EHV-1 usually occur at what stage of gestation?","answer":"8 - 11 months (last trimester)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1847","question":"Equine Herpes Virus-1 causes Rhinopneumonitis in horses. Name ONE other problem EHV-1 can cause.","answer":"Abortion in pregnant mares, birth of weak foals, or neurological disease"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1848","question":"Give 3 ways to help prevent rotavirus infections in foals.","answer":"Vaccinate pregnant mares (at 8, 9, and 10 months gestation); isolate sick foal; good hygiene (wash hands, use boot dip, wear disposable gloves and boots); good management practices (clean and disinfect stalls)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1849","question":"What is the most common viral cause of foal diarrhea?","answer":"Rotavirus"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1850","question":"Besides fever and depression, name 3 signs, symptoms, or features of Rotavirus infections in foals.","answer":"Anorexia (loss of appetite); watery diarrhea; dehydration; decreased sucking; highly contagious"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1851","question":"What viral disease of horses causes blister-like lesions of the mouth, dental pad, tongue, lips, nostrils, hooves, and teats?","answer":"Vesicular stomatitis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1852","question":"Vesicular stomatitis is a viral disease that results in the formation of vesicles in the mouth and on the lips, hooves, and teats.  What is a vesicle?","answer":"Fluid-filled sac or blister-like lesion (accept either)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1853","question":"Which disease has outward signs which are very similar to vesicular stomatitis?","answer":"Hoof and mouth disease"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1854","question":"What is the incubation period for vesicular stomatitis?","answer":"2 – 8 days (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1855","question":"Name TWO changes that can be made to the diet of a horse that is experiencing pain due to mouth lesions.","answer":"Put on pasture; feed a mash by adding water to feed (such as pellets or brans)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1856","question":"Name 3 diseases that must be ruled out before making a definitive diagnosis of West Nile.","answer":"EPM (Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis); EEE (Eastern Equine Encephalitis); WEE (Western Equine Encephalitis); VEE (Venezuelan Equine Encephalitis); rabies; botulism"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1857","question":"Give ONE treatment for West Nile.","answer":"Treat the symptoms (rest, IV fluids, anti-inflammatories for fever and pain); pad stall; antibiotics only for secondary bacterial infections"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1858","question":"Which virus is the leading cause of arbovirus encephalitis in horses and humans in the US?","answer":"West Nile (FYI: An arbovirus is an Arthropod Borne Virus.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1859","question":"Since birds are the reservoir host for West Nile, finding a large number of dead ones can be a signal that the virus is present in the area.  Name 3 of the birds most often associated with West Nile.","answer":"Blue jays, crows, ravens, raptors (eagles, owls, hawks etc.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1860","question":"What is the incubation period for West Nile Disease?","answer":"5 - 15 days (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1861","question":"Wild birds are the principal reservoir of which virus?","answer":"West Nile (or other encephalomyelitis viruses such as EEE or WEE)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1862","question":"Which neurological infectious disease was first detected in the US in 1999?","answer":"West Nile"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1863","question":"What is the recovery rate for horses infected with West Nile?","answer":"50% or higher"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1864","question":"Many horses infected with West Nile will begin to improve how many days after displaying clinical signs?","answer":"3 – 7 days (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1865","question":"Why are antibiotics NOT usually given to horses with West Nile?","answer":"West Nile is a viral disease and antibiotics are used to treat bacterial diseases. (FYI:  Antibiotics should NOT be given for viral infections unless there’s evidence of a secondary bacterial infection.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1866","question":"Besides fever, depression, and anorexia or loss of appetite, name 3 signs or symptoms of West Nile.","answer":"Weakness; incoordination (ataxia); paralysis; inability to swallow (dysphagia); head pressing; circling; aimless wandering; seizures; hyper-excitability; coma; behavioral changes; abnormal gait; muscle twitching; falling asleep during activities"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1867","question":"What is the first step in a disease prevention plan?","answer":"Consult a vet"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"int bonus","number":"1868","question":"Identify the 3 diseases or conditions by the following stances or body positions: sawhorse stance; outstretched head and neck; and sitting dog stance.","answer":"Sawhorse stance—tetanus; outstretched head and neck—strangles or choke; sitting dog stance—laminitis"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1869","question":"Name 3 causes of slobbering or excessive salivation in horses.","answer":"Feeds (such as red clover); choke; dental problems; inappropriate bits; infectious diseases (such as Rabies or vesicular stomatitis); shavings (containing bitterweed); drugs"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1870","question":"Name TWO health problems that can be created by moldy or dusty hay.","answer":"Colic, heaves, allergies"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1871","question":"What general term describes a disease of a muscle?","answer":"Myopathy (my-AHH-path-ee)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1872","question":"What is the difference between hyperplasia and hypertrophy?","answer":"Hyperplasia is an increase in the number of cells; hypertrophy is an increase in the size of the cells."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1873","question":"What is the condition in which cerebrospinal fluid accumulates, causing the head to enlarge and the central nervous system to be abnormal?","answer":"Hydrocephalus (hie-droe-SEF-ah-lus)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1874","question":"What is the difference between hemiparesis and hemiplegia? (hem-ee-pair-EE-sis and hem-ee-PLEEJ-ee-ah)","answer":"Hemiparesis is weakness on one side of the body; hemiplegia is paralysis on one side of the body."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1875","question":"What is the MEDICAL term for an uncoordinated gait?","answer":"Ataxia [FYI:  Wobbler’s Syndrome or CMD (cervical spondilomyopathy) is seen in large dogs and horses and can cause ataxia.]"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1876","question":"Describe Wobbler's Syndrome.","answer":"Incoordination of the back legs (generally in growing horses) caused by compression of the cervical spinal cord"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1877","question":"Hemiparesis is weakness on one side of the body. What does the term hemiplegia describe?","answer":"Paralysis on one side of the body"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1878","question":"Name 3 disorders of the horse that are affected by nutritional management.","answer":"Colic; laminitis; gastric ulcers (EGUS); Equine Metabolic Syndrome (EMS); Cushing’s disease; developmental orthopedic disease (DOD); hyperkalemic periodic paralysis (HYPP); exertional rhabdomyolysis (Tying Up); heaves (COPD)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1879","question":"What causes Big Head Disease?","answer":"Excessive phosphorus and/or low calcium in the diet (FYI: Big Head Disease is also called Miller's Disease, Bran Disease, and nutritional secondary hyperparathyroidism.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1880","question":"Give ONE common name for nutritional secondary hyperparathyroidism.","answer":"Big Head Disease, Miller's Disease, Bran Disease"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1881","question":"Horses with dietary deficiencies of what mineral can develop Bran Disease?","answer":"Calcium (FYI:  It's also called Big Head Disease, Miller's Disease, and Nutritional Secondary Hyperparathyroidism.  It can also be caused by too much phosphorus in the diet.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1882","question":"What disease is caused by a toxin-producing fungus found in contaminated corn that's consumed by horses?","answer":"Moldy corn poisoning, leukoencephalomalacia, or blind staggers (accept any)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1883","question":"What is White Muscle Disease?","answer":"Disease of the muscles caused by deficiencies of selenium and/or Vitamin E (FYI:  Muscles become pale.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1884","question":"In areas where the soil has low available selenium content, what disease can be prevalent in foals if the mares are fed homegrown feeds?","answer":"White muscle disease (FYI: White muscle disease is caused by low selenium and/or low Vitamin E.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1885","question":"2 part question:  What is Exercise Induced Pulmonary Hemorrhage and what causes it?","answer":"Bleeding from the respiratory tract (or nose) after physical exertion; caused by the bursting of small blood vessels in the lungs"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1886","question":"What is epistaxis? (eh-pee-STAX-is)","answer":"Bleeding from the nose (FYI: It often occurs in EIPH or Exercise Induced Pulmonary Hemorrhage.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1887","question":"What medication is commonly used to treat exercise induced pulmonary hemorrhage?","answer":"Lasix (also accept Salix or Furosemide)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1888","question":"What is the SLANG term for a horse that bleeds from the lungs due to strenuous physical exertion?","answer":"Bleeder"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1889","question":"What is pulmonary hemorrhage?","answer":"Bleeding in the lungs"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1890","question":"What is the COMMON name of the respiratory disease, often of older horses, that causes coughing, nasal discharge, wheezing, and heaving of flanks?","answer":"Heaves (FYI:  It’s also called COPD, Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease, RAO, or Recurrent Airway Obstruction.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1891","question":"What is a common respiratory disease of older horses?","answer":"Heaves, COPD (Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease), RAO (Recurrent Airway Obstruction) (accept any term or acronym)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1892","question":"What part of the lungs is damaged when a horse has pulmonary emphysema?","answer":"Alveoli (al-VEE-oh-lie)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1893","question":"Which respiratory disease is an allergic and inflammatory disorder that may develop after respiratory infections?","answer":"Heaves, COPD (Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease), or RAO (Recurrent Airway Obstruction) [accept any term or acronym]"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1894","question":"Describe 3 management guidelines for decreasing a horse’s symptoms of heaves.","answer":"Leave horse on pasture; provide lots of fresh air; provide good ventilation; decrease dust; wet food; feed pelleted food; use dust-free bedding; spray down stall; use fans; adjust humidity; give medications (antihistamines, steroids, bronchodilators)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1895","question":"What is the term for inflammation of the membranes surrounding the lungs?","answer":"Pleurisy"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1896","question":"What is pleurisy?","answer":"Inflammation of the membranes surrounding the lungs (FYI: often a complication of respiratory infections)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1897","question":"What is the major cause of death in foals less than 8 months of age?","answer":"Pneumonia"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1898","question":"What is the term for an infection localized in the lungs?","answer":"Pneumonia or pneumonitis (accept either)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1899","question":"Explain the unsoundness \"roaring\".","answer":"Whistling or wheezing when breathing (due to an obstruction of the larynx caused by partial paralysis)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1900","question":"The vocal chords are two muscles that project across the lower part of the larynx.  Paralysis on one or both of the muscles results in a condition known as what?","answer":"Roaring (FYI: Roaring is called recurrent laryngeal hemiplegia.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1901","question":"What is the MEDICAL TERM for the condition characterized by excessive noises with breathing, especially during exercise?  This condition is caused by an upper airway obstruction.","answer":"Laryngeal hemiplegia (FYI:  Recurrent laryngeal hemiplegia is paralysis of a vocal cord, usually due to a damaged left recurrent laryngeal nerve.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1902","question":"What is the SLANG term for a horse that whistles or wheezes during exercise?","answer":"Roarer"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1903","question":"Many developmental orthopedic diseases are due problems with endochondral ossification.  What is endochondral ossification?","answer":"Development of cartilage into bone"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1904","question":"Name 3 major factors that predispose a growing animal to DOD (developmental orthopedic disease).","answer":"Rapid growth; trauma to growth plates; genetic predisposition; nutritional imbalance"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1905","question":"What is osteochondritis? (ahs-tee-oh-con-DRIGHT-is)?","answer":"Improper maturation of cartilage to bone (FYI:  Osteochondritis affects the cartilage and subchondral bone of joints.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1906","question":"Name 3 causes of skin and hair problems in horses.","answer":"Infections (bacterial, viral, fungal); parasites (summer sores); trauma; photosensitivity (sunburn); chemicals; irritants; nutritional deficiencies; allergies (hives); tumors; alopecia (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1907","question":"What is a caruncle?","answer":"Small, fleshy outgrowth"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1908","question":"What procedure is used in the treatment of sarcoid lesions that causes destruction of tissue by the application of extreme cold?","answer":"Cryosurgery (also accept cryotherapy)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1909","question":"What is a tumor of pigment-forming cells that's commonly seen in older gray horses?","answer":"Melanoma"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1910","question":"By age 15 most gray horses will have developed what condition?","answer":"Melanoma"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1911","question":"What is a sarcoid?","answer":"Type of skin tumor in horses"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1912","question":"Name ONE area where sarcoids occur.","answer":"Eyelids, ears, head, legs, sheath"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1913","question":"What is thought to be the cause of sarcoids?","answer":"Virus (such as BPV or bovine papilloma virus, but the exact cause is unknown) (FYI: Sarcoids are benign, wart-like tumors that can recur.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1914","question":"What is the name of a common skin condition of the horse that can resemble an ulcerated wart and may be caused by a virus?","answer":"Sarcoid"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1915","question":"Name 3 of the categories of sarcoids.","answer":"Occult, verrucous, nodular, fibroblastic, mixed"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1916","question":"Name TWO breeds that are predisposed to developing squamous cell carcinoma.","answer":"Appaloosa, Paint, Belgian (FYI: Squamous cell carcinoma is a type of skin cancer that develops on horses with large areas of white hair and pink skin, especially on the face.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1917","question":"Name 3 treatments for a horse with squamous cell carcinoma.","answer":"Surgical removal; chemotherapy; laser; freezing; radiation; combination of these"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1918","question":"In reference to diseases, what does endemic mean?","answer":"Prevalent or very commonly found (accept either)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1919","question":"What is the study of the transmission and control of diseases?","answer":"Epidemiology"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1920","question":"What does the term \"pathological\" mean?","answer":"Diseased condition"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1921","question":"What is another name for a benign fatty tumor?","answer":"Lipoma"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1922","question":"What is the term for a tumor that is not malignant?","answer":"Benign"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"easy","number":"1923","question":"Give ONE other name for Monday Morning Sickness.","answer":"Tying Up (also called Monday Morning Sickness, Azoturia, Black Water Disease, Exertional Rhabdomyolysis, and other names)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1924","question":"Why do horses that \"tie up\" sometimes have dark or coffee colored urine?","answer":"Breakdown of muscle tissue causes myoglobin to be released into the urine."},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1925","question":"What is the muscle disorder that can appear in horses under regular heavy exercise that are not worked for a few days, yet still remain on full feed?  It can also occur in out-of-condition horses that have been worked too hard.","answer":"Tying Up (also called Monday Morning Sickness, Azoturia, Black Water Disease, Exertional Rhabdomyolysis, and other names)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1926","question":"Why should you reduce the grain intake of a horse on non-work days?","answer":"To avoid Tying Up (also called Monday Morning Sickness, Azoturia, Black Water Disease, Exertional Rhabdomyolysis, and other names)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1927","question":"Horses that develop firm back and hindquarter muscles after exercise (to the point where they are unable to move) are said to be suffering from what?","answer":"Tying up (also called Monday Morning Sickness, Azoturia, Black Water Disease, Exertional Rhabdomyolysis, and other names)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1928","question":"Name TWO things that can be done to prevent Tying Up.","answer":"Regular exercise; don’t overwork; avoid long periods of stall rest; warm up slowly; add fiber to diet; decrease grain; add fat to diet; add nutritional supplements if needed"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"sr bonus","number":"1929","question":"Name 3 symptoms of Tying Up.","answer":"Reluctance to move; stiffness; tremors; firm, tender muscles over loin and croup; sweating (diaphoresis); rapid, shallow breathing (tachypnea); rapid heart rate (tachycardia); dark urine (myoglobinuria)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1930","question":"Horses with recurrence of urinary calculi would benefit from feeding a diet that has less of what specific mineral?","answer":"Calcium (FYI:  Urinary calculi are kidney and bladder stones.)"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"hard","number":"1931","question":"A horse with chronic renal failure would require a diet that has less of certain nutrients.  Name TWO of these nutrients.","answer":"Protein, calcium, phosphorus"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1932","question":"What part of the horse’s body is not functioning properly if the horse has renal failure?","answer":"Kidneys"},
{"category":"Diseases","level":"medium","number":"1933","question":"What is cystitis?","answer":"Infection or inflammation of the bladder"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1934","question":"What is the purpose of a cutting competition?","answer":"To show the ability of the horse to cut a cow from a herd and prevent it from returning"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1935","question":"What is a \"cutting horse\"?","answer":"Horse who's trained to separate one animal from the herd (horse used in a cutting class)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1936","question":"Which breed dominates cutting competitions?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1937","question":"In reference to cutting, how long are a horses and rider given to demonstrate their skills?","answer":"2 ½ minutes"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1938","question":"During a cutting horse competition, when does the rider lift the reins and signal the horse to “quit the cow”?","answer":"When the cow turns away or gives up its efforts to return to the herd"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1939","question":"2 part question:  Where did the sport of cutting begin and where did the name come from?","answer":"On ranches (in the early 1800's); cows had to be separated or cut from the herd for branding, medical treatments, etc."},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1940","question":"In which equine sport does the rider \"drop\" the reins and allow the horse to work independent of any guidance?","answer":"Cutting"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1941","question":"For what specific equine competition would you have \"herd holders\"?","answer":"Cutting"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1942","question":"What is the beginning score for a cutting horse entry?","answer":"70"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1943","question":"Name 3 things that cutting performances are judged on.","answer":"Challenges made by the cattle cut, horse's instinctive reactions, errors made by horse and/or rider (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1944","question":"What term refers both to a system of training horses and a competitive equestrian sport?","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1945","question":"Dressage has its roots in classical Greek horsemanship, but it was not recognized as an important equestrian pursuit until what era?","answer":"Renaissance"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1946","question":"Dressage has its roots in the classical horsemanship of what country?","answer":"Greece"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1947","question":"Why can dressage for horses be compared to ballet training for humans?","answer":"Both dressage and ballet progressively develop musculature and coordination (develop balance and correct movement)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1948","question":"What do you call advanced exercises and training in horsemanship?","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1949","question":"The term dressage comes from a French word meaning what?","answer":"Training"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1950","question":"What do the initials USDF stand for?","answer":"United States Dressage Federation"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1951","question":"In equine competition, what is \"kur\"?","answer":"Musical freestyle ride in dressage"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1952","question":"In reference to dressage, the popularity of dressage greatly increased with the addition of which competition?","answer":"Freestyle dressage"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1953","question":"Kur is the term for what type of musical freestyle performance? (pronounced cure)","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1954","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the two-track exercise in which the horse moves forward and sideways at the same time?","answer":"Half pass"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1955","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the movement in which the horse trots in a very cadenced, floating manner with a marked period of suspension?","answer":"Passage (rhymes with massage)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1956","question":"In reference to dressage, describe the difference between the movements piaffe and passage. (PEE-ahff and puh-SAHJ)","answer":"Piaffe is a trot in place; passage (is a highly collected trot) with forward movement"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1957","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the highly, collected trot in place with a prolonged period of suspension?","answer":"Piaffe (PEE-ahf)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1958","question":"In reference to dressage, describe the difference between the movements travers and renvers. (TRA-vair and RON-vair)","answer":"Travers—haunches in; renvers—haunches out (in reference to riding on the rail)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1959","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the correct term for a full turn on the haunches?","answer":"Volte (pronounced volt)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1960","question":"In reference to dressage, name ONE of the classical “airs above the ground” movements when all 4 feet are off the ground.","answer":"Ballotade, capriole, croupade"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1961","question":"Airs above the ground refers to any of the dressage movements in which the horse's forelegs or both forelegs and hind legs are off the ground.  Which legs are off the ground when performing a capriole? (ca-pree-OLE)","answer":"Both fore and hind legs (FYI: Capriole means \"leap of the goat\".)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1962","question":"In reference to dressage, what is the term for the highly schooled movements in which the horse’s forelegs or the forelegs and hind legs are off the ground?","answer":"Airs above the ground"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"1963","question":"In reference to dressage, at what marker does the horse and rider enter the dressage arena?","answer":"A"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1964","question":"Starting with the entry point and going clockwise, what are the 8 letters of the small dressage ring?","answer":"A  K  E  H  C  M  B  F (FYI pneumonic:  All King Edwards' Horses Can Manage Big Fences; small dressage rings are 20 meters x 40 meters)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1965","question":"Name 3 of the trots that might be called for in a dressage test.","answer":"Collected, medium, working, extended"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1966","question":"There are 5 different walks in a dressage test.  Which of these would be completed with the horse on a \"long rein\"?","answer":"Free walk"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1967","question":"Name 3 walks that might be called for in a dressage test.","answer":"Working walk, collected walk, medium walk, extended walk, free walk"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1968","question":"How does a collected walk differ from a medium walk as used in dressage?","answer":"Collected walk is shorter and has more action than the medium walk"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1969","question":"In reference to driving, why are the tails of driving and working horses docked?","answer":"To prevent the tail from getting caught in the driving lines and harness"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1970","question":"In reference to driving, on which side does the driver mount the vehicle?","answer":"Right or off side (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1971","question":"When driving a horse, the bearing rein is the rein opposite the direction of the desired movement. Which rein is the bearing rein when you give a draft horse the verbal cue of haw?","answer":"Right rein (FYI: Haw is a left turn; gee is a right turn.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1972","question":"In reference to driving, what is the term for the cloth that's draped across the lap of passengers to keep them warm and dry when riding in a carriage?","answer":"Apron, rug, or lap robe (accept any)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1973","question":"What is the name for the metal rod on which the wheels of a carriage turn?","answer":"Axle"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1974","question":"In reference to carriages, what is the \"box\"?","answer":"Driver's seat"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1975","question":"English stagecoaches often were accompanied by a cockhorse that was ridden behind the coach.  What was the purpose of the cockhorse?","answer":"Hitched in front of the team when going up steep hills or heavy going"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1976","question":"2 part question:  When driving a team, what are the verbal commands for turning and which direction are they for?","answer":"Gee—right turn; haw—left turn"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1977","question":"In reference to driving, where does the coachman sit on a hansom cab?","answer":"On a seat outside the body of the carriage behind the enclosed passenger seat"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1978","question":"In reference to driving, what is a jerk line?","answer":"Single rein fastened to the brake handle of a carriage and run through the driver’s hand to the bit of the lead horse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1979","question":"What term refers to the mounted horseman who rode on the outside of a stagecoach for protection from bandits?","answer":"Outrider"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1980","question":"When showing the Hackney Pony in harness classes, name 3 types of hitches used?","answer":"Single, pairs, tandem"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1981","question":"When hitching horses one in front of the other, what are the correct terms for 2, 3, and 4 horse hitches?","answer":"2 is tandem; 3 is random; 4 is quadrem"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1982","question":"In reference to driving, what term is used to describe the middle team in a 6 horse hitch?","answer":"Swing team"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1983","question":"In reference to driving, where is the \"point team\" in an 8-horse hitch?","answer":"Team behind the leaders (FYI: Teams from front to back are leaders or lead team, point team, swing team, and wheelers or wheel team.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1984","question":"In reference to driving what term refers to the team of horses behind the lead team in an 8 horse hitch?","answer":"Point team"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1985","question":"In reference to driving, what kind of hitch has two pairs of horses with one pair hitched in front of the other?","answer":"Four-in-hand, four up, or four horse hitch (accept any)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"1986","question":"Correctly identify the 4 pairs of horses in an 8 horse hitch in order from front to back.","answer":"Leaders, point or body team, swing team, wheelers"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1987","question":"In reference to driving, describe a unicorn hitch.","answer":"Two horses hitched as a pair with a third horse hitched in front of them (pair of wheel horses with a single lead horse) (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1988","question":"In reference to driving, what term describes a hitch with two wheel horses and one lead horse?","answer":"Unicorn hitch"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1989","question":"You do the math…Your Arabian completed the 100 mile Tevis Cup endurance race in 22 hours which included the two mandatory 60 minute rest stops.  What was your average speed?","answer":"5 miles per hour (100 miles divided by 20 hours=5 miles per hour)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1990","question":"The Tevis Cup is an endurance ride that takes place in California each year.  What famous route does this ride follow?","answer":"Pony Express route"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1991","question":"What is the name of the endurance competition that is ridden over the old Pony Express route from Lake Tahoe to Auburn, California?","answer":"Tevis Cup"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1992","question":"What 3 phases make up a 3-day or combined training event?","answer":"Dressage, cross country jumping, stadium or show jumping"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1993","question":"What horsemanship competition was originally a trial for cavalry patrol mounts and was designated as an Olympic sport in 1912?","answer":"Combined training  or 3 day eventing (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1994","question":"In three day eventing, to which side of the jump would a rider correctly see a red flag?","answer":"Right side"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"1995","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the cry of the hunt once the fox has been sighted?","answer":"Tally ho (also accept halloa or view halloo)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1996","question":"Larking refers to unnecessarily jumping fences when participating in what equine activity?","answer":"Fox hunting"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1997","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is type of dress is worn during \"cubbing season\"?","answer":"Rat catcher shirt (FYI: Cubbing is the training period for young hounds, before the start of the formal fox hunting season, where the young hounds hunt fox cubs .)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1998","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the person called who hunts the hounds and is in charge of the kennels?","answer":"Huntsman"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"1999","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what do the initials MFH indicate when used after a person’s name?","answer":"Master of Fox Hounds"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2000","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what term is used when the hounds lose the scent of the fox and stop?","answer":"Check (also accept throw up)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2001","question":"In reference to fox hunting, why is the scarlet livery worn by foxhunting staff commonly called “pinks”?","answer":"Famous British tailor named Pinque supposedly made the first coats"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2002","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is a \"capping fee\"?","answer":"Fee paid by a visitor for a day of fox hunting"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2003","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is a den?","answer":"Home of a fox"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2004","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the term for the \"bay\" of a hound?","answer":"Cry"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2005","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the term for the mounted followers of a fox hunt?","answer":"Field"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2006","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what does the term \"gone to ground\" mean?","answer":"Fox has taken refuge in the ground, drain, den, or other shelter"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2007","question":"How many poles are used in pole bending?","answer":"6 (six) poles"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2008","question":"What is the term for games on horseback?","answer":"Gymkhana"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2009","question":"What is gymkhana?","answer":"Games on horseback"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2010","question":"Scurry, potato race, speed barrels, flags, and pole bending are all activities seen at what type of equine event?","answer":"Gymkhana, games, or play day (accept any)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2011","question":"How many barrels are there in a cloverleaf barrel pattern?","answer":"3 (three) barrels"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2012","question":"What equipment is being described? This is used in speed-based events. The horse determines the “time” for this device. It has a clock that is “automatically” triggered when the horse starts the event and stops when the horse goes through the finish.","answer":"Automatic timer or electronic timer (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2013","question":"Which association was established to promote safe, knowledgeable riding instruction?","answer":"American Riding Instructors Association"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2014","question":"Name an English riding activity that a saddle seat rider does NOT usually participate in.","answer":"Jumping"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2015","question":"2 part question:  In most equestrian events, which side of an obstacle is indicated by a red flag and which side of an obstacle is indicated by a white flag?","answer":"Red flag—right side; white flag—left side"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2016","question":"You are completing a cross country race and are approaching a brush fence with a white flag on the right side of the obstacle.  What does this indicate?","answer":"You are approaching the fence from wrong direction (FYI: White flag should be on left side of the obstacle; right flag should be on the right side of the obstacle.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2017","question":"A good seat for jumping is not developed by strength in gripping or hanging on the reins, but by what?","answer":"Balance"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2018","question":"For the jumping position, in what direction should the rider be looking?","answer":"Straight ahead (between the horse's ears)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2019","question":"What should a rider NEVER use for balance when learning to jump?","answer":"Reins"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2020","question":"What is another name for the jumping position?","answer":"Two-point position"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2021","question":"When learning to jump, in order to give security to the rider and freedom for the horse, what length should the stirrup leathers be?","answer":"Medium length (1 - 2 holes shorter than on the flat length)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2022","question":"What is the purpose of the two point position?","answer":"Adjust the rider's balance to match the horse during jumping and/or galloping"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2023","question":"In reference to jumping, what TWO criteria determine the winner of an \"against the clock\" competition?","answer":"Rider with fastest time and the fewest faults"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2024","question":"\"Against the clock\" is a term used in which equestrian discipline where the winner is determined by the fastest time and the fewest faults?","answer":"Show jumping or stadium jumping (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2025","question":"In reference to jumping, what term refers to the desirable arc a horse’s body makes as it goes over a jump?","answer":"Bascule"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2026","question":"In reference to jumping, what does the term \"bascule\" mean?","answer":"Desirable arc a horse’s body makes as it goes over a jump"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2027","question":"In reference to jumping, what does the term \"charging\" mean?","answer":"Rushing into a fence"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2028","question":"In reference to jumping, what is the term used when a horse rushes into a fence while jumping?","answer":"Charging"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2029","question":"In reference to jumping, what is meant when a competitor has a \"clear round\"?","answer":"Round is completed without jumping or time faults"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2030","question":"In reference to jumping, what is an \"element\"?","answer":"One jump in a combination"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2031","question":"What is the general term for a separation between rider and horse that necessitates remounting?","answer":"Fall"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2032","question":"In regards to the horse, what designates a \"fall\"?","answer":"When both the shoulder and hip on the same side touch the ground"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2033","question":"In reference to jumping, what term describes when the rail or top element of a jump is dislodged by the horse during a jump?","answer":"Knockdown (also accept rail down)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2034","question":"What is the term for a horse stopping in front of or passing a jump without jumping it?","answer":"Refusal"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2035","question":"Identify each of these 4 jumps:  jump made of shrubs and brush with a clearly visible bar; drop jump that is a solid earthen ramp or wall; spread obstacle consisting of a sunken trough of water; obstacle that is wide rather than high.","answer":"Brush jump, bank jump, water jump, spread jump"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2036","question":"In reference to jumping, what is the name for a drop jump that is a solid earthen ramp or wall?","answer":"Bank jump"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2037","question":"What are cavaletti?","answer":"Raised jumps made of poles on the ground or poles on the ground which are properly spaced (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2038","question":"What are 3 things that cavaletti work teaches a horse?","answer":"Rhythm, balance, agility, lengthen stride, improve balance, loosen up muscles, strengthen muscles"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2039","question":"In reference to jumping, what must the rider do when making a second attempt at a combination jump when do if a horse refuses the second element of a combination?","answer":"Take both jumps again"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2040","question":"In reference to jumping, what type of jump has two fences set within 24 feet of each other?","answer":"In and out or combination jump (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2041","question":"In show jumping, a combination obstacle consists of two or more separate jumps that are numbered and lettered such as 4A and 4B.  If you’re judging this class, would jumps 4A and 4B each receive a score or would they be judged as one obstacle?","answer":"Judged as one obstacle"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2042","question":"In reference to jumping, what is an obstacle called when the wall or fence is set down in a ditch so as not to obstruct the horse’s view?","answer":"Ha-ha"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2043","question":"What is a spread jump?","answer":"Jump with width to it (such as an oxer)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2044","question":"Name 3 functions of the American Horse Show Association.","answer":"Sanctions shows; keeps records; licenses judges and stewards; handles disciplinary measures; awards annual prizes; compiles annual rule book"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2045","question":"What is the umbrella organization for leaders or groups who work with youth and horses?","answer":"American Youth Horse Council"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2046","question":"What is the name for the manager of an equestrian team who's responsible for making all the arrangements, both on and off the field, for a national team who's competing abroad?","answer":"Chef d'Equipe (chef de keep)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2047","question":"What Spanish term for roping classes is more commonly known as a favorite type of soda?","answer":"Colas"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2048","question":"Freestyle patterns ridden to music are found in which TWO equestrian sports?","answer":"Dressage and reining"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2049","question":"The Russian equestrian sport of kabakhi is ridden at a full gallop and includes what other type of sport?","answer":"Archery"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2050","question":"In which type of competition do horses perform without personal contact from a rider or handler, as in circus acts?","answer":"Liberty classes"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2051","question":"What is the term for the Australian game on horseback that is based on polo and lacrosse?","answer":"Polocrosse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2052","question":"Dressage is one of how many official Olympic equestrian sports?","answer":"3 (three) (FYI:  dressage, show jumping, and 3-day eventing; reining is currently a demonstration sport only)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2053","question":"What organization is responsible for making the rules and regulations for the conduct of the equestrian sports in the Olympic Games?","answer":"FEI (Federation Equestre Internationale)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"int bonus","number":"2054","question":"Name the 3 official Olympic equine sports.","answer":"Dressage, stadium or show jumping, 3-day eventing, (FYI: reining is currently a demonstration sport only with no medals)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2055","question":"Why is it important to keep a pack saddle from sliding backwards?","answer":"So it doesn't rest on the horse's kidneys or lumbar region"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2056","question":"Name ONE way to restrain a pack horse.","answer":"Hobbles, picket line, highline"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2057","question":"Name TWO pieces of equipment that you can use to help stabilize a load on a pack horse.","answer":"Breeching, breast collar, crupper"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2058","question":"When your horse is carrying a pack load down a steep grade, what piece of rigging, other than the cinch, needs to be adjusted and pulled tighter?","answer":"Breeching"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2059","question":"What is the purpose of a pack saddle's breeching?","answer":"Prevents the saddle from sliding forward when going downhill"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2060","question":"Which piece of equipment is used to keep a pack saddle from sliding backwards?","answer":"Breast collar"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2061","question":"If you are using a stock saddle for packing, what piece of equipment—that goes around the base of the tail and attaches to the saddle—would you use to keep the pack load centered?","answer":"Crupper"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2062","question":"What is the purpose of a crupper on a pack saddle?","answer":"To keep the saddle from sliding forward or to keep the pack load centered (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2063","question":"When securing the entire balanced load to the pack animal, what is the most important factor?","answer":"Hitch"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2064","question":"What is another name for a basket or barrel hitch?","answer":"Sling hitch"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"int bonus","number":"2065","question":"Name 3 hitches used in packing.","answer":"Squaw hitch, half diamond, single diamond, double diamond, triple diamond, one-man diamond, box hitch, Arizona, square, sling, basket, barrel"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2066","question":"Single, double, half, Arizona, and diamond are terms referring to what?","answer":"Pack hitches"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2067","question":"In reference to packing, what is a lash rope used for?","answer":"To tie the load onto the pack saddle"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2068","question":"In securing your pack before hitting the trail, what are the last TWO items you need?","answer":"Lash cinch and lash rope"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2069","question":"What is a half-inch rope of soft, twisted nylon 45 - 50 feet in length that's used to secure the entire load on a pack saddle?","answer":"Lash rope"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2070","question":"What must be balanced and centered on your pack animal?","answer":"Load or pack"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2071","question":"In reference to packing, what is a manta or mantee?","answer":"Canvas cover used to cover the load when packing"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2072","question":"A piece of canvas which is used to cover your pack load is called what?","answer":"Manta or mantee"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2073","question":"In reference to packing, what does the term \"mantied\" mean?","answer":"Load is placed in a canvas cover"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2074","question":"What item of pack equipment could contain shelves or double as a small table?","answer":"Panniers"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2075","question":"In reference to packing, what is a pannier?","answer":"Container used for carrying supplies while packing"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2076","question":"What is the name for the piece of equipment that's used to carry supplies on a pack trip?","answer":"Panniers"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2077","question":"What is the purpose of a quarter strap in packing?","answer":"Reduce cinch sores"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2078","question":"Traditional pack saddles come in two styles.  Name them.","answer":"Crossbuck or sawbuck and Decker"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"int bonus","number":"2079","question":"Name 3 types of saddles that can be used in packing.","answer":"Decker, crossbuck or sawbuck, McClellan, Western or stock"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2080","question":"When comparing crossbuck and Decker saddles, which is better suited to a sling load that's mantied?","answer":"Decker"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2081","question":"What type of pack saddle has a centerfire single cinch and is used with a half breed?","answer":"Decker"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2082","question":"Which pack saddle has a single cinch?","answer":"Decker"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2083","question":"How many cinches are on a Decker pack saddle?","answer":"1 (one) cinch"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2084","question":"2 part question:  In reference to packing, describe a half-breed and explain how it's used.","answer":"Heavy canvas pad with wooden bars at the bottom used over a Decker saddle; provides extra padding and holds the pack away from the animal's sides"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2085","question":"In reference to packing, what is the purpose of the \"half-breed\"?","answer":"To provide extra padding or to hold packs away from the animal's sides (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2086","question":"Why is a traditional McClellan saddle a reasonably effective packsaddle?","answer":"Lightweight; has plenty of rings and straps to tie things"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2087","question":"What is the use of a sawbuck saddle?","answer":"Packing"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2088","question":"On a sawbuck or crossbuck saddle, where is sheepskin lining added for more protection and comfort?","answer":"Blades"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2089","question":"Extra-long crossbucks are used for what purpose?","answer":"To hold the pack away from the animal's sides"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2090","question":"What type of rigging does a crossbuck or sawbuck saddle have?","answer":"Double"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2091","question":"Which pack saddle has a double rigged cinch?","answer":"Crossbuck or sawbuck"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2092","question":"You do not have a crossbuck or Decker saddle available, but you want to go packing.  What other COMMONLY available saddle could you use with some modifications?","answer":"Western saddle"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2093","question":"Over what TWO parts of a stock saddle would panniers fit?","answer":"Cantle and swells"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2094","question":"2 part question:  In regards to withers, what type of conformation is undesirable in a pack horse and why?","answer":"Little or no withers—allows saddle to turn and rub or creates sores; withers that are too high—harder to fit and more prone to sores"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2095","question":"In choosing a packhorse, what kind of withers are best?","answer":"Medium high withers"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2096","question":"Why is a horse or mule with little or no withers undesirable as a pack animal?","answer":"Because the pack saddle won’t fit well (which may cause sores)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2097","question":"What is possibly the oldest team equine sport?","answer":"Polo"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2098","question":"Polo matches are divided into 7 ½ minute periods called what?","answer":"Chukkars (chukkas)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2099","question":"What is the name of the game played by teams on horseback using mallets to hit a wooden ball?","answer":"Polo"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2100","question":"What do the initials USPC stand for?","answer":"United States Pony Club"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2101","question":"Name 3 programs offered by the United States Pony Club.","answer":"Dressage; cross country; stadium or show jumping; mounted games; tetrathlon; know-down; vaulting; fox hunting; polocross"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2102","question":"2 part question:  Explain the difference between harness racing and flat racing and name TWO breeds that participate in each.","answer":"Harness races are driving races (with sulkies); breeds—Standardbred, Trottingbred Pony, Russian Trotter, Orlov; flat races are riding races (without jumps); breeds—Thoroughbred, Quarter Horse, Appaloosa, Paint, Arabian"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2103","question":"In Colonial New England, why was horse racing socially unacceptable?","answer":"Too closely associated with the landed gentry in England"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2104","question":"Administering drugs to a horse to improve or hinder his performance in a race or competition is known as doping.  Name 3 body fluids that may be tested to detect doping","answer":"Urine, saliva, blood"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2105","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term used for administering an illegal drug to a horse to increase or decrease its speed or performance?","answer":"Doping"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2106","question":"What is the term for the person who rides a horse in a race?","answer":"Jockey"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2107","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for when jockeys ride with one stirrup longer than the other to help keep their balance on sharp turns?","answer":"Acey-deucy"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2108","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is an \"apprentice\"?","answer":"Jockey in training"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2109","question":"In reference to horse racing, what does the term \"blow a stirrup\" mean?","answer":"Lose a stirrup iron"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2110","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term used for a jockey in training?","answer":"Apprentice or bug boy"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2111","question":"In reference to horse racing, who chooses the colors of the jacket and cap worn by a jockey in the Kentucky Derby?","answer":"Horse's owners"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2112","question":"In reference to horse racing, what are the cap and jacket of a jockey called?","answer":"Silks"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2113","question":"In reference to Quarter Horse racing, what is a speed index?","answer":"Method of rating racehorses that's determined by horse's speed and the distance covered"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2114","question":"In reference to horse racing, the All-American Futurity is a race for which breed of horse?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2115","question":"2 part question:  The first organized Thoroughbred races are traditionally credited to Governor Samuel Ogle.  When and where were the first races staged?","answer":"1749; Annapolis, Maryland"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2116","question":"What is the primary difference between the horses that are raced in the Kentucky Derby and the Kentucky Oaks?","answer":"Kentucky Oaks is a race for fillies only (FYI: Both races are for 3 year old Thoroughbreds.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2117","question":"In 1875 what horse was the first winner of the Kentucky Derby?","answer":"Aristides (ar-ee-STY-dees)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2118","question":"In 1973, Secretariat became the first horse in 25 years to do what?","answer":"Win the Triple Crown"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2119","question":"Secretariat won the Belmont Stakes in record time.  What was his time?","answer":"2 minutes and 24 seconds"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2120","question":"Collectively, the Kentucky Derby, Preakness Stakes, and Belmont Stakes are known as what?","answer":"Triple Crown"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2121","question":"At what age do Thoroughbred horses compete for the Triple Crown?","answer":"3 (three) years of age"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2122","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the third and final race in the Triple Crown?","answer":"Belmont (FYI: Belmont is 1 ½ miles.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2123","question":"Name the 3 Thoroughbred races included in the Triple Crown.","answer":"Kentucky Derby, Preakness, Belmont"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2124","question":"Who was the first undefeated Triple Crown winner?","answer":"Seattle Slew"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2125","question":"What is the second race in the Triple Crown for 3 year old Thoroughbreds?","answer":"Preakness"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2126","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the type of wagering where the person placing the bet must pick the first and second finishers in exact order?","answer":"Exacta"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2127","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for exercising a horse at a moderate speed?","answer":"Breeze"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2128","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for a short, fast training run of 3 - 4 furlongs?","answer":"Blowout"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2129","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the difference between a breeze and a blowout?","answer":"Breeze—easy workout at a moderate speed; blowout—short, fast run"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2130","question":"In reference to horse racing, what term refers to two or more horses arriving simultaneously at the finish line?","answer":"Dead heat (Do NOT accept \"photo finish\" where one horse finishes slightly in front of the others.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2131","question":"What term refers to a horse that breaks through the starting gate prematurely?","answer":"False start"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2132","question":"In reference to horse racing, how long is a furlong?","answer":"1/8 of a mile (220 yards or 102.17 meters)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2133","question":"You do the math…How many furlongs are in a 1½ mile race?","answer":"12 furlongs (FYI: 1 furlong equals 1/8th of a mile)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2134","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is done to try to equalize the performance of the horses in a handicapped race?","answer":"Weight is added (more weight is added to the better horses)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2135","question":"In reference to horse racing, what does the term \"maiden\" mean?","answer":"Horse that has never won a race (at a recognized track)."},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2136","question":"In reference to horse racing, what does the term \"also ran\" mean?","answer":"Any horse who ran, but didn't place in the race"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2137","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for finishing second in a race?","answer":"Place"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2138","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the name for one's starting position?","answer":"Post position"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2139","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the official name for the prize money in a horse race?","answer":"Purse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2140","question":"In reference to horse racing, give ONE definition of a \"ringer\".","answer":"Horse entered into a race under false identity; horse falsely entered that is sure to win the race; horse entered below his class where he is almost certain to win (accept any reasonable explanation)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2141","question":"In reference to horse racing, give TWO terms commonly used to describe the condition of the racetrack footing.","answer":"Fast, sloppy, muddy, heavy"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2142","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for a race horse that runs well on wet, sloppy tracks?","answer":"Mudder"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2143","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for the side of the track furthest from the winning post?","answer":"Backstretch"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"int bonus","number":"2144","question":"Name 3 different types of horse racing.","answer":"Flat, harness, steeplechase, chuckwagon, chariot, endurance (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2145","question":"What historic events took place at Circus Maximus?","answer":"Roman chariot races (also accept chariot races)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2146","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is a \"claiming race\"?","answer":"Race in which every horse including the winner may be claimed or purchased for a previously stated price"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2147","question":"What is a flat race?","answer":"Race without jumps"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2148","question":"What do you call a race without jumps?","answer":"Flat race"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2149","question":"In reference to harness racing, which horse typically races the SLOWEST, a trotter or a pacer?","answer":"Trotter"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2150","question":"In reference to harness racing, what is the name of a light, two-wheeled racing rig?","answer":"Sulky"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2151","question":"In reference to harness racing, what is a \"free-legged\" pacer?","answer":"Pacer who races without hobbles"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2152","question":"In reference to horse racing, where did the name \"steeplechase\" come from?","answer":"In the late 1700's, the races often went from one church to another"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2153","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the name given to a race over natural or artificial obstacles such as fences, hedges, and water jumps?","answer":"Steeplechase"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2154","question":"What do you call a man who herds and tends cattle?","answer":"Cowboy"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2155","question":"In reference to ranching, what is a \"maverick\"?","answer":"Unbranded stray"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2156","question":"Where are most working horses in the US found?","answer":"Cattle ranches"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2157","question":"In reference to livestock, what is a \"knacker\"?","answer":"Person who buys animal carcasses or buys and slaughters unwanted livestock (FYI:  Renderers use animal parts to make needed items like pet food, Neatsfoot oil, etc.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2158","question":"What is another name for an auction ring?","answer":"Sale ring or bull pen"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2159","question":"What is a vaquero?","answer":"Spanish term for cowboy"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2160","question":"What are you doing if you are fuzztail running?","answer":"Herding and catching wild horses"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2161","question":"What is the term for a cowboy from the western US who follows the horsemanship techniques of the old California vaqueros?","answer":"Buckaroo"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2162","question":"In reference to ranching, what is the term for a cowboy whose job is to rescue cattle that have gotten trapped in mud or marshland?","answer":"Bog rider"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2163","question":"In reference to ranching, what is the purpose of a boundary rider?","answer":"To ride the fences of the property and repair any problems"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2164","question":"In reference to reining, in order to achieve a sliding stop, when should you signal your horse for the stop?","answer":"When the horse's rear legs are moving forward under its body"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2165","question":"Reining is a judged event designed to show what?","answer":"Athletic ability of a ranch-type horse in the confines of the show arena (how willing a horse is guided through a series of maneuvers such as circles, spins, sliding stops, and rollbacks (accept any reasonable explanation)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"int bonus","number":"2166","question":"Name 3 things that are included in a reining pattern.","answer":"Circles, flying lead changes, rollbacks, 360 degree spins, sliding stops"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2167","question":"In reference to reining, which hind foot should remain in place when completing a spin to the right in a reining pattern?","answer":"Right hind foot"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2168","question":"What do you call reining maneuvers set to music?","answer":"Freestyle reining"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2169","question":"What is freestyle reining?","answer":"Reining maneuvers set to music"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2170","question":"In what year did the National Reining Horse Association hold its first team tournament championship?","answer":"1995"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2171","question":"What is the automatic beginning score for a reining pattern?","answer":"70"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2172","question":"You do the math…You are judging a reining class and have just finished scoring the last horse.  You have given this horse a total maneuver score of + 3 ½ (plus 3 ½) and total penalties of -5 (minus 5).  What would be the final score for this horse?","answer":"Final score 68 ½ (70+ 3 ½ -5=68 ½)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2173","question":"How is a reining pattern scored?","answer":"Starting score is 70; points are added or deducted for each maneuver"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2174","question":"In reference to rodeo, name ONE event that has a rope barrier.","answer":"Calf roping (tie down roping), team roping (head and heeling), steer wrestling (bulldogging)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2175","question":"What is the only current women's event in PRCA rodeo?","answer":"Barrel racing"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2176","question":"Name TWO kinds of rodeo bronc riding.","answer":"Saddle and bareback"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2177","question":"Name 3 rodeo \"rough stock\" events.","answer":"Bareback riding, saddle bronc riding, bull riding"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2178","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is another name for the activity described as “heading and heeling”?","answer":"Team roping"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2179","question":"Name ONE founding principle for High School Rodeo.","answer":"Encourage youth to stay in school; promote sportsmanship; encourage horsemanship; encourage character development through the sport of rodeo"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2180","question":"In reference to rodeo, what do the initials NHSRA stand for?","answer":"National High School Rodeo Association"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2181","question":"In reference to rodeo, what do the initials PRCA stand for?","answer":"Professional Rodeo Cowboys Association"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2182","question":"For what GENERAL type of equine activity would an Association saddle be used?","answer":"Rodeo"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2183","question":"What is a \"calf horse\"?","answer":"Horse specifically trained for use in roping"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2184","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the term for the box from which livestock are released into the arena in rodeo events?","answer":"Chute"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2185","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the slang term for the main office of a rodeo where excuses and grievances are aired?","answer":"Crying room"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2186","question":"What is the term for the wrap taken with a lariat around the horn of a Western saddle when roping?","answer":"Dally"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2187","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the name for the prize money paid to the winners of each go-round of a competition?","answer":"Day money"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2188","question":"In which equestrian sport would winning competitors receive \"day money\"?","answer":"Rodeo"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2189","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the name of the cowboy who rides on the side of the steer opposite the steer wrestler?","answer":"Hazer"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2190","question":"In reference to rodeo, what is the name for the person who helps the rider off the bronc when the ride is completed, pulls the flank strap off the bronc, and removes the bronc from the arena?","answer":"Pickup man"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2191","question":"In reference to calf roping, what is the name of the 6 foot length of rope used to tie the legs of the calf?","answer":"Pigging string"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2192","question":"Touching the saddle with a free hand is referred to by the slang term“pulling leather” and is a disqualification in what rodeo event?","answer":"Saddle bronc riding"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2193","question":"What is a re-ride in rodeo?","answer":"Bronc or bull rider is given a second ride in the same go-round"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2194","question":"Please fill in the blanks.  Be a good sport.  Win without_______ and lose without ________.","answer":"Win without bragging and lose without complaining."},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2195","question":"What builds character faster than purple ribbons?","answer":"Good sportsmanship"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"2196","question":"What are TWO things you should remember when winners are announced?","answer":"Win graciously; lose graciously; don't run over the judge, ring steward, or ribbon person; listen to the judge's reasons for placing the class because it may help in the future"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2197","question":"What organization compiles the rulebook for the horse show world?","answer":"American Horse Show Association "},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2198","question":"In reference to horse showing, what does AHSA stand for?","answer":"American Horse Show Association"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2199","question":"When is a show stick acceptable for showmanship classes?","answer":"When you're showing a draft horse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2200","question":"When do you NOT switch sides in showmanship?","answer":"When showing a draft horse (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2201","question":"Explain how a draft horse is decorated for show.","answer":"Mares and geldings both have tails tied; mares may have manes rolled; geldings have manes rolled and decorated."},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2202","question":"Which type of class is judged on the rider?","answer":"Equitation or horsemanship (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2203","question":"When riding in group classes like equitation, name ONE thing you can do to avoid bunching up.","answer":"Pass, cut corner, circle to get to clear area (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2204","question":"How should you change directions on the rail in a horse show?","answer":"Turn to the inside or away from the rail"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2205","question":"In a Conformation Hunter Class, what percent of the class is judged on performance?","answer":"60%"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2206","question":"Name TWO pieces of prohibited equipment for Hunt Seat Equitation.","answer":"Martingales, tie-downs, certain types of nosebands"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2207","question":"What part of the rider's legs should be used as aids in Hunt Seat Equitation?","answer":"Calf or lower legs (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2208","question":"A typical Hunter Hack class requires the horses to jump two fences and show on the rail at what 4 gaits?","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, and hand gallop"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2209","question":"Name 3 things Working Hunter horses are judges on.","answer":"Even hunting pace, manners, and jumping style together with faults earned on the course. (FYI: Open jumping, show jumping, or stadium jumping is judge only on the number of faults.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2210","question":"Name 3 pieces of optional personal appointments in Hunt Seat Equitation.","answer":"Unroweled spurs, crops or bats, gloves"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2211","question":"How far ahead of the class starting time should the judge post any required pattern?","answer":"At least one hour"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2212","question":"In a pattern riding class, what is the penalty for NOT following the pattern?","answer":"Disqualification"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2213","question":"Name ONE horse show class in which patterns are generally used.","answer":"Showmanship, Western Equitation, Western Riding, Reining, English Equitation, Horsemanship, Dressage, Trail (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2214","question":"What is the difference between performance and equitation classes?","answer":"Performance classes are judged or timed on the horse; equitation classes are judged on the rider"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2215","question":"What do the following horse show classes have in common:  pole bending, dressage, and harness ponies?","answer":"They are all performance classes."},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2216","question":"Where is the emphasis placed in a pleasure or performance class?","answer":"On the horse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2217","question":"In Saddle Seat riding, on which side of the horse would the rider hold his crop or whip?","answer":"Inside hand (side facing the middle of the arena) (FYI: Saddle seat riders change the whip hand when changing directions.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2218","question":"In Saddle Seat riding, where should the bight of the rein be when riding in Saddle Seat Equitation?","answer":"Off side"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2219","question":"What type of turn is generally preferred in showmanship?","answer":"Pivot turn"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2220","question":"Explain how to back your horse in showmanship.","answer":"Turn to face towards the rear of the horse with your right hand extended; walk forward beside the horse as it backs up (do not touch your horse with your hand)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2221","question":"When turning the horse in showmanship, which direction do you generally turn?","answer":"To the right or away from you"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2222","question":"What personal equipment is PROHIBITIED in showmanship classes?","answer":"Spurs"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2223","question":"Besides keeping your horse posed so that judge gets the best view, name ONE other thing you should do at all times during a showmanship class.","answer":"Be aware of where the judge is, know what's expected of you, know the pattern (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"novice","number":"2224","question":"In a show, what side should you be on when leading your horse?","answer":"Left side"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2225","question":"Where are the dividing lines that define the quarter system of showmanship?","answer":"Down the backbone of the horse and across the shoulders or withers"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2226","question":"What is the purpose of a Showmanship pattern?","answer":"To test the exhibitor's ability to present a horse to the judge (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"2227","question":"Name 3 common elements in Showmanship patterns.","answer":"Walk, trot, pivot turn, back, set up for inspection"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2228","question":"If the handler is wearing Hunt Seat attire in Showmanship, what tack should be on the horse?","answer":"English bridle (also accept plain leather halter)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2229","question":"When showing a horse in hand with a Pelham or double bridle, with which rein do you lead the horse?","answer":"Lead with the curb rein (FYI:  The snaffle rein should be placed over the horse’s neck.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"jr bonus","number":"2230","question":"Name the 3 gaits performed in Stock Seat Equitation.","answer":"Walk, jog, lope"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2231","question":"Name 3 pieces of optional person appointments in Stock Seat Equitation.","answer":"Spurs, chaps, sweaters, vests, coats"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2232","question":"What is the term for the rider's personal attire and any equipment needed for showing?","answer":"Appointments"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2233","question":"In references to horses, what are appointments?","answer":"Equipment and clothing used in showing"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2234","question":"What is the general name for a halter class in which coat color and pattern, NOT conformation, is a deciding factor?","answer":"Color class"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2235","question":"A rider who stays far away from the arena corners and does not make good use of the full arena is said to be doing what?","answer":"Cutting corners"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2236","question":"For an entry in a \"Get of Sire\" class, how many horses are shown together?","answer":"3 (three) horses"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2237","question":"What does the term \"show in hand\" mean?","answer":"Show at halter, show in showmanship, or show leading your horse instead of riding or driving (accept any)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2238","question":"What do you call the official who ranks the horses at horse shows?","answer":"Judge"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2239","question":"What is a \"junior\" horse?","answer":"One that's 5 years of age or younger"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2240","question":"Generally, in horse shows, when is a snaffle bit or bosal allowed?","answer":"When showing a young horse (junior horse 5 years of age or younger)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2241","question":"In which horse show class are young riders mounted and led by an adult handler?","answer":"Lead line"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"intermediate","number":"2242","question":"What is the term for having a pleasing, graceful, alert general appearance?","answer":"Stylish"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2243","question":"In general, what type of horse is the best candidate for a therapeutic riding horse?","answer":"Extremely gentle or tolerant horse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2244","question":"In reference to equine therapy what type of therapy uses horsemanship skills to achieve goals such as improved speech or motor skills?","answer":"Therapeutic or rehabilitative (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2245","question":"In reference to equine therapy, what does PATH stand for?","answer":"Professional Association of Therapeutic Horsemanship (PATH International)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"hard","number":"2246","question":"In reference to equine therapy, describe how hippotherapy provides benefits for a paralyzed rider.","answer":"Movement of the horse imparts movement of the rider's pelvis that closely resembles walking (FYI: There are 4 types of equine therapy:  Equine Facilitated Psychotherapy (EFP), Equine Facilitated Learning (EFL), Hippotherapy, and Therapeutic Riding.)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2247","question":"In reference to equine therapy, Special Olympics riding is a therapeutic riding program designed to develop what?","answer":"Rider's social skills"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2248","question":"Name 3 things a therapy horse must learn to tolerate.","answer":"Wheelchairs, loading ramps, crutches, sudden noises, rider's lack of balance, inadvertent pressure by rider (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2249","question":"Therapeutic riding includes 4 methods or activities.  What are they?","answer":"Hippotherapy, rehabilitative, sports (Special Olympics), vaulting"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2250","question":"Name ONE type of trail ride.","answer":"Social or pleasure, competitive, endurance"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2251","question":"On long trail rides, how often should you dismount and lead your horse?","answer":"5 minutes each hour"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2252","question":"What term describes when the horse is required to stand still when the lead rope or reins are dropped on the ground?","answer":"Ground tie"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2253","question":"What is the common term for riding a horse across country, in fields, on roads, in parks, and on logging trails?","answer":"Trail riding"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2254","question":"What is the name of the person who looks after the horses on a trail ride?","answer":"Wrangler"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2255","question":"Name 3 types of trail rides.","answer":"Social or pleasure, competitive, endurance"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2256","question":"How many vaulters may be on the horse at one time?","answer":"One, two, or three (accept any)"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"easy","number":"2257","question":"What discipline is defined as gymnastics on horseback?","answer":"Vaulting"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2258","question":"Name ONE thing vaulting is judged on.","answer":"On how well the horse and vaulter(s) work together; technique; performance; form; difficulty; balance; security; consideration of the horse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2259","question":"2 part question:  Vaulting is judged on teamwork and how well the human and equestrian athletes work together.  Similar to Olympic ice skating competitions, the individual or teams will be scored on two different types of performance.  Name them.","answer":"Compulsory moves and freestyle routines"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2260","question":"Modern vaulting was developed in Germany in the 1940's as a way to do what?","answer":"Offer children an inexpensive way to participate in equestrian sports"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2261","question":"In reference to vaulting, what is a longueur? (long-ER)","answer":"Person who controls the vaulting horse"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"medium","number":"2262","question":"2 part question:  For an ideal team in vaulting there are bigger, stronger vaulters and some smaller vaulters.  What are the common terms for both of these types of vaulters?","answer":"Bases and flyers"},
{"category":"Equine Activities","level":"sr bonus","number":"2263","question":"Explain the different ways vaulting was practiced during the early Roman times, Middle Ages, and Renaissance.","answer":"Early Romans—acrobatic displays on cantering horses;  Middle Ages—knights practiced jumping onto horses; Renaissance—agility training for young nobles"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2264","question":"The legs, hands, weight, and voice as used in controlling a horse are called what?","answer":"Aids (more specifically natural aids)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2265","question":"What are the natural aids used for while riding your horse?","answer":"To control your horse (to tell your horse what you want him to do)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2266","question":"Explain what is meant when a rider uses \"diagonal aids\".","answer":"Rider uses opposite hand and leg"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"int bonus","number":"2267","question":"What are the 3 general steps to obtain a desired lead?","answer":"Leg pressure, weight shift, rein (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"jr bonus","number":"2268","question":"Name 3 natural aids that are used to tell your horse what to do.","answer":"Voice, legs, hands, weight"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2269","question":"Name TWO natural aids that are used to tell your horse what to do.","answer":"Voice, hands, legs, weight"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2270","question":"Constant, steady pulling on the reins can cause what problem?","answer":"Hard mouth or damage to the horse's mouth (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2271","question":"Why are light hands so important in riding?","answer":"Heavy hands can hurt the horse's mouth"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2272","question":"Heavy hands can cause damage to what part of the horse?","answer":"Mouth (specifically the bars or interdental space)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2273","question":"What part of the horse's body do your hands control?","answer":"Forequarters"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2274","question":"Which of the natural aids is used lightly to guide the horse's forehand?","answer":"Hands"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2275","question":"When riding, what should be the MAIN means of communication with the horse?","answer":"Legs"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2276","question":"When riding, your legs are used to signal what?","answer":"Speed or direction of movement (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2277","question":"If the English rider is balanced correctly over her feet, where does the stirrup leather hang?","answer":"Straight down"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2278","question":"Ride with your weight on what part of your foot?","answer":"Ball of the foot (DON'T stick your feet too far into the stirrups or your feet could get \"hung up\")"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2279","question":"A horseman will shift his seat to place his body in balance with what?","answer":"Action of the horse"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2280","question":"What causes a chair seat?","answer":"Sitting behind the motion of the horse"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2281","question":"While sitting properly on a horse, a perpendicular line may be drawn from the rider's shoulder, hip, and heel.  Another perpendicular line may be drawn between what other TWO parts of the body?","answer":"Knee and toe"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2282","question":"When a rider maintains a balanced seat, he is directly over what area of the horse?","answer":"Center of motion (15th vertebrae)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2283","question":"Give ONE reason why it's important for a rider to stay deep in the saddle and to sit up straight.","answer":"So you don’t confuse the horse, throw the horse off balance, or fall off if the horse makes an unexpected move"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2284","question":"What is meant by the phrase “above the bit”?","answer":"Horse is carrying its head to high and is evading the bit making it difficult to control."},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2285","question":"What is meant by the phrase \"behind the bit\"?","answer":"Horse evades the bit by over-flexing at the poll"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2286","question":"A horse that moves forward with his head tucked into his chest is said to be what?","answer":"Behind the bit"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2287","question":"What is meant by the phrase \"on the bit\"?","answer":"When the horse has accepted contact with the bit (reacts to aids with quiet responsive manner)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2288","question":"What is the term for one who rides horseback?","answer":"Equestrian"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2289","question":"What is meant by the phrase \"sit tall in the saddle\"?","answer":"Sit up straight"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2290","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen if you get out of balance while riding.","answer":"You can throw your horse off balance, you can fall off, and you can stiffen and lose the rhythm of motion with the horse (accept any)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"int bonus","number":"2291","question":"What are the 3 basic equitation or horsemanship styles?","answer":"Stock seat or Western, Hunt Seat, Saddle Seat"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"sr bonus","number":"2292","question":"Name 3 important general aspects of equitation.","answer":"Body position, hand position, leg position, seat, performing correctly at different gaits, performing pattern correctly"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2293","question":"2 part question:  The term \"perched\" refers to what type of English saddle and rider?","answer":"Close contact saddle; jumping rider"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2294","question":"Which English rider sits in the saddle with a very sharp hip angle?","answer":"Jumping rider"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"int bonus","number":"2295","question":"Name 3 styles of English riding.","answer":"Hunt Seat, Saddle Seat, and Dressage"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2296","question":"What is the rising and descending of the rider in rhythm with the trot called?","answer":"Posting"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2297","question":"In reference to horseback riding, what is posting?","answer":"Rising and descending of the rider in rhythm with the trot"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"hard","number":"2298","question":"If the horse is traveling counter clockwise in the arena, what legs are moving forward when the rider rises for a correct diagonal?","answer":"Right front and left hind"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2299","question":"What are you doing when you settle in the saddle and take up on the reins?","answer":"Gathering your horse"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2300","question":"Explain how you would gather your horse.","answer":"Take up on the reins and settle in the saddle"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2301","question":"When riding a trot Western style, the body should be inclined slightly more in which direction than at the walk?","answer":"Forward"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2302","question":"What term means to step a horse backwards?","answer":"Back"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2303","question":"How do you ask your horse to back?","answer":"Grip with your legs, hold the reins low, pull lightly, use your voice, accept any reasonable explanation"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2304","question":"A “rein-back” is a movement signaled by the rider to the horse.  What does the horse do when this signal is given?","answer":"Back up"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2305","question":"In performing a correct rein back, how should the legs of the horse move?","answer":"In diagonal pairs (FYI:  The rein back is a two beat maneuver where a horse backs with his legs in diagonal pairs.)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2306","question":"A pivot is a turn on the hindquarters. When performed correctly, which hind foot should remain more or less in place when completing a pivot clockwise?","answer":"Right hind foot"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2307","question":"What motion is being described?  When a galloping horse stops, lifts his forelegs, swings around 180 degrees, and starts galloping again in the same direction from which he came?","answer":"Rollback"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2308","question":"What is a rollback?","answer":"When a galloping horse stops, lifts his forelegs, swings around 180 degrees and starts galloping again the in the direction from which he came (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2309","question":"Explain how you would get your horse to sidepass.","answer":"Hold the horse to prevent forward movement, rein in the direction you wish to move the forequarters, use outside leg to move the hindquarters (accept any reasonable explanation)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2310","question":"What do you call a turn on the front legs?","answer":"Turn on the forehand"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2311","question":"What is meant by the appropriate size horse and rider?","answer":"Not a small rider on large horse or vice versa"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"sr bonus","number":"2312","question":"Give 3 possible solutions for a small rider to mount a tall horse when using English tack.","answer":"Use a mounting block, have a friend give you a leg up, drop the left stirrup for mounting and re-adjust it after you're mounted"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2313","question":"When mounting your horse, which foot goes into the stirrup first?","answer":"Left foot"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2314","question":"On what side of the horse do you usually mount or get on?","answer":"Left side"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2315","question":"When you get ready to mount safely, what do you do to control your horse?","answer":"Adjust reins and hold the horse steady (adjust the reins evenly with enough tension to feel the bit)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2316","question":"When mounting for Western Equitation, on what part of the saddle do you place the right hand?","answer":"Saddle horn"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2317","question":"What is the rein called that's PUSHED against the neck in the direction of the turn?","answer":"Bearing rein or neck rein (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2318","question":"True neck reining is the response of your horse to what?","answer":"Pressure of the bearing rein against the neck"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2319","question":"In reference to horseback riding, what is the bearing rein?","answer":"Rein pushed against the neck in the direction of the turn when neck reining"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"intermediate","number":"2320","question":"What do you call the part of the reins that passes between the thumb and fingers and out the top of the hand?","answer":"Bight"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2321","question":"What do you call a method of holding single reins where the reins overlap in the rider's hands across the horse's back?","answer":"Cross reins"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2322","question":"When teaching a horse to neck rein, what is the rein called that PULLS in the direction of the turn?","answer":"Leading rein or direct rein (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2323","question":"What is \"plow reining\"?","answer":"Direct reining"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2324","question":"After you have mounted, on which side of the horse should the romal be found?","answer":"Opposite side from the reining hand"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2325","question":"If you are using split reins, how many fingers can be between the reins in a Western Pleasure class?","answer":"1 (one) finger"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2326","question":"On which side of the horse should the ends of split reins fall when using one finger between the reins?","answer":"Same side as the reining hand"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"medium","number":"2327","question":"When a rider is riding side saddle they have both legs on the near side of the horse.  What term refers to riding with one leg on each side of the horse?","answer":"Astride"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2328","question":"In which riding style is the rider seated sideways?","answer":"Sidesaddle"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"sr bonus","number":"2329","question":"Give 3 reasons for riding sidesaddle.","answer":"Handicapped riders; those who for some reason can't ride astride; costume; parade; fox hunting; pleasure"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2330","question":"What is another name for the LEFT side of the horse?","answer":"Near side"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2331","question":"What is the “near side” of the horse?","answer":"Left side"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2332","question":"What is another name for the RIGHT side of the horse?","answer":"Off side or far side (accept either)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"novice","number":"2333","question":"What is the “off side” of the horse?","answer":"Right side (also accept far side)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2334","question":"In reference to horseback riding, what is a \"passenger\"?","answer":"One who rides without control letting the horse go where it wants"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2335","question":"One who rides a horse without control, letting the horse go as he wishes, is called what?","answer":"Passenger"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2336","question":"What slang term is used when you hold on to the saddle with both hands while riding a bucking horse?","answer":"\"Pulling leather\""},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2337","question":"What does it mean to \"pull leather\"?","answer":"Hold on to saddle with both hands when riding a bucking horse"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2338","question":"What is a \"rubberneck\"?","answer":"Horse with a very flexible neck (that may be hard to rein)"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2339","question":"What is the term for a horse with a very flexible neck that may be hard to rein?","answer":"Rubberneck"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2340","question":"What do you call a horse that holds his head too high and his nose out?","answer":"Stargazer"},
{"category":"Equitation and Riding","level":"easy","number":"2341","question":"What is a \"stargazer\"?","answer":"Horse that holds his head high and his nose out"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2342","question":"Name TWO by-product feeds that can be added to a horse's ration as additional sources of fiber.","answer":"Beet pulp, wheat bran, brewer's dried grains, rice bran"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2343","question":"Give 4 examples of by-product feeds.","answer":"Rice bran, wheat bran, brewer's grains, corn gluten, beet pulp, corn distiller's dried grains"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2344","question":"Traditionally, what is done to beet pulp pellets before feeding?","answer":"They're soaked in water."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2345","question":"Give ONE reason why horses are fed beet pulp.","answer":"Respiratory problems; heaves; thin horses; chronic colic; dental problems; exercise-related muscle problems (Tying Up); Equine Metabolic Syndrome (insulin resistance) (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2346","question":"What feed has more digestible energy than hay and more bulk than grain?","answer":"Beet pulp"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2347","question":"How much beet pulp can be fed per day to horses?","answer":"Up to 10 pounds per day"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2348","question":"Give ONE reason why wheat bran should NOT be fed in large quantities or for prolonged periods of time even though it’s a good source of fiber.","answer":"Because it's too high in phosphorus (and can cause calcium and phosphorus imbalances); may form a dough ball in the horse’s stomach"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2349","question":"When feeding wheat bran as a supplement, how much can be fed per day?","answer":"1 (one) pound of wheat bran per day"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2350","question":"What is typically used as a fat supplement, but is also a fair source of fiber?","answer":"Rice bran"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2351","question":"Molasses is added to feed to reduce dust and improve palatability.  Name the TWO plants that are the primary source of molasses fed to horses in the United States.","answer":"Sugar cane and sugar beets"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2352","question":"What feed additive is commonly used to reduce dust and to increase palatability of a feed?","answer":"Molasses"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2353","question":"Commercially mixed feeds may contain what percent molasses?","answer":"15%"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2354","question":"Give TWO reasons for using molasses in feeds.","answer":"Settles dust; increases palatability"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2355","question":"If fed without any other source of roughage, complete feeds may increase the risk of what?","answer":"Colic, laminitis, wood chewing (accept any)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2356","question":"Basically, what does a feed tag do?","answer":"Tells you what's inside the bag"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"int bonus","number":"2357","question":"Name 3 things listed on a feed tag.","answer":"Ingredients, manufacturer name and address, minimum crude protein, crude fat, maximum crude fiber, weight, brand, product name, use directions, caution statements, guaranteed analysis"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2358","question":"Name ONE thing that must be in a prominent location on the tag of a medicated feed.","answer":"Caution statement, active drug ingredient(s), detailed use description, feed ingredients"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2359","question":"What is required for all commercial feed products and is used as a method of communication between feed manufacturer and customer?","answer":"Labeling"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2360","question":"Name 3 things included on medicated feed tags besides general information.","answer":"Caution statement, active drug ingredient(s), detailed use description"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2361","question":"In reference to nutrition, what do the letters CF stand for?","answer":"Crude fiber"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2362","question":"Would a feed with a 2% or 5% crude fiber have a higher digestible energy?","answer":"Feed with 2% crude fiber (FYI: The lower the crude fiber, the higher the digestible energy)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2363","question":"When reading a feed tag, the percent of crude fiber is the best indicator of what?","answer":"Energy content (FYI: The higher the crude fiber, the lower the digestible energy.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2364","question":"In feed analysis, what do the initials DE stand for?","answer":"Digestible Energy"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2365","question":"When looking at the feed tag for the concentrate you are currently feeding you notice the abbreviation GRAS.  What does GRAS indicate?","answer":"Generally Recognized as Safe (for animal consumption)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2366","question":"Ideally, how much time should foals spend on pasture?","answer":"24/7 (all the time or as recommended by your vet)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2367","question":"What is creep feeding?","answer":"Providing an area where the foal can eat without interference from the mare"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2368","question":"Orphan foals have a very high dietary energy requirement and should be fed how often during the first 1 – 2 weeks of life?","answer":"Every 2 to 4 hours (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2369","question":"How old should foals be when introduced to concentrates?","answer":"1 - 2 months (or as early as the foal shows interest)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2370","question":"When do foals usually show an interest in eating grain?","answer":"As early as two weeks of age"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2371","question":"What type of feed should be the start of any horse feeding program?","answer":"Forages (also accept hay or pasture)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2372","question":"Name ONE forage that is a good source of Vitamin E.","answer":"Alfalfa, orchard grass, fescue, Timothy"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2373","question":"What type of forage would be most appropriate for a horse with renal failure?","answer":"Grass forage (because it's lower in protein, calcium, and phosphorus)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2374","question":"Which type of hay has a higher nitrogen content, alfalfa or grass?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2375","question":"Give ONE reason why grass clippings and/or garden refuse are NOT recommended for feeding horses.","answer":"Garden refuse may contain plants that are lethal to horses; lawn clippings ferment easily in warm weather or may contain endophytes which might be toxic"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2376","question":"Grasses and legumes have differing nutrient contents.  Name TWO things that each type is generally higher in.","answer":"Grasses—higher in fiber and dry matter; legumes—higher in protein, energy, minerals (calcium and phosphorus), and vitamins"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2377","question":"Dehydrated roughages are usually rich in what 3 things?","answer":"Vitamin A, B vitamins, proteins"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2378","question":"Give 3 examples of roughages.","answer":"Pasture, hay, silage, by-product feeds, straw"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2379","question":"Fiber is necessary in horse diets to ensure the normal functioning of what body system?","answer":"Digestive system"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2380","question":"Feed stuffs that are high in fiber are referred to as what?","answer":"Forages"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2381","question":"The amount of seed heads on grasses or the amount of flowers on legumes present at the time of harvest tells you what about the hay?","answer":"Stage of maturity"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2382","question":"What is the most important factor affecting the nutrient content of grasses and legumes?","answer":"Stage of maturity at harvest"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2383","question":"Are mineral and vitamin contents higher, lower, or equal in immature grasses and legumes than in mature plants?","answer":"Higher in immature plants"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2384","question":"How is plant maturity of GRASS hay visually determined?","answer":"Amount of seed heads of grasses present at time of harvest"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2385","question":"Which type of forage should be harvested at the “boot” stage?","answer":"Grasses (FYI:  Boot stage is when the grass seed heads are just beginning to form.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2386","question":"How is the plant maturity of LEGUME hay visually determined?","answer":"By the amount of flowers present at time of harvest"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2387","question":"Which type of forage should be harvested at the pre-bloom stage?","answer":"Legumes (FYI:  Pre-bloom stage is determined by the amount of flowers present.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2388","question":"As forages mature and the percentage of lignin and structural carbohydrates increases, what happens to the digestibility of the forage?","answer":"Digestibility decreases as forage matures and lignin content increases."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2389","question":"Do horses prefer pastures of mixed grass types or a single type?","answer":"Mixed types"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2390","question":"Give 3 advantages of a grass-legume pasture.","answer":"Increased productivity (mature at different times), increased nutritional value of forage, pure alfalfa pasture often too rich/has too much protein, horses prefer mixed types of grass"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2391","question":"In order to decrease the risk of laminitis, colic, diarrhea, and stable vices, forage should be what percent of the horse's diet?","answer":"50 - 70% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2392","question":"Why is leafiness in hay an important guide to feeding value?","answer":"Most of the nutrients are found in the leaves"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2393","question":"What is meant by the term \"forage quality\"?","answer":"Nutritional quality of forages (characteristics affecting the consumption and nutrition quality)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2394","question":"Name TWO methods of appraising forage quality.","answer":"Visual appraisal, chemical analysis"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2395","question":"What is the term for forage that's been fermented and stored in anaerobic conditions?","answer":"Silage or haylage (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2396","question":"Good quality silage is a suitable replacement for how much hay or pasture?","answer":"1/3 - 1/2 or 33% - 50% (accept any number within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2397","question":"Fresh green pasture is what percent water?","answer":"75%"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2398","question":"What is \"sweet feed\"?","answer":"Grain mix that's sweetened with molasses (accept any reasonable explanation)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2399","question":"To maintain freshness, what is the maximum time that commercially prepared feed should be stored in a stable?","answer":"1 (one) month"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2400","question":"What is the most important factor to consider when storing grain?","answer":"Protect grain from moisture (or safe storage)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2401","question":"Corn, oats, barley, and milo contain what percent TDN?","answer":"70 - 80% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2402","question":"Energy-rich grains have what percent digestible protein?","answer":"7 - 10% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2403","question":"Name 3 of the most energy-rich grains.","answer":"Oats, corn, barley, milo/sorghum"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2404","question":"Which of the following cereal grains fed to horses is HIGHEST in crude fiber:  barley, oats, corn, or wheat?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2405","question":"What advantage do cereal grains have over forage?","answer":"They are a concentrated source of energy and nutrients."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2406","question":"Timeline...Put the following feedstuffs in order from most energy dense to least:  wheat, oats, and corn.","answer":"Wheat, corn, oats (FYI: DE in hard red wheat is 1.56 Mcal/lb., soft red wheat is 1.55 Mcal/lb., corn is 1.54 Mcal/lb., and oats is 1.30 Mcal/lb.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2407","question":"Grain or concentrates should be what percent or less of a horse's total diet?","answer":"40% or less"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2408","question":"Name 4 of the most energy-rich grains.","answer":"Oats, corn, barley, milo/sorghum"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2409","question":"Which of the following cereal grains fed to horses is LOWEST in crude protein:   barley, oats, corn, or wheat?","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2410","question":"2 part question:  When feeding barley to horses, in what form should it be fed and why?","answer":"Crimped or rolled; because it has a hard hull"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2411","question":"Why is corn considered a \"hot feed\"?","answer":"Corn has a high energy content (lots of carbohydrates)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"novice","number":"2412","question":"What grain can be fed rolled, shelled, cracked, whole kernel, or on the cob?","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2413","question":"What grain is being described?  It's the second most palatable grain for horses.  It's low in fiber and is high in digestible energy through its starch content.","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2414","question":"Name 3 ways corn can be fed to horses.","answer":"Cracked, shelled, ground, rolled, crimped, whole kernel, whole ear or on the cob"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2415","question":"Which grain is more economical per unit of energy, oats or corn?","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2416","question":"Groats are grain kernels that have had what removed?","answer":"Hulls"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2417","question":"What is an oat groat?","answer":"Oat with the hull removed"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2418","question":"What is the name for the outer covering of grains?","answer":"Hull"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2419","question":"What concentrate has the alternate name of sorghum?","answer":"Milo"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"novice","number":"2420","question":"What is the most popular grain fed to horses?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2421","question":"Which concentrate is the MOST expensive in terms of cost per unit of nutrients?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2422","question":"Name 3 advantages of feeding oats to your horse.","answer":"Difficult to overfeed, less likely to cause founder, most palatable of grains, soft kernel so processing not necessary, stores better, less likely to have mold or mycotoxins, not considered a hot feed"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2423","question":"Rye grain is high in protein, but is typically not fed to horses for what reason?","answer":"Poor palatability"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2424","question":"Give ONE reason why wheat isn't generally fed to horses.","answer":"High cost; small, hard kernels must be processed to be digested; low palatability"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2425","question":"2 part question:  Grass hays can be divided into TWO types.  What are the types and give TWO examples of each?","answer":"Warm season–Bahia grass, Bermuda grass, Teff, prairie grass, pearl millet, browntop millet; cool season–orchard grass, Timothy, tall fescue, smooth brome, reed canary grass, perennial ryegrass"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2426","question":"Name 3 grasses commonly used in PASTURES.","answer":"Orchard grass, Timothy, perennial ryegrass, annual ryegrass, tall fescue, reed canary, Kentucky bluegrass, smooth brome, Bahia, Bermuda, crabgrass, pearl millet, browntop millet"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2427","question":"Name 3 types of grass hay.","answer":"Orchard grass, Timothy, smooth brome, Bermuda, prairie, Teff, reed canary, Bahia, tall fescue, perennial ryegrass"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2428","question":"Which common pasture grass is present in all states, is winter hardy, rapid-growing, and palatable and tolerates close grazing?","answer":"Kentucky bluegrass"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2429","question":"What is the major cool season grass that's grown from Florida to Canada?","answer":"Tall fescue (fescue)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2430","question":"Timothy is useful when planted in pastures for rotational grazing.  How long should Timothy pastures rest before re-grazing?","answer":"3 weeks"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2431","question":"2 part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using Timothy in pastures.","answer":"Advantages—very palatable, winter hardy, late maturing (good quality forage for a longer time); disadvantages—uneven yield, slow re-growth, poor heat or drought tolerance, can develop cereal rust mites in some areas"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2432","question":"2 part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using orchard grass in pastures.","answer":"Advantages—leafy, rapid re-growth, good early and late season growth; disadvantages—marginal winter hardiness, very bunchy in growth habits, doesn’t tolerate close grazing (FYI:  Orchard grass is used mostly for hay.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2433","question":"Which cool season grass is grown mainly for hay instead of pasture?","answer":"Timothy"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2434","question":"Which cool season grass is adaptable to a wide range of soils, tolerant of continuous grazing, has excellent fall productivity, and is winter hardy?","answer":"Tall fescue (fescue)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2435","question":"How soon after planting pearl millet in warm soil should it be ready for grazing?","answer":"30 - 40 days (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2436","question":"Why is Teff safe to feed to horses with metabolic or digestive disorders?","answer":"Low in carbohydrates or sugars (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2437","question":"What height should pearl millet or browntop millet be for letting horses begin to graze it?","answer":"20 - 24 inches (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2438","question":"Name ONE warm season grass whose production is similar to that of sorghum and sorghum hybrids, but does not have the cystitis or prussic acid problems.","answer":"Pearl millet or browntop millet"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2439","question":"2 part question: Name a warm season grass that's generally safe to feed as hay, but that's NOT recommended for use in pastures.  Explain why.","answer":"Sorghum, Sudan grass, or Johnson grass; can cause cystitis (urinary tract infections) or cyanide (prussic acid) toxicity"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2440","question":"What is a summer annual grass that originated in Ethiopia where it's used primarily as a cereal crop?","answer":"Teff"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2441","question":"Which grasses tend to be LOWER in nutritional value, warm season or cool season grasses?","answer":"Warm season grasses"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2442","question":"What warm-season, perennial, sod-forming grass is grown for both pasture and hay?","answer":"Bermuda grass"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2443","question":"Although crabgrass is generally thought of as a nuisance, it produces extremely palatable, high quality forage and is generally preferred by horses over what?","answer":"Other perennial grasses"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2444","question":"Give ONE advantage of growing crabgrass in pastures with tall fescue.","answer":"Summer production is highest at time when fescue growth has slowed; dilutes toxins present in endophyte-infected tall fescue"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2445","question":"What warm season grass frequently invades Bermuda grass and tall fescue pastures and lawns?","answer":"Crabgrass"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2446","question":"Name 3 warm season grasses that are NOT recommended for pastures.","answer":"Sorghum, Sudan grass, Johnson grass, Sorghum/Sudan hybrids"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2447","question":"Horses spend what percent of their time grazing at night?","answer":"20 - 50% (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2448","question":"If forage is good, approximately how long do free ranging horses graze per day?","answer":"10 - 17 hours per day (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2449","question":"Horses on pasture will spend 10 - 17 hours per day doing what?","answer":"Grazing"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2450","question":"How does the relative humidity affect the length of grazing time?","answer":"Higher humidity results in longer grazing time"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2451","question":"The horse is an animal that developed grazing on grasslands.  Its digestive tract was therefore designed to do what?","answer":"Handle frequent, small feedings of forage"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2452","question":"According to the Horse Industry Handbook, tell which grazes longer per day for each of the 3 following pairs:  stallions or mares, Thoroughbreds or Arabians, and individuals or herds.","answer":"Mares, Arabians, herds"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2453","question":"Name 3 things that influence grazing time for horses on pastures","answer":"Age, gender, breed, grouping, time of day, season, environmental conditions (rain, wind, snow, temperature, humidity, etc.) (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2454","question":"When feeding groups of horses, what may develop because of dominance issues and may cause aggressive behavior?","answer":"Pecking order"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2455","question":"The horse's digestive system was not designed to be fed large quantities of what type of feed?","answer":"Concentrates or grain"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2456","question":"A dramatic increase in the amount of grain fed to your horse should occur gradually over what period of time?","answer":"10 - 14 days (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2457","question":"When changing types of hay, how should you manage the change?","answer":"Mix the types together for a period of approximately two weeks"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2458","question":"What is the easiest way to determine if your horse's energy or calorie needs are being met?","answer":"Monitor body weight"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2459","question":"Older horses may need some adjustments to their diet in order to maintain what?","answer":"Body condition or weight (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2460","question":"A horse is considered at maintenance if he is what?","answer":"Not working, not growing, not producing (not pregnant or lactating) (accept any)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2461","question":"Horses like to have a regular routine and are less likely to go off their feed or develop vices if fed how?","answer":"On a regular schedule"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2462","question":"Horsemen should feed by weight, not by what?","answer":"Volume"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2463","question":"How many pounds of a complete feed are needed to meet the average 1000 pound horse's daily needs?","answer":"10 - 15 pounds (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2464","question":"You do the math…A horse will eat approximately 2% of its body weight daily.  If a 1000 pound horse is only fed hay, how many pounds will he eat per day?","answer":"20 pounds"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2465","question":"When using a complete feed, how many pounds it is advised to feed at one feeding?","answer":"2 - 4 pounds per feeding (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2466","question":"Why is it recommended to feed horses 2 - 3 times a day instead of once?","answer":"Horses have small stomachs; overeating can cause colic"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2467","question":"During winter, the average 1000 pound mature idle horse requires how much hay per day?","answer":"15 - 20 pounds (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2468","question":"How many acres of pasture per horse do you need in order to maintain productivity?","answer":"2 - 3 acres per horse (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2469","question":"When feeding a group of horses together in open areas, how far apart should the feeders be placed?","answer":"40 - 50 feet apart (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2470","question":"Describe ONE way you'd manage the change when switching horses from grass hay to lush pasture.","answer":"Turn them out for just a few hours a day at first; slowly increase the grazing time; feed hay before turning them out; use a grazing muzzle (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2471","question":"Name 3 feeding guidelines.","answer":"Water available; salt available; feed at regular times; don't feed on ground; don't overfeed; don't feed moldy hay; feed by weight not volume; several small feedings are better than one big feeding; change feeds gradually (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2472","question":"You do the math…You are feeding a weanling that weighs approximately 400 pounds.  If you are feeding twice a day and need to feed a total of 1% of the body weight, how many pounds would you feed for the morning feeding?","answer":"2 (two) pounds"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2473","question":"What is the FIRST step in designing a workable feeding program?","answer":"Figuring out the nutrient requirements of the horse (FYI:  Nutrient requirements for horses are determined on their body weight, physiological status, and state of production.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2474","question":"Explain the difference between a balanced ration and a maintenance ration.","answer":"Balanced ration contains all digestible nutrients required; maintenance ration furnishes just enough of each required nutrient to maintain horse in current condition"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2475","question":"What is the term for a ration that supplies the proper amounts of all nutrients needed by the animal?","answer":"Balanced ration (also accept complete feed) "},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2476","question":"You are feeding your barrel horse 10 pounds of grain a day.  How many pounds of hay would you need to feed per day?","answer":"At least 10 pounds of hay per day (FYI: Forage should be at least 50% of the horse's ration.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2477","question":"A single feeding of concentrates should NEVER exceed what amount?","answer":"5 (five) pounds or not more than 3/4% of the horse's body weight (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2478","question":"You do the math…If a lactating broodmare should be fed 3% of her body weight in total feed each day, how much total feed should a mare that weighs 900 pounds receive in a day?","answer":"27 pounds of total feed intake (900 x 0.03=27)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2479","question":"Based on research studies for the initial re-feeding of the starved horse, the best approach is feeding what type of feed?","answer":"High quality alfalfa hay (in frequent small feedings)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2480","question":"The amount fed should be adjusted as necessary to maintain what?","answer":"Optimal body weight or condition"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2481","question":"What type of ration is designed to keep a horse in the same physical condition, not allowing weight gain or loss?","answer":"Maintenance ration"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2482","question":"What is the definition of a ration?","answer":"Entire amount of feed allowed an animal for a day"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2483","question":"In general, how much feed should a horse consume per day?","answer":"1½ to 3% of his body weight (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2484","question":"2 part question:  How should concentrate feeds be measured and explain why?","answer":"Measure by weight (not by volume); concentrates weigh different amount (a coffee can of oats will weigh less than a coffee can of corn)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2485","question":"Name 3 questions you might ask when trying to determine if nutrition is a cause of disease or poor performance.","answer":"What type of feed; how much and how often was horse fed; how long has horse been on this feeding program; is horse in pasture or stall; how many horses were affected; were toxic plants eaten; does horse have any other signs of disease"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2486","question":"Name 5 feeding guidelines.","answer":"Water available; salt available; feed at regular times; don't feed on ground; don't overfeed; don't feed moldy hay; feed by weight not volume; several small feedings are better than one big feeding; change feeds gradually (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2487","question":"Name the TWO basic types of hay.","answer":"Grass and legume"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2488","question":"What is the most important winter feed for horses, hay or grain?","answer":"Hay"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"int bonus","number":"2489","question":"Name 3 basic steps in making hay.","answer":"Growing; cutting; raking; drying; baling; storing"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2490","question":"Give 3 possible causes for the lack of a sweet or pleasant smell in hay.","answer":"Over maturity; bleaching; old hay; mold; leaching"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2491","question":"What is the oldest and most common method of selecting hay?","answer":"Visual appraisal (by looking at it)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2492","question":"You have just purchased a truckload of grass hay and would like to have it tested for nutrient analysis.  Explain how you'd do this.","answer":"Use a hay probe to take samples from at least 20 bales; mix samples together; send 1 quart of the mixture to the lab for analysis"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2493","question":"What is the MOST ACCURATE method of assessing the nutrient makeup of hay?","answer":"Chemical analysis"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2494","question":"What is a hay probe?","answer":"Instrument used for taking samples of hay for nutrient analysis"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2495","question":"Name TWO things to look for when selecting good hay.","answer":"Green color; fine stems; lots of leaves; no dust; no mold; no weeds; no bad odor; no poisonous plants; no blister beetles; no foreign objects; no rain damage (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2496","question":"Name 3 qualities to look for when purchasing hay.","answer":"Green color; fine stems; lots of leaves; no dust; no mold; no weeds; no bad odor; no poisonous plants; no blister beetles; no foreign objects; no rain damage (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2497","question":"What instrument is used to take hay samples for nutrient content analysis?","answer":"Hay probe"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2498","question":"Name TWO components of the visual appraisal of hay is other than just looking at the hay.","answer":"Feel and smell"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2499","question":"Name 4 qualities to look for when purchasing hay.","answer":"Green color; fine stems; lots of leaves; no dust; no mold; no weeds; no bad odor; no poisonous plants; no blister beetles; no foreign objects; no rain damage (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2500","question":"What is the ideal percentage for the moisture content of hay when it is baled?","answer":"17% (accept any number within the 15 - 20% range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2501","question":"Hay that's been mowed, then rained on, can lose what percent of its nutritional value?","answer":"40 - 50% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2502","question":"Give ONE reason why hay should NOT be baled if the moisture level is over 30%.","answer":"Hay will become moldy; hay will heat up; hay will lose vitamins; hay will have decreased protein digestibility; spontaneous combustion"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2503","question":"Give TWO characteristics of moldy hay.","answer":"Musty smell; whitish color; dusty; unpalatable; damp; hot"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2504","question":"Name 3 things that can happen when hay is baled with a moisture level of 30%.","answer":"Hay will become moldy; hay will heat up; hay will lose vitamins; hay will have decreased protein digestibility; spontaneous combustion (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2505","question":"What happens to the total nutrient content of hay when it is over-cured and baled with a moisture content that is too low?","answer":"Nutrient content decreases (because the leaves shatter and fall off)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2506","question":"2 part question:  Hay should be baled at a maximum moisture content of 15% - 20%.   Give ONE reason why moisture content above this level and ONE reason why moisture content below this level could reduce the quality of the baled hay.","answer":"Above–potential for mold, increased heat production, or decreased protein levels); below–leaves will be lost during processing (which decreases the nutritional value and palatability)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2507","question":"Name 3 types of cereal grain used for hay.","answer":"Oat, beardless wheat, barley"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2508","question":"Hay with a bleached color indicates exposure to what?","answer":"Sunlight or rain (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2509","question":"Describe the color of overly mature hay.","answer":"Pale yellow or brown (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2510","question":"In reference to hay, what part of the plant is the LEAST digestible?","answer":"Stems"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2511","question":"As hay grows older, does it become more or less digestible?","answer":"Less digestible"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2512","question":"Give TWO reasons for spraying preservatives such as mold inhibitors or propionic acid on forage as its cut.","answer":"Reduces bacterial and fungal growth; allows farmer to bale at higher moisture content."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2513","question":"How long does hay usually take to dry after being cut?","answer":"3 - 5 days (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2514","question":"Which general type of hay usually has the LEAST dust?","answer":"Grass hay"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2515","question":"If you have to feed your horse dusty hay, how can you reduce the dustiness before feeding?","answer":"Sprinkle it with water."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2516","question":"What kind of hay tends to be the dustiest?","answer":"Legume hay (alfalfa)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2517","question":"Give ONE reason why hay should be fed in a feeder.","answer":"To decrease ingestion of sand, dirt, or feces; to decrease parasite infestation"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2518","question":"To decrease the chances of hay getting into the horse's eyes or the horse inhaling dust, hay feeders for horses should be no higher than what?","answer":"Shoulder level of the horse (also accept withers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2519","question":"Name TWO things that can occur if the hayrack is too high for the horse eating from it.","answer":"Hay gets into horse's eyes; increased dust inhalation; respiratory problems"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2520","question":"At what stage of growth is grass hay most easily digested by the horse?","answer":"Boot stage, pre-bloom stage, immature hay, or when seed heads begin to appear (accept any)  "},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2521","question":"Give 3 reasons why immature hay at the pre-bloom or boot stage is more desirable as horse feed than mature hay.","answer":"Most easily digested; highest leaf to stem ratio; highest nutrient value"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2522","question":"Name 3 factors that influence when to cut hay.","answer":"Weather conditions, labor availability, equipment availability, if cut too early or too late plants may not re-grow well for the next cutting"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2523","question":"What physical part of hay contains the highest level of carbohydrates and proteins?","answer":"Leaves"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2524","question":"Give ONE reason why hay can't supply all the energy needs for a hard-working horse.","answer":"Energy concentration of hay is lower than that of grain; horse can't eat enough hay to meet the increased energy needs "},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2525","question":"Name 3 factors affecting the quality of hay.","answer":"Type (grass or legume), species, stage of maturity when cut, leafiness, weather conditions, harvest conditions, curing procedures, storage conditions, presence of weeds, presence of pests, presence of dust, presence of mold"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2526","question":"Which hay would have a higher calcium content, Timothy or clover?","answer":"Clover"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2527","question":"Which cutting of hay will usually have the HIGHEST fiber content?","answer":"First cutting"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2528","question":"What happens to the lignin content as hay matures?","answer":"Lignin content increases as hay matures. (FYI: Lignin, like cellulose, is a complex compound found in the cell walls of plants.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2529","question":"If hay is rained on before baling, it will lose some nutrients, especially carbohydrates.  However, good quality, rained on hay can benefit horses that are sensitive to what?","answer":"Forage sugar content"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2530","question":"Hay bought during the winter will often be high priced for what reason?","answer":"Demand is high; hay is hard to find, so prices are raised (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2531","question":"Give ONE reason why hay prices fluctuate from year to year.","answer":"Weather during growing and processing; type of hay grown; how hay is stored; fuel costs; number of horses in region; demand from other livestock species; perceived value of forage type (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2532","question":"Many factors influence the supply and demand for hay and thus hay prices.  Name TWO supply factors and TWO demand factors","answer":"Supply—weather, species, preservation techniques, storage availability, fuel cost; demand—number of horses in region, perceived value of certain forage species, demand from other livestock species, weather"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2533","question":"Older horses with dental problems may not be able to eat forage in the traditional form of hay and may need alternatives.  Name TWO of these alternatives.","answer":"Chopped hay, hay cubes (soak first), hay pellets, complete feeds"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2534","question":"What is the main objective when growing and processing hay?","answer":"Preserve nutrient and energy content"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2535","question":"Name 3 ways that hay can be processed.","answer":"Small rectangular bales, big round bales, big rectangular bales, hay cubes, pellets, chopped, silage, compressed"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"jr bonus","number":"2536","question":"Give 3 ways hay can be fed to horses other than loose or from bales.","answer":"Cubes, pellets, chopped, silage, compressed, wafers"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2537","question":"What are hay cubes?","answer":"Cubes of hay (hay that's been chopped, compressed, and formed into cubes)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2538","question":"Give ONE advantage of hay cubes.","answer":"Easy to transport, easy to store, more consistent product"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2539","question":"How many pounds of hay cubes can be fed to horses per day?","answer":"Up to 15 pounds per day"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2540","question":"Give ONE disadvantage of feeding hay cubes.","answer":"Horse can develop vices such as wood chewing if no long stem forage is fed; potential for choke"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2541","question":"NUTRITIONALLY, what is the only advantage of feeding hay pellets over hay?","answer":"You get a more consistent product with hay pellets."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2542","question":"Hay can be stored for how long without losing more than 20% of its nutrients?","answer":"1 - 2 years (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2543","question":"What is the most important factor to consider when storing hay?","answer":"Protect hay from moisture"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2544","question":"Why should you store hay off the ground?","answer":"So moisture from the ground won't spoil the bottom bales or so air can circulate (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2545","question":"How can storing \"heavy\" bales of hay cause fires?","answer":"Dampness or mold in heavy bales can cause hot spots that can lead to spontaneous combustion"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2546","question":"Name 3 things to consider when storing hay.","answer":"Store off the ground so ground moisture won't spoil bottom bale, allow for air circulation, protect from sunlight, protect from moisture/rain, protect from vermin"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2547","question":"Most studies to date have shown that herbal supplements don't enhance normal immune response, but may help with what?","answer":"Compromised immune system"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2548","question":"Just because herbs are natural, doesn't necessarily mean they're safe.  Name 3 negative things about using them in the horse's diet.","answer":"Can cause toxicity, negative side effects, drug-like interaction with other components of diet, some contain prohibited substances, potential for some to be banned from various competitions"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2549","question":"What is the most common legume fed to horses?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2550","question":"Legumes are higher in protein and calcium than what other type of forage?","answer":"Grasses"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2551","question":"What does a legume contain that allows it to produce higher levels of energy and protein than grasses?","answer":"Bacteria (in the root nodules)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2552","question":"Which legume is more expensive than others and is also difficult to establish?","answer":"Birdsfoot trefoil"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2553","question":"Perennial peanut hay is a good substitute for what other legume in tropical regions?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2554","question":"Which is higher in protein alfalfa, hay, or corn?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2555","question":"Birdsfoot trefoil is a low-growing legume perennial that's commonly used by highway departments for what purpose?","answer":"Roadside seeding or erosion control (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2556","question":"Which type of clover has low productivity, but it's commonly found in pre-packaged pasture mixes?","answer":"White clover (FYI:  White clover is nutritious, palatable, and is very competitive in pastures when conditions are cool and moist.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2557","question":"Which type of hay should NOT be fed to horses with kidney problems?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2558","question":"Give ONE reason why pure alfalfa pasture is NOT recommended for most horses.","answer":"Contains more protein than most horses require; requires long rest periods between grazing"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2559","question":"Red clover grows best in acidic, wet soils and is usually grown in areas where which other legume will not grow?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2560","question":"2 part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using red clover in pastures.","answer":"Advantages—highly nutritious, deep rooted, grows where alfalfa won't grow, easy to establish; disadvantages—biennial (only grows for two years), can cause photosensitivity, can cause slobbering"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2561","question":"Name 3 different varieties of clover that can be used in pastures or for HAY.","answer":"Red, alsike, sweet, white, ladino"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2562","question":"Name 3 legumes commonly used for HAY.","answer":"Alfalfa, birdsfoot trefoil, red clover, white clover, perennial peanut"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2563","question":"Name 3 legumes commonly used in PASTURES.","answer":"Alfalfa, birdsfoot trefoil, red clover, white clover, alsike clover, sweet clover"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2564","question":"Give 3 considerations and/or potential hazards associated with feeding alfalfa pasture or hay.","answer":"Dust; mold; blister beetles; mycotoxins; caution in older horses; caution with kidney, liver, or metabolic problems; can cause development orthopedic disease (DOD), respiratory problems, colic, tying up, thumps, or mineral imbalances"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2565","question":"Name ONE possible cause of eating problems such as wood chewing, eating dirt, tail chewing, or eating tree bark.","answer":"Boredom; lack of long stem forage or “chew time”; lack of exercise; copying other horses; nutrition problems"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2566","question":"Give ONE reason why a horse may not have cleaned up his feed.","answer":"Overfed, something wrong with the feed, limited access to water, horse is sick, horse has teeth problems (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2567","question":"Why would you mix chaff or chopped hay in with your horse's grain?","answer":"To discourage horse from bolting feed"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"int bonus","number":"2568","question":"Name 3 things that cause horses to chew bark off trees.","answer":"Boredom; lack of long stem forage or “chew time”; lack of exercise; changes in weather; taste of bark of certain trees (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2569","question":"Just before winter, some may feed their older horses to achieve a body condition score greater than 5.  Why would this be helpful?","answer":"Horse has to use more energy in the cold weather"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2570","question":"Name ONE thing that energy or calorie deficiency in mature animals causes.","answer":"Weight loss, poor reproduction, or poor athletic performance"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2571","question":"Why is eating grain less effective than eating hay for keeping a horse warm in winter?","answer":"One pound of hay produces more body heat than one pound of grain (FYI:  The heat of fermentation of fiber will help keep the horse warm)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2572","question":"What GENERAL type of pasture plants provides the greatest amount of nutrients and a longer grazing season?","answer":"Mixture of grasses and legumes"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2573","question":"What causes \"hay belly\"?","answer":"Horse eating more hay (extra bulk distends the intestinal tract)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2574","question":"What type of equine is more efficient in digesting fiber and therefore can be fed a diet that is higher in fiber?","answer":"Donkey"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2575","question":"Name 3 things on which selection of feeds should be based.","answer":"Nutrient content (quality); cost; availability; acceptability to horse (palatability); convenience (of storing and feeding)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2576","question":"Name 3 factors, other than feeding too little, that result in thin horses.","answer":"Parasites, lactating mares, hard work, poor teeth, pecking order/too much competition for food, malabsorption, hot/humid weather, disease, starvation"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2577","question":"Name 3 commercial feed classes.","answer":"Sweet feed, complete feed, pellets, extruded feed, supplements"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2578","question":"Name the 3 general types of feed.","answer":"Forage, concentrates, mixed feed"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2579","question":"Give ONE reason why you'd use a complete feed.","answer":"When you only have poor quality hay, when you have no hay available, horse with poor teeth (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2580","question":"What is a \"complete feed\"?","answer":"Combination of concentrates and forage in one product, one you don't have to feed hay with, one that provides all the horse's nutritional needs (accept any)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2581","question":"A complete feed contains all of the nutrients needed by the horse except for what TWO things?","answer":"Water and salt"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2582","question":"In which of the 3 main types of feed do grains and molasses fall?","answer":"Concentrates (FYI: The 3 main types of feeds are forages, concentrates, and mixed feeds.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2583","question":"Give 3 examples of concentrates.","answer":"Grain, molasses, by-product feeds (rice bran, wheat bran), vitamin supplements, mineral supplements, protein supplements, energy supplements, fats"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2584","question":"A deficit of what TWO nutrients can cause fatigue or exhaustion?","answer":"Energy, water, electrolytes"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2585","question":"Give TWO benefits of feeding flaxseed to horses.","answer":"Gives glossy hair coat or “bloom”; softens stools to prevent impaction; has high level of Omega 3 fatty acids; treats allergic skin disease or “sweet itch” (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2586","question":"Name 3 herbs commonly fed to horses.","answer":"Devil’s claw, Echinacea, garlic, ginger, ginseng, valerian root, yucca"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2587","question":"Name 3 contributing factors that result in obese horses.","answer":"Fed extra because people enjoy feeding them; overfeeding to mask undesirable traits; increasing feed as soon as they know mare's pregnant; inadequate exercise (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2588","question":"2 part question:  Explain the difference between straw and cereal grain forage and tell what each is used for.","answer":"Straw is what's left of the plant after the seed heads have been removed; used as bedding; cereal grains are plants such as oats that've been harvested with the seeds still attached; used as hay"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2589","question":"Straw should NOT be considered as a source of nutrition for horses other than for supplemental use as what?","answer":"Source of fiber or \"chew factor\""},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2590","question":"Name ONE grain that should be rolled or crimped before using.","answer":"Barley, milo or sorghum, wheat"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2591","question":"Which weighs less, a quart of pellets or a quart of extruded feed?","answer":"Extruded feed"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2592","question":"Extruded feeds are half the weight of pelleted feeds because of what substance found in each pellet?","answer":"Air"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2593","question":"What is the primary benefit of extruded feed?","answer":"Improved digestibility"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2594","question":"In reference to feeds, what is crimping?","answer":"Flattening and rippling grain (by running it through corrugated rollers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2595","question":"What is the process of cracking grain by passing it through corrugated rollers called?","answer":"Crimping"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2596","question":"Grains are processed in many ways.  What benefit does steam rolling have over dry rolling?","answer":"Decreases dust"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2597","question":"Name ONE thing that should be done to help foals, old horses, and horses with bad teeth digest grains.","answer":"Crack, crimp, roll, soak, steam, or extrude grain "},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2598","question":"Give 3 ways grain is processed.","answer":"Grinding, roasting, crimping, dry rolling, cracking, steaming, extruded, popping, pelleting"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2599","question":"Name 3 disadvantages of pelleted feed.","answer":"Increased cost, rapid rate of eating can lead to choke, if roughage not also fed can lead to bad habits like wood chewing"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2600","question":"Give 3 advantages of pelleted feeds.","answer":"Consistent product; decreased feed waste; less storage space; easier to store; easier to transport; reduced dust; better feed efficiency; beneficial for horses with poor teeth; less bulky"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2601","question":"What is trace mineralized salt?","answer":"Salt that contains trace minerals"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2602","question":"Name TWO types of salt blocks available for horses.","answer":"Plain, trace mineralized, iodized, added selenium, rock salt"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2603","question":"What is the chemical name for salt?","answer":"Sodium chloride (NaCl) (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2604","question":"Besides water, horses on pasture not having access to commercial feeds should always have access to what?","answer":"Salt (or trace mineralized salt)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2605","question":"Why should you offer salt free choice?","answer":"Horse will usually eat enough to meet its needs without overeating"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2606","question":"How should sodium chloride or salt be fed in a horse's diet?","answer":"Free choice"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2607","question":"How much free-choice salt will horses typically consume each day?","answer":"1 - 3 ounces (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2608","question":"What is \"lite salt\"?","answer":"½ sodium chloride and ½ potassium chloride"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2609","question":"Give TWO reasons why you do NOT need to add Vitamin B to a horse’s ration.","answer":"Good quality hay is an excellent source; significant amounts are produced in the horse’s intestines"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2610","question":"Steamed bone meal, limestone, and dicalcium phosphate are the most common sources of what TWO minerals?","answer":"Calcium and phosphorus"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2611","question":"What is a calming supplement designed to do for a horse?","answer":"Quiet down a nervous or excited horse"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2612","question":"Why is glucosamine commonly used as a supplement in animals and humans?","answer":"Glucosamine decreases the symptoms of arthritis."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2613","question":"Name ONE supplement that’s commonly used for arthritis in horses.","answer":"Glucosamine, chondroitin, hyaluronic acid (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2614","question":"What is the percentage of digestible protein in protein supplements?","answer":"25 - 48% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2615","question":"Give TWO reasons why soybean meal is a popular supplement.","answer":"High in protein; economical"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2616","question":"Name ONE effect of an equine supplement that contains Valerian Root.","answer":"Calming effect, sedative effect, anti-spasmodic effect"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2617","question":"Give ONE advantage of feeding Zeolite to young horses.","answer":"Increases bone density; decreases exertion induced bone injuries (FYI: Zeolite is a silicon-based supplement.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2618","question":"What is the name of the residue remaining in feeds after complete burning of the organic material?","answer":"Ash"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2619","question":"What is a biennial plant?","answer":"Plant that lasts for two years (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2620","question":"What is cellulose?","answer":"Plant fiber (complex carbohydrates in the cell walls of plants)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2621","question":"In reference to feeds, what is dry matter?","answer":"What's left in a feed after the water has been removed"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2622","question":"What is an \"easy keeper\"?","answer":"Animal that doesn't need as much feed as others under similar conditions"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"intermediate","number":"2623","question":"What is an animal called that's nutritionally unthrifty and that requires more feed than others?","answer":"Hard keeper"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2624","question":"What is an omnivore?","answer":"Animal that eats both plants and meat"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2625","question":"Referring to feeds, what does the term \"tillering\" mean?","answer":"Plants in early stages of growth"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2626","question":"What is the term for animals that prefer to eat plants?","answer":"Herbivore"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2627","question":"Explain the difference between an herbivore and a carnivore.","answer":"Herbivores eat plants; carnivores eat meat."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2628","question":"In feeding management, what is the wicking effect?","answer":"Uptake of moisture from ground into a bale of hay"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2629","question":"Horses are less likely to consume toxic plants if provided with what?","answer":"Enough hay or pasture (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"int bonus","number":"2630","question":"Name 3 poisonous plants. PART OF THE ANSWER DO NOT READ:  White Snakeroot; white top; milkweed; moldy sweet clover; alsike clover; black walnut; buttercup; horse chestnut (buckeye); pokeweed; dogbane; lily of the valley; elderberry; chokecherry","answer":"Yew; water hemlock; poison hemlock; oleander; death camas; locoweed; foxglove; Johnson or Sudan grass; wild cherry; red maple; yellow star thistle; Russian knapweed; horsetail; fiddleneck or bracken fern; tansy ragwort; St. John’s wort; horsetail"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2631","question":"Name 3 poisonous trees found in North America.","answer":"Red maple; oak (acorns); black walnut; chokecherry or wild black cherry; elderberry; horse chestnut or buckeye; black locust; black chestnut (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2632","question":"Name 3 plants that induce excessive salivation in the horse.","answer":"Red clover; foxtail; bearded barley; awns from wheat or rye; poison hemlock; water hemlock; death camas; Russian thistle; yellow star thistle; Canada thistle; white snakeroot; horse nettle; stinging nettle; azalea; bristle grass; buttercup; laurel"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2633","question":"Name TWO measures which can be taken to help prevent plant poisoning in your horse.","answer":"Proper pasture management, feed clean hay, don't feed garden waste, don't enclose horses close to toxic plants, be able to recognize toxic plants"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2634","question":"Name 3 effects of ingesting poisonous plants.","answer":"Excessive salivation (slobbering); colic; diarrhea; photosensitivity; liver disease; neurologic disease; lameness; muscle weakness; anemia; sudden death; birth defects (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2635","question":"Give TWO signs or symptoms of black walnut poisoning.","answer":"Decreased feed intake, depression, laminitis, respiratory distress, leg edema, colic, death"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2636","question":"What is the slang term for aimless wandering, circling, and apparent blindness caused by locoweed or moldy corn poisoning?","answer":"Blind staggers"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2637","question":"Give ONE cause of blind staggers.","answer":"Moldy corn, locoweed, or selenium poisoning"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2638","question":"What insect should you check your hay for?  These insects can harm the horse if eaten.","answer":"Blister beetles"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2639","question":"2 part question:  Blister beetle poisoning is more common when horses consume what type of hay and explain why?","answer":"Alfalfa or clover hay; the beetles are crushed during the hay making process so they remain in the baled hay"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2640","question":"What is the toxin produced by blister beetles?","answer":"Cantharidin (can-THAIR-ih-din)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2641","question":"Give ONE way you can reduce the likelihood of blister beetle infestation in hay you purchase.","answer":"Only buy hay from known sources; buy first cutting hay (which is seldom infested)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2642","question":"What is the biggest danger associated with blister beetles?","answer":"Blister beetles secrete a toxic chemical (cantharidin) which can cause death if eaten, even if the blister beetles are dried."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2643","question":"How does drying affect the toxicity of Buttercups?","answer":"Buttercups become non-toxic when they are dried."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2644","question":"2 part question:  What is Rumensin and how is it associated with horses?","answer":"Feed additive used to increase feed efficiency and weight gain in cattle; should NOT be fed to horses because it's highly toxic"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2645","question":"Why should you NOT feed cattle or poultry feed to horses?","answer":"Can contain antibiotics or other toxins that can poison horses"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2646","question":"What cattle feed additive is extremely toxic to horses?","answer":"Those that contain ionophores (such as Monensin or Rumensin) or growth hormones"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2647","question":"Horses that eat the leaves of wild cherry trees can get what kind of poisoning?","answer":"Cyanide poisoning"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2648","question":"Name ONE poison that is found in Johnson and Sudan grasses.","answer":"Cyanide (prussic acid) and nitrates (cause cystitis)  "},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2649","question":"Other than death, give 3 symptoms of cyanide poisoning.","answer":"Cherry-red venous blood, rapid labored breathing, frothing at the mouth, dilated pupils, incoordination, muscle tremors, convulsions, dark red or cyanotic mucous membranes"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2650","question":"What is the most common group of toxins that result in feed-related poisoning?","answer":"Mycotoxins (toxins from molds or fungi)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2651","question":"In reference to toxins in feeds, what is a mycotoxin?","answer":"Toxin produced by a mold or fungus"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2652","question":"Virtually all feed has some mold spores, but presence of excessive mold can cause several problems if inhaled.  Name 3 of these problems.","answer":"Coughing, heaves, allergic reactions"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2653","question":"Name 3 health problems caused by mycotoxins.","answer":"Feed refusal, reproductive problems, immune system suppression, excess slobbering, photosensitivity, blood clotting problems"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2654","question":"Name 3 conditions that can cause mold in feed.","answer":"Moisture, high heat, broken grain kernels, insect infestation, improper harvesting, improper packaging, improper storage"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2655","question":"Name TWO feeds that are often affected by mycotoxins.","answer":"Tall fescue, corn, peanuts, cottonseed, red clover"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2656","question":"Corn infected with aflatoxins can cause damage to what organ of the horse's body?","answer":"Liver"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2657","question":"Name 3 signs or symptoms of “clover poisoning”.","answer":"Slobbers (red clover affected with fungus “black patch”); photosensitivity (alsike); liver damage (alsike); clotting problems (moldy sweet clover) [accept any correct answers]"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2658","question":"Which type of clover can cause photosensitivity and liver damage?","answer":"Alsike clover"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2659","question":"What is the MAIN symptom of a horse that has grazed red clover that's affected with the fungus commonly known as \"black patch\"?","answer":"Excessive salivation or “slobbers” (FYI:  Black patch produces Slaframine.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2660","question":"Sweet clover poisoning results in altered blood clotting, anemia, and a deficiency of which vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin K (FYI:  Dicoumarin is produced by moldy sweet clover which affects vitamin K levels.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2661","question":"In reference to clover poisoning, what is dicoumarin?","answer":"Toxin found in moldy sweet clover (that affects Vitamin K levels and causes clotting problems)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2662","question":"Fescue poisoning affects pregnant mares in the late stages of gestation.  What is the best and easiest way to rapidly relieve the effects of fescue toxicosis?","answer":"Remove mare from infected fescue pasture or access to infected hay"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2663","question":"Which TWO general types of horses are affected by tall fescue poisoning?","answer":"Reproducing mares and foals"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2664","question":"Name ONE problem tall fescue can cause when used in pastures.","answer":"Prolonged gestation, abortion, decreased milk production, retained placenta, weak foals (caused by endophyte production)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2665","question":"What species of pasture grass contains a fungal endophyte that can cause problems in horses, especially pregnant mares?","answer":"Tall fescue (fescue)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2666","question":"Name 3 clinical signs associated with fescue toxicosis.","answer":"Prolonged gestation; abortion; decreased milk production; retained placenta; thickened placenta; dystocia (difficult birth); weak foals; slow growth in foals (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2667","question":"Why is foxtail harmful to horses even though it's not toxic?","answer":"Awns can become imbedded in the mucous membranes of the mouth (and can cause ulcers)."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2668","question":"When are oak trees most toxic?","answer":"In the spring (FYI:  Leaves are green and flower buds are just opening.  Green acorns are more toxic than aged acorns.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2669","question":"Tannic acid is produced by what plant?","answer":"Oak"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2670","question":"Acorns produce what plant toxin?","answer":"Tannic acid"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2671","question":"What is the main symptom observed after ingestion of Pokeweed?","answer":"Diarrhea"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2672","question":"Name ONE part of the red maple tree that is toxic to horses.","answer":"Dry, wilted leaves; bark"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2673","question":"At what stage are red maple leaves toxic to horses?","answer":"When they're wilted or dried"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2674","question":"What perennial weed has five bright yellow petals, 5 green sepals, and may cause colic, diarrhea, and photodermatitis?","answer":"St. John's Wort"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2675","question":"It is rare that a horse is poisoned by a single mouthful of a toxic plant.  Name ONE plant that is an exception to this rule.","answer":"Water hemlock, poison hemlock, yew"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"sr bonus","number":"2676","question":"Name 3 poisonous plants that can cause sudden death in the horse.","answer":"Yew; water hemlock; poison hemlock; oleander; death camas; foxglove; Johnson grass; Sudan grass; chokecherry; elderberry; service berry; arrow grass; pod grass; dog bane or Indian hemp; lily of the valley; milkweed; wild blue flax; larkspur"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2677","question":"Water hemlock contains one of the most poisonous compounds known.  What is this compound?","answer":"Cicutoxin (SICK-you-tox-in)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2678","question":"Name ONE ornamental plant that is very poisonous to horses if eaten.","answer":"Yew, red maple, oleander, rhododendron, foxglove, Indian paintbrush, Lily of the Valley, oak, black walnut"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2679","question":"What type of sudden death poisoning would be the result of ingestion of water hemlock?","answer":"Alkaloid sudden death"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2680","question":"Plant poisoning from consumption of Milkweed would be treated as what type of sudden death poisoning?","answer":"Cardiac sudden death"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2681","question":"Poisonous plants that are classified as hepatotoxic primarily affect which organ?","answer":"Liver"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2682","question":"Why do lactating mares have the best chance of survival after ingesting the poisonous plant White Snakeroot?","answer":"The toxin is excreted from the body by lactation."},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2683","question":"What is the main symptom of the poisoning that occurs when horses eat Yellow Star Thistle or Russian Knapweed?","answer":"Inability to take in or chew food (FYI: Poisoning is called \"chewing disease\" or nigropallidal encephalomalacia.)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"medium","number":"2684","question":"At what time of the year is Yellow Star Thistle a concern when ingested by horses?","answer":"Late summer to early fall (accept either)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2685","question":"Horses will usually drink enough water during the winter if water is maintained at what temperature?","answer":"45 - 68 degrees (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2686","question":"When allowed to choose between a bucket and an automatic watering system, which one did most horses prefer?","answer":"Bucket"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2687","question":"What does hyper-hydration mean?","answer":"Excess water consumption"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2688","question":"By the age of two months, most foals are drinking how much water per day?","answer":"Up to one gallon"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2689","question":"How much water do horses usually drink each day?","answer":"8 - 12 gallons per day (accept any number in this range)"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"hard","number":"2690","question":"Lactating mares may increase their water intake over their maintenance requirement by what  amount in order to meet lactation demands?","answer":"2 - 3 times maintenance requirement"},
{"category":"Feeds","level":"easy","number":"2691","question":"How many times do most horses drink per day?","answer":"2 - 8 times per day (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2692","question":"Name 3 natural gaits common to most breeds.","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, gallop, back"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2693","question":"Why do working ranch horses need to have gaits that are comfortable for the rider and are easy on the horse?","answer":"Both work long days (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2694","question":"What is the term used to describe the rhythmic, characteristic movements of a horse's feet and legs?","answer":"Gaits"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2695","question":"What is a natural gait?","answer":"Gait horse does naturally or is born knowing how to do (accept any reasonable wording) "},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2696","question":"What are TWO reasons you should have a working understanding of gaits?","answer":"To detect lameness, to train a performance horse, to be able to use a horse for a specific purpose"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2697","question":"What gaits does a 3 gaited horse perform?","answer":"Walk, trot, canter"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2698","question":"Name 3 gaits that have 4 beats.","answer":"Walk, gallop or run, slow gait or stepping pace, rack or singlefoot, running walk, amble, paso, tolt, racking walk (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2699","question":"Terms for gaits are somewhat synonymous.   Give the other name for each of the following gaits:  trot, lope, slow gait, and rack.","answer":"Trot—jog, lope—canter, slow gait—stepping pace, rack—single foot"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2700","question":"How many beats are there in the horse's gait when backing?","answer":"2 (two) beats"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2701","question":"What gait is an easy, rhythmical, 3-beat gait?","answer":"Canter or lope (accept either)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2702","question":"What was the original name for the canter?","answer":"Canterbury gallop"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2703","question":"Most gaits are symmetrical.  However, there are TWO asymmetrical gaits.  Name them.","answer":"Canter or lope and gallop or run"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2704","question":"How many beats are in the canter?","answer":"3 (three) beats"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2705","question":"In reference to gaits, what is a lead?","answer":"Independently moving or leading front leg in a canter/lope or gallop/run (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2706","question":"When a horse is cantering in a counterclockwise direction in a riding arena, which lead is considered the correct one?","answer":"Left lead"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2707","question":"While cantering on the right lead, which feet bear more weight and are subject to more strain?","answer":"Left hind and right front"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2708","question":"At the canter or lope, what do you call the independently moving front leg?","answer":"Lead"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2709","question":"Why should the leads at a canter be changed periodically?","answer":"So the muscles develop evenly on both sides of the horse or to prevent too much strain on one side of the horse (accept either)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2710","question":"What is the collected canter exhibited in Western classes called?","answer":"Lope"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2711","question":"When on the left lead, which leg or legs are on the ground for the SECOND BEAT of the canter?","answer":"Left rear and right front (FYI: 1st beat—right hind, 2nd beat—left hind and right front, 3rd beat—left front)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2712","question":"What is the LAST foot to hit the ground in the canter when on the right lead?","answer":"Right front"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2713","question":"With which foot does a horse START a right lead canter?","answer":"Left hind"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"novice","number":"2714","question":"What is another name for the gallop?","answer":"Run"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2715","question":"What is the difference between a full gallop as run by a racehorse and a hand gallop?","answer":"Full gallop is a 4-beat gait; hand gallop is a 3-beat gait and is more of an extended canter."},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2716","question":"How many beats are there in a gallop?","answer":"4 (four) beats "},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2717","question":"In the gallop, where does the drive or power come from?","answer":"Hindquarters or hind legs"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2718","question":"Beginning with the contact of the left hind foot with the ground explain the footfall sequence of a horse on the right lead at the gallop.","answer":"Left hind, right hind, left front, right front"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2719","question":"At a gallop on a right lead, what is the next foot to hit the ground after the right front?","answer":"Left rear"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2720","question":"What is the footfall sequence of a galloping horse?","answer":"One hind foot, the other hind foot, diagonal front foot, the other front foot"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2721","question":"How much weight may a horse dissipate on his lead foot when running?","answer":"1 (one) ton per second"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2722","question":"Name 3 causes of lameness that are NOT related to the feet or lower legs.","answer":"Neck pain; wither pain; shoulder pain; hip pain; stifle pain; inherited; trauma; infection; metabolic; neurological"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2723","question":"In reference to gaits, describe the pace.","answer":"Two beat gait lateral gait (legs move in lateral pairs; front and hind legs on the same side start and stop at the same time)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2724","question":"What is the base of support for the pace?","answer":"Two lateral legs (two legs on the same side are on the ground at once)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2725","question":"Which gait is a two-beat lateral gait?","answer":"Pace"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2726","question":"In reference to gaits, describe a sidepass.","answer":"Sideways movement without forward or backward movement"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2727","question":"Name this movement:   There is no forward or backward movement.  The horse steps laterally with both forequarters and hindquarters moving together with a crossover step.","answer":"Sidepass or traverse or sidestep"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2728","question":"Which gait is a rapid, two-beat diagonal gait?","answer":"Trot"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2729","question":"In reference to gaits, describe the trot.","answer":"Two beat diagonal gait (front foot and opposite hind foot start and stop at the same time)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2730","question":"What is the base of support for the trot?","answer":"Two diagonal legs"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2731","question":"Which gait is faster, the trot or the pace?","answer":"Pace"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2732","question":"What is the difference between a trot and a pace?","answer":"Trot—two-beat diagonal gait (opposite front and hind feet start and stop at the same time); pace—two-beat lateral gait (front and hind feet on the same side start and stop at the same time)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2733","question":"What is an extended trot?","answer":"Lengthening of the stride without an increase in tempo/speed"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2734","question":"What is the term for the lengthening of the trot stride without an increase in tempo?","answer":"Extended trot"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"novice","number":"2735","question":"What is another name for the slow trot seen in Western classes?","answer":"Jog"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2736","question":"The walk is the horse's slowest gait.  What is the average speed of the horse's walk?","answer":"4 miles per hour"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"novice","number":"2737","question":"Which gait is the slowest gait and is common to all breeds of horses?","answer":"Walk"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2738","question":"Which natural gait is the slowest 4-beat gait with each foot striking the ground independently from the other 3 feet?","answer":"Walk"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2739","question":"What kind of base of support does the horse have at the walk?","answer":"Triangular (3 legs are on the ground at once)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2740","question":"2 part question:  What does the term \"double-gaited\" mean and in which breed is it seen?","answer":"Horse can both trot and pace; Standardbred"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2741","question":"Name TWO acquired gaits.","answer":"Singlefoot or rack, slow gait or stepping pace, amble, paso, running walk, foxtrot (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2742","question":"What is the general term for gaits that must be taught?","answer":"Acquired gaits"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2743","question":"Which of the following is an acquired gait:  trot, slow gait, or canter?","answer":"Slow gait"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2744","question":"Name TWO gaits, other than the walk, trot, canter, gallop or back, that may be natural gaits to some breeds.","answer":"Running walk, fox trot, pace, paso (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2745","question":"In reference to gaits, what is an acquired gait?","answer":"Gait that requires training and practice (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2746","question":"What are 3 gaits of the Missouri Fox Trotter?","answer":"Walk, fox trot, and canter"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2747","question":"2 part question:  Identify this gait and name the breed.  The gait starts out as a simple trot, but the hind diagonal foot comes down before the front foot making it a 4 beat gait.","answer":"Gait—Foxtrot;  breed—Missouri Foxtrotter"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2748","question":"Describe the fox trot gait.","answer":"4 beat diagonal gait (where the hind foot hits the ground an instant before the diagonal forefoot; head usually nods; walking in front and trotting in back)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2749","question":"What is the name of the gait described as walking in front and trotting behind?","answer":"Fox trot"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2750","question":"Describe the paso gait.","answer":"Broken pace (4 beat lateral gait)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2751","question":"What are the 3 speeds of the paso gait?","answer":"Paso fino, paso corto, paso largo"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2752","question":"2 part question:  What is “termino” and in which breed is it seen?","answer":"Forelegs roll towards the outside as horse strides forward (like the arm motion of a swimmer); seen in the Peruvian Paso"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"int bonus","number":"2753","question":"Name the 5 gaits performed by a 5-gaited horse.","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, slow gait or stepping pace, rack or singlefoot"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2754","question":"What 2 gaits does a 5-gaited horse perform that a 3-gaited horse does NOT perform?","answer":"Slow gait (stepping pace); rack (singlefoot)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2755","question":"What is the 5th gait of the American Saddle Horse?","answer":"Rack or singlefoot (accept either)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2756","question":"What is the name for the fast, flashy, 4-beat gait that's sometimes referred to as the singlefoot?","answer":"Rack"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2757","question":"What is another name for the rack?","answer":"Singlefoot"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2758","question":"What is the fastest artificial gait?","answer":"Rack or singlefoot (accept either)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2759","question":"Which gait of the horse is easy on the rider, but is extremely tiring for the horse?  It's the fastest 4-beat artificial gait.","answer":"Rack or singlefoot (accept either)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2760","question":"What is another name for the slow gait?","answer":"Stepping pace"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2761","question":"How many beats are in the gait referred to as the stepping pace?","answer":"4 (four) beats"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"jr bonus","number":"2762","question":"Name the 3 gaits of the Tennessee Walker.","answer":"Walk (flat walk), running walk, canter (rocking chair canter)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2763","question":"What is the term used to describe the canter of the Tennessee Walker?","answer":"Rocking chair canter"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2764","question":"What is the name for a fast, 4-beat ground-covering walk of the Tennessee Walking Horse?","answer":"Running walk"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2765","question":"2 part question: The Plantation Gait is a smooth, ground-covering gait that made the Tennessee Walking Horse popular in the South. What is the proper name for this gait and how many beats does it have?","answer":"Running walk; 4 beats"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2766","question":"What is the footfall sequence for the running walk, starting with the left front foot?","answer":"Left front, right rear, right front, left rear"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2767","question":"When a horse is limited in his movement, what else is limited?","answer":"His usefulness"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2768","question":"Which abnormal way of going is worse, inward or outward movement of the front legs?","answer":"Inward movement (because legs can interfere)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"int bonus","number":"2769","question":"In reference to gaits, name 3 abnormal ways of going.","answer":"Paddling or winging out; dishing or winging in; winding, rope walking, or plaiting; rolling; trappy; pounding; cross firing; forging; interfering; pointing; scalping; speedy cutting; limping"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2770","question":"In reference to horses, what is a \"daisy cutter\"?","answer":"Horse that skims the surface of the ground at the trot  (doesn't bend legs much)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2771","question":"Which is the more dangerous deviation in the flight of the foot, paddling out or dishing in?","answer":"Dishing in"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2772","question":"How will a splay footed horse travel?","answer":"Dish or wing in"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2773","question":"What conformation fault does a horse have if he dishes or wings in when he travels?","answer":"Splay foot or toe out (also accept base wide)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2774","question":"What is the term used to describe a noticeable pause in the flight of the foot as though the stride were completed before the foot reaches the ground?","answer":"Floating or dwelling (accept either)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2775","question":"What is the term used when a horse's action is difficult to perform and is painfully excessive?","answer":"Labored action"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2776","question":"In reference to gaits, what is \"labored action\"?","answer":"When a horse has to work hard to move (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2777","question":"In reference to gaits, what is paddling?","answer":"Throwing the front feet outward while traveling"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2778","question":"What is the term used when a pigeon toed horse throws the front feet outward while traveling?","answer":"Paddling"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2779","question":"What is a perceptible extension of the stride with little flexion called?","answer":"Pointing"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2780","question":"In reference to gaits, what is pounding?","answer":"Striking the ground hard in the stride"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2781","question":"Pounding is a defect in the way of going and is often associated with what TWO conformation faults?","answer":"Straight shoulders and short, steep or straight pasterns"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2782","question":"Striking the ground hard in the stride is called what?","answer":"Pounding"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2783","question":"What is the term for excessive lateral shoulder motion?","answer":"Rolling"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2784","question":"In reference to gaits, what is rolling?","answer":"Excessive lateral shoulder motion (like the motion of a bulldog walking)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2785","question":"What is the term used when describing a winding or twisting of the striding leg around in front of the supporting leg which results in contact like that of a rope walking artist?","answer":"Rope walking, winding, or plaiting (accept any)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2786","question":"2 part question:  In reference to way of going, what is plaiting and what type of conformation results in this way of travel?","answer":"Forefeet travel inward to land in front of one another; occurs in base narrow, toed-out horses"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2787","question":"What is the term used when the stride lacks spring or action, therefore causing unnecessary rider fatigue?","answer":"Rough or hard gaited (accept either)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2788","question":"What do you call a pacer that rolls his body sideways as he paces?","answer":"Sidewheeler"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2789","question":"A trappy stride is most commonly seen in horses with what TWO conformation defects?","answer":"Straight shoulders and short, steep pasterns"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2790","question":"In reference to gaits, what does the term \"trappy\" mean?","answer":"Short, quick, choppy stride"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2791","question":"What is the term used for a short, quick, choppy stride?","answer":"Trappy"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2792","question":"What do you call an exaggerated paddling that is particularly noticeable in high-going horses?","answer":"Winging or winging out"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2793","question":"In what type of horse is winging out most noticeable?","answer":"High stepping harness horses (such as Saddlebreds, Hackneys, or Morgans)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2794","question":"In reference to gaits, as a GENERAL term what is interfering?","answer":"When a horse's leg hits another leg while the horse is moving"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2795","question":"What are the TWO major general types of leg interference that can occur in horses?","answer":"Supporting leg and striding leg interference"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2796","question":"In reference to gaits, what is the term for striking the inside one leg with the inside of the hoof or skin of the opposite leg?","answer":"Interfering"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"int bonus","number":"2797","question":"In reference to horse's way of going, name 3 types of interference.","answer":"Forging, scalping, crossfiring, speedy cutting, shin hitting, hock hitting, overreaching (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2798","question":"Roughened hair, nicks, and scars on the inside of the fetlock are evidence of what?","answer":"Interfering (also accept striking)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2799","question":"Explain the difference between stance phase and swing phase of a leg.","answer":"Stance phase is when the leg is on the ground; swing phase is when the leg is off the ground."},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2800","question":"2 part question:  Name TWO striding leg interferences where the toe of the forefoot hits the hind leg and describe where on the hind leg the striking occurs.","answer":"Hock hitting—front toe hits hock; scalping—front toe hits hind coronet; shin hitting—front toe hits hind cannon (on same side); speedy cutting—front toe hits hind pastern or fetlock (on same side)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2801","question":"In reference to supporting leg interference, explain the difference between brushing and striking","answer":"Brushing—slight contact between legs; striking – harder contact between legs that may result in an open wound"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2802","question":"In reference to gaits, what is brushing?","answer":"Slight contact between one leg and another leg"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2803","question":"What term refers to supporting leg interference that results in an open wound?","answer":"Striking"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2804","question":"In reference to gaits, what is cross firing?","answer":"Horse is on one lead in the front and on the opposite lead in the back; hindfoot on one side strikes the diagonal forefoot; forging in a pacing horse (accept any)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2805","question":"What is the name of the interference when a pacer hits the sole or shoe of the front foot with the diagonal rear foot?","answer":"Cross firing  "},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2806","question":"In reference to gaits, what is forging?","answer":"Striking the forefoot with the toe of the hindfoot (on the same side)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2807","question":"A short underline can cause a horse to do what?","answer":"Forge (also accept interfere)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2808","question":"Give the name of the traveling defect where the toe of the hindfoot hits the sole or shoe of the forefoot.","answer":"Forging"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2809","question":"In striding leg interference, a moving leg makes contact with another moving leg. What is this called when it occurs at a slow trot, disappears at a faster trot, and causes a characteristic clicking sound?","answer":"Forging"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2810","question":"What is it called when the toe of the front foot strikes the coronet or hairline of the hind hoof?","answer":"Scalping"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2811","question":"In reference to gaits, what is scalping?","answer":"Toe of the front foot hits the hairline or coronet of the hind foot (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2812","question":"What is the term used when the inside of the diagonal fore and the hind pasterns make contact, sometimes seen in fast trotting horses?","answer":"Speedy cutting"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"novice","number":"2813","question":"In reference to gaits, what is speedy cutting?","answer":"When the inside of the diagonal fore and the hind pasterns make contact (sometimes seen in fast trotting horses)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2814","question":"What movement is important for opening gates?","answer":"Side pass, sidestep, or traverse (accept any)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2815","question":"What is the speed of the canter?","answer":"10 – 17 miles per hour"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2816","question":"When running a quarter mile, racing Quarter Horses have been clocked at up to what speed?","answer":"50 miles per hour"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2817","question":"What is the speed of the running walk?","answer":"7 - 10 miles per hour (accept any answer within this range)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2818","question":"The trot is the most energy efficient of the gaits.  What is the speed of the trot?","answer":"8 – 10 miles per hour"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2819","question":"The distance from imprint to imprint by a horse's foot is called what?","answer":"Stride"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2820","question":"In relation to stride, name TWO things that determine a horse's speed.","answer":"Stride length; stride frequency (rapidity); amount of time the hoof is on the ground versus the time the hoof is off the ground"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2821","question":"Name 4 gaits that do NOT have a stride suspension phase.","answer":"Walk, foxtrot, amble, running walk, paso"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2822","question":"Name 3 important features of the stride.","answer":"Balance, directness, height, length, rapidity, regularity"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2823","question":"What is the term for the moment in a horse's stride between landing and takeoff?","answer":"Breakover"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2824","question":"In reference to foot action, what is meant by the term \"height\"?","answer":"Amount of elevation in the stride"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2825","question":"How do you determine the stride length of a horse?","answer":"Distance from imprint to imprint of the same foot"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2826","question":"At the gallop, Secretariat had a stride of what length?","answer":"29 feet"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2827","question":"What is the Thoroughbred's average length of stride at the gallop?","answer":"21 - 23 feet (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"sr bonus","number":"2828","question":"Give TWO reasons why you want a horse with a long stride.","answer":"Absorbs more shock, moves with less effort, covering longer distance with each stride"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2829","question":"What makes it possible for a horse to do a flying lead change?","answer":"Brief period of suspension (when all 4 legs are off the ground)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2830","question":"In which of the following breeds would you see the longest suspension during the trot, Hackney or Standardbred?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2831","question":"Referring to gaits, what is a \"period of suspension\"?","answer":"Period when all 4 feet are off the ground"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2832","question":"In reference to horses, what is action?","answer":"How a horse moves its feet and legs at the walk, trot, canter, etc."},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2833","question":"Your horse is being ridden at a controlled and correct gait.  The hocks are well under him and he is ridden well up to his bit with his neck flexed and his jaw relaxed.  What is the correct term for the appearance of this horse?","answer":"Collected"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2834","question":"What is a counter canter?","answer":"Balanced canter on one lead while the horse is traveling in the opposite direction (intentionally cantering a horse on the opposite lead from the direction it's traveling)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2835","question":"What is the term for a balanced canter on one lead while the horse is traveling in the opposite direction?","answer":"Counter canter"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2836","question":"What term would be used to describe a horse that's cantering on one lead in front and a different lead in the rear?","answer":"Disunited canter, cross firing, or cross canter (accept any)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2837","question":"What is the expression used for a horse's gaits when the rider's reaction is pleasant and enjoyable?","answer":"Easy gaited"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"hard","number":"2838","question":"Generally speaking, when it's said that a horse is \"engaged\", what does this mean?","answer":"Horse is using its hindquarters for impulsion"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2839","question":"What is the term for when a horse lifts his front and hind feet very high, flexing at the knees and hocks?","answer":"Flashy or high-gaited"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2840","question":"In reference to gaits, what is four-beating?","answer":"4-beat canter instead of a 3-beat canter (lopes with front legs and trots with hind legs)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2841","question":"In reference to gaits, explain free-going.","answer":"Free forward movement (when the horse moves forward freely in a smooth, collected manner without pain or difficulty) (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2842","question":"What is the expression used when a horse's gaits are executed in a smooth, collected manner and its action is not excessive or labored?","answer":"Free going"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"intermediate","number":"2843","question":"What is the term for changing from one gait to another?","answer":"Transition"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"easy","number":"2844","question":"What is meant by the term \"way of going\"?","answer":"How a horse moves (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Gaits","level":"medium","number":"2845","question":"What term is used to refer to the nature of movement in the horse?","answer":"Way of going or action (accept either)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2846","question":"What is the study of how characteristics are passed from parents to offspring?","answer":"Genetics"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2847","question":"What is the name of the special procedure used to visualize or examine chromosomes under a microscope?","answer":"Karyotyping (CARE-ee-oh-type-ing)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2848","question":"What is a punnet square?","answer":"Diagram that’s used to predict the outcomes of matings (way of determining what percentage of offspring of a mating will have which genes of the parents)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2849","question":"Who is known as the “father of modern genetics”?","answer":"Gregor Mendel (FYI: Mendel was a scientist and friar in the 1800’s who studied pea plants.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2850","question":"Define heredity.","answer":"Passing of traits from parents to offspring"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2851","question":"In reference to genetics, what does diploid mean?","answer":"Chromosomes are in pairs. (FYI:  Somatic or body cells are diploid; gametes or sex cells are haploid.  The prefix “di” means two.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2852","question":"In reference to genetics, what does haploid mean?","answer":"Chromosomes are single, NOT in pairs. (FYI:  Somatic or body cells are diploid; gametes or sex cells are haploid.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2853","question":"What is the COMMON term for deoxyribonucleic acid?","answer":"DNA"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2854","question":"Genes are made up of complex molecules of what?","answer":"DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2855","question":"If a gene CANNOT mask the genetic makeup of the other gene in a pair, is it dominant or recessive?","answer":"Recessive"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2856","question":"If a gene has the ability to mask the genetic makeup of the other gene in the pair, is it dominant or recessive?","answer":"Dominant"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2857","question":"In genetics, what does the term \"co-dominance\" mean?","answer":"When two alleles are equally dominant (like some color genes or genes for straight or curly hair)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2858","question":"In genetics, what does the term “partial dominance” mean?","answer":"Gene action that results in an intermediate state between the two alleles (Example:   A single dominant cream gene doesn’t make a chestnut a cremello.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2859","question":"Give ONE example of partial or incomplete dominance where the dominant gene is not fully expressed.","answer":"Cream dilution in a palomino"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2860","question":"The cream gene is a partially dominant gene which does what when combined with other color genes?","answer":"Lightens or dilutes the color"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2861","question":"What are the basic units of inheritance?","answer":"Genes"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2862","question":"In reference to genes, what is in allele? (uh-LEEL)","answer":"One possible form of a gene pair"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2863","question":"In reference to genetics, what are loci? (LOH-keye)","answer":"Specific locations of genes on a chromosome (FYI:  Singular is locus.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2864","question":"What does genotype mean?","answer":"Genetic makeup"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2865","question":"What does phenotype mean?","answer":"Outward appearance of an animal"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2866","question":"What is the difference between genotype and phenotype?","answer":"Genotype is the genetic makeup; phenotype is the outward appearance."},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2867","question":"If paired genes are the same, are they homozygous or heterozygous?","answer":"Homozygous"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2868","question":"If paired genes are NOT identical, are they homozygous or heterozygous?","answer":"Heterozygous"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2869","question":"Where is the cytoplasm located in a cell?","answer":"Between the nucleus and the cell wall"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2870","question":"What is the dense center of a cell that contains the genetic material?","answer":"Nucleus"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2871","question":"What is the nucleus of a cell?","answer":"Dense center of a cell that contains the genetic material"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2872","question":"In the inheritance of sex or gender in the horse, what are the chances for the foal to be male?","answer":"50 - 50 (half may be male)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2873","question":"What is the general term for the X and Y chromosomes?","answer":"Sex chromosomes"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2874","question":"What is the sex genotype for a mare?","answer":"XX"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2875","question":"What is the sex genotype of a stallion?","answer":"XY"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2876","question":"If a sperm carrying the X chromosome fertilizes the egg, what sex will the foal be?","answer":"Female"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2877","question":"What is the proper name for a mature sex cell?","answer":"Gamete"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2878","question":"In what type of cells do chromosomes exist as singles, NOT as pairs?","answer":"Sex cells, egg and sperm, gametes, or haploid cells (accept any)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2879","question":"The genetic material of the sperm cell is contained in which section of the sperm cell, the head, midpiece, or tail?","answer":"Head section"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2880","question":"Define 3 of the following terms:  outcrossing, grading up, crossbreeding, inbreeding, and line-breeding.","answer":"Outcrossing—mating animals from different families within the same breed; grading up—mating animal with unknown ancestry with registered animal; crossbreeding—mating registered animals of different breeds; inbreeding—mating closely related animals"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2881","question":"What do you call the form of inbreeding that's aimed at trying to maintain a close relationship with a particular animal?","answer":"Line breeding"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2882","question":"What is inbreeding?","answer":"Breeding closely related animals"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2883","question":"What does the term \"nicking\" mean?","answer":"When the offspring has more superior qualities than expected by their pedigree"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2884","question":"What is outcrossing?","answer":"Mating animals that are members of the same breed, but which show no relationship close up in the pedigree"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2885","question":"What is a chromosome?","answer":"Long, thread-like structure in the nucleus of a cell that contains genetic material"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2886","question":"How many chromosomes are responsible for the sex of a foal?","answer":"2 chromosomes (one pair)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2887","question":"2 part question:  Are chromosome pairs always identical?  Explain your answer.","answer":"No.  Males have XY sex chromosomes and females have XX chromosomes."},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2888","question":"How many PAIRS of chromosomes do horses have?","answer":"32 pairs of chromosomes"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2889","question":"How many chromosomes does the sperm of a stallion or an egg of a mare contain?","answer":"32 SINGLE chromosomes (Do NOT accept 32 pairs.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2890","question":"How many chromosomes do mules and hinnies have?","answer":"63 chromosomes (FYI: Horses have 64; donkeys have 62.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2891","question":"How many chromosomes does a donkey have?","answer":"62 chromosomes"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2892","question":"Are the genes for coat color separate or combined with the gene loci for occurrence and pattern of white hairs on the body?","answer":"Separate"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2893","question":"Genetically, name 3 ways a BLACK coat color be modified.","answer":"Dilutions; spotting;  graying; roaning;  agouti gene (bay)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2894","question":"Name 3 coat colors whose base color is black with a dilution or modification.","answer":"Bay and seal brown (agouti); buckskin (single cream bay); perlino (double cream bay); classic dun (dun bay); grulla (dun black); smoky black (single cream black); smoky cream (double cream black); red roan (bay); blue roan (black); gray"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2895","question":"What gene must be present to produce the color bay?","answer":"Dominant agouti gene (agouti gene)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2896","question":"In reference to coat color genetics, what color modifier do the letters A/a represent?","answer":"Agouti gene (FYI: Agouti gene controls the distribution of black on bay horses to the points only.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2897","question":"What does the agouti gene do?","answer":"Restricts the black pigmentation pattern to the points of the horse (mane, tail, lower leg, ear rims)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2898","question":"Genetically, what is the difference between a buckskin and a “classic” or \"coyote\" dun?","answer":"Buckskin is a cream dilution of bay; classic or coyote dun is a dun dilution of bay."},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2899","question":"What does dilution of color mean?","answer":"Lessening the intensity of the color"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2900","question":"Identify ONE of the two colors that must be present in the genetic  lineage of a cream colored horse.","answer":"Palomino or buckskin"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2901","question":"2 part question:  What color results from a single cream dilution of bay and what color results from a double cream dilution of bay?","answer":"Single cream dilution—buckskin; double cream dilution—perlino "},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2902","question":"What color is a cream dilution of bay?","answer":"Buckskin"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2903","question":"Genetically speaking, what is a buckskin?","answer":"(Single) cream dilution of bay"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2904","question":"A double cream dilution of chestnut results in what color?","answer":"Cremello"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2905","question":"The cremello color is a result of a double cream dilution of what base color?","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2906","question":"You are planning to breed your chestnut mare and would love her to produce a palomino foal.  In order to guarantee a foal of this color, what color stallion should she be bred to?","answer":"Cremello"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2907","question":"What color is a single cream dilution of chestnut?","answer":"Palomino"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2908","question":"What does it mean when we say that Palomino horses do not “breed true”?","answer":"Breeding a palomino to a palomino doesn’t always result in a palomino foal (only 50% will be palomino)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2909","question":"The palomino color is a single cream dilution of what base color?","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2910","question":"If a palomino mare were mated to a palomino stallion, what percentage of foals would be what color?","answer":"50% palomino, 25% cremello, 25% chestnut"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2911","question":"The perlino color is a double cream dilution of what base color?","answer":"Bay"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2912","question":"Which one of the following modifications of black does NOT have black points:  bay, seal brown, buckskin, dun, grulla, or perlino?","answer":"Perlino"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2913","question":"Name the 3 colors that result from dun dilutions of black, bay, and chestnut.","answer":"Black—grulla; bay—classic, coyote, or zebra dun (dun); chestnut—red dun or claybank dun"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2914","question":"What color is a dun dilution of black?","answer":"Grulla"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2915","question":"Grulla is a dun dilution of what basic coat color?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2916","question":"What color is a dun dilution of chestnut?","answer":"Red dun"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2917","question":"What is the base color of a red silver horse?","answer":"Bay (FYI: Red silver is a silver dapple dilution of bay.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2918","question":"What color would be the result of the silver dapple gene on the following 3 colors:  black, bay, and chestnut?","answer":"Black—blue silver, silver dapple, or taffy; bay—red silver; chestnut—chestnut (FYI:  Silver dapple gene only affects black areas.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2919","question":"Which is the dominant coat color, black or chestnut?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2920","question":"If a chestnut is mated to a chestnut, what color or colors can be produced?","answer":"Only chestnut (FYI: Chestnut is recessive to black.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2921","question":"What color is recessive to black and bay?","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2922","question":"2 part question:  What colors of foals would a chestnut mare produce when mated with a homozygous black stallion and when mated with a heterozygous black stallion?","answer":"When mated with a homozygous black stallion, ALL of the foals would be black; when mated with a heterozygous black stallion, half of the foals would be black and half would be chestnut"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2923","question":"In reference to coat color genetics, what is the Extension gene?","answer":"Gene that regulates black and red coloring (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2924","question":"If you breed a heterozygous black stallion to a heterozygous black mare, what percentage of the foals may be red?","answer":"25%"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2925","question":"What TWO base colors are determined by the Extension gene?","answer":"Black and red (chestnut) (FYI: Bay is an Agouti modification of black.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2926","question":"In reference to coat color genetics, what genes must a chestnut horse have?","answer":"2 (two) recessive extension genes (ee)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2927","question":"Name TWO genotypes of a black horse.","answer":"EE, Ee, aaEE, aaEe"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2928","question":"What color foal will a homozygous gray produce?","answer":"Gray (FYI: Gray is dominant to other colors.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2929","question":"The gene for what color is located at the G locus?","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2930","question":"What paint or pinto color pattern has the genetic color code for dominant white at the T locus?","answer":"Tobiano"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2931","question":"Which color can cover up or mask the colored areas of a horse?","answer":"White"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2932","question":"Why are all dominant white horses heterozygous and not homozygous?","answer":"Homozygous white fetuses die in utero (before birth)."},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"easy","number":"2933","question":"What do you call an abnormal condition that an animal possesses at birth?","answer":"Congenital"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"intermediate","number":"2934","question":"What does the term \"congenital\" mean?","answer":"Abnormal condition that an animal possesses at birth"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2935","question":"What is a genetic disease?","answer":"Disease that can be passed on to offspring (and may be the result of a genetic mutation)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2936","question":"Name 3 genetic diseases in horses.","answer":"SCID (combined immunodeficiency); HYPP; HERDA; PSSM; GBED; OLWS (overo lethal white syndrome); malignant hyperthermia; hemophilia; JEB; aniridia (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2937","question":"Aniridia is a genetic disorder in which the iris of the eye is absent.  This occurs primarily in which horse breed?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2938","question":"What term is used to describe the genetic disease characterized by the failure of the immune system to form?","answer":"Combined Immunodeficiency (CID) or Severe Combined Immunodeficiency (SCID) (FYI: CID is commonly seen in Arabians.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2939","question":"CID or Combined Immunodeficiency is an inherited disease of which breed?","answer":"Arabian or part Arab (accept either)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2940","question":"What sensory deficit is often present in horses with the splashed white color pattern?","answer":"Deafness"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2941","question":"Identify the following disease that primarily affects Quarter Horses:  superficial and deep layers of the skin separate resulting in \"stretchy\" skin that's easily damaged or torn.","answer":"HERDA (Hereditary Equine Regional Dermal Asthenia) or HC (Hyperelastosis Cutis) (accept any)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2942","question":"This disease results in “stretchy” skin due to separation of the superficial and deep layers of the skin. What breed is affected by HERDA or HC?","answer":"Quarter Horse (FYI:  HERDA stands for Hereditary Regional Dermal Asthenia.  HC stands for Hyperelastosis Cutis.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2943","question":"HERDA or HC is an inherited disorder that causes what?","answer":"Causes skin to be very stretchable, fragile, and/or vulnerable to trauma"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2944","question":"Which Quarter Horse sire has been linked to the disorder HERDA?","answer":"Poco Bueno"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2945","question":"A horse with what genetic disease would benefit from a diet that is low in potassium?","answer":"HYPP or Hyperkalemic Periodic Paralysis (also accept PIPP or Potassium Induced Periodic Paralysis)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2946","question":"HYPP is found in which Quarter Horse line?","answer":"Impressive"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2947","question":"Give ONE way to diagnose HYPP.","answer":"Genetic blood test, clinical signs, or elevated blood potassium levels (hyperkalemia)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2948","question":"How is HYPP diagnosed?","answer":"Genetic blood test (also by clinical signs and elevated blood potassium levels) [FYI:  There’s a 5-panel test that checks for the following genetic diseases—HYPP, PSSM, HERDA, GBED, and MH (malignant hyperthermia).]"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2949","question":"Which breed of horse carries the genetic disease HYPP?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2950","question":"What causes foals with Overo Lethal White Syndrome do die?","answer":"Failure of nerves in the gastrointestinal tract to develop which causes colic (FYI: Condition is called ileocolonic aganglionosis.)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2951","question":"What genetic disease is associated with the frame overo pattern?","answer":"Lethal White Foal Syndrome or OLWS (Overo Lethal White Syndrome) (accept either)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2952","question":"What do the initials OLWS refer to?","answer":"Overo Lethal White Syndrome"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2953","question":"Which lethal genetic defect can result from mating two overo Paint horses?","answer":"Lethal White Foal Syndrome or OLWS (Overo Lethal White Syndrome) (accept either)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2954","question":"What does the abbreviation PSSM indicate?","answer":"Polysaccharide Storage Myopathy (FYI: PSSM is a genetic disease of horses such as Quarter Horses that can cause \"tying up\".)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2955","question":"2 part question:  If a mare is a carrier for an X-linked genetic disease, what percent of her male foals will be affected with the disease and what percent of her female foals will be carriers?","answer":"50% males will be affected and 50% of females will be carriers"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2956","question":"On what chromosome do you find the gene for hemophilia?","answer":"X chromosome"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2957","question":"Which chromosome carries the genes for most sex-linked traits?","answer":"X chromosome"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2958","question":"What sex-linked disease results in a deficiency of clotting factor VIII (8)?","answer":"Hemophilia (Hemophilia A)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2959","question":"Are male or female horses primarily affected by genetic diseases that have an X-linked mode of inheritance?","answer":"Male horses"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2960","question":"Give ONE example of a sex-linked trait in horses.","answer":"Hemophilia"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2961","question":"Explain how mitosis (my-TOE-sis) differs from meiosis (my-OH-sis).","answer":"Mitosis is normal cell division where each daughter cell receives an identical copy of the original chromosome pairs; meiosis is sex cell division where each daughter cell only receives half of each chromosome pair (haploid number of chromosomes)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2962","question":"Name the TWO types of cell division.","answer":"Mitosis and meiosis (my-TOE-sis and my-OH-sis)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2963","question":"What is the term for sex cell division?","answer":"Meiosis (my-OH-sis)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2964","question":"What is the term for normal or somatic cell division?","answer":"Mitosis (my-TOE-sis)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2965","question":"Describe 3 steps of mitosis. (my-TOE-sis)","answer":"Chromosomes duplicate, chromosomes line up in the middle of the cell, chromosomes pull a part,  cells start to divide, cell division completes with each daughter cell receiving a complete copy of the chromosomes"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2966","question":"What are the TWO basic types of genetic action?","answer":"Qualitative and quantitative"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2967","question":"2 part question:  What is the difference between qualitative and quantitative genetic actions?","answer":"Qualitative genetic action—trait is influenced by 1 - 3 pairs of genes; quantitative genetic action—trait is influenced by a number of genes"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2968","question":"In traits affected by qualitative gene action there are 3 primary types of gene action that affect the trait.  Name them.","answer":"Dominance, co-dominance, partial dominance"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2969","question":"In what type of gene action are several genes required to produce a trait?","answer":"Quantitative"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2970","question":"2 part question:  What is a quantitative trait and give one example?","answer":"Trait influenced by many genes; examples – speed, cow sense, jumping ability"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2971","question":"What does the term “quantitative gene action” mean?","answer":"Trait is controlled by several genes"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"sr bonus","number":"2972","question":"Name 3 traits of horses that are influenced by many genes.","answer":"Conformation, temperament, physical performance, size, muscularity, longevity"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"int bonus","number":"2973","question":"Name 3 things, other than genetic makeup, that may affect a horse's potential.","answer":"Care, feeding, training, injuries (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"int bonus","number":"2974","question":"Name 3 things that should be considered when selecting breeding stock.","answer":"Conformation, breeding or pedigree, disposition, size, individual performance records, progeny records (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"int bonus","number":"2975","question":"Name TWO factors that determine how well a horse will do in a particular discipline such as horse racing.","answer":"Heredity; environment (nutrition, exercise, training, health) (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2976","question":"Is the curly coat of the American Bashkir Curly caused by a dominant or a recessive gene?","answer":"Recessive"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"medium","number":"2977","question":"Although a horse may have the genetic potential to be large, fast or intelligent, 30-50% of the trait is due to what?","answer":"Environmental factors (such as feed, care, training and injuries)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2978","question":"What is gene mapping?","answer":"Determining and recording the identities and positions of genes"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2979","question":"What is “heritability estimate”?","answer":"Percentage of the horse’s expressed trait that is due to genetics (probability of that trait being passed from one generation to the next)"},
{"category":"Genetics","level":"hard","number":"2980","question":"Justin Morgan was the foundation sire for the Morgan breed. His ability to pass his breed type on to his offspring regardless of the type of mare he was bred to would be referred to by what genetics term?","answer":"Prepotent or prepotency (accept either) "},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"jr bonus","number":"2981","question":"Name 3 grooming tools and give their purposes.","answer":"Curry comb—removes deep dirt; dandy or stiff brush—removes dirt; body brush—removes dust and brings out oils; face brush—brush face; mane and tail comb—comb mane and tail; hoof pick—clean hooves"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2982","question":"Name 3 grooming tools.","answer":"Currycomb, dandy or stiff brush, body or soft brush, face brush, mane and tail comb, hoof pick, grooming cloth, sweat scraper, clippers"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2983","question":"Name the final touch to the horse's appearance before entering the show ring.","answer":"Going over the coat with a grooming cloth"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"sr bonus","number":"2984","question":"Name 3 uses of a grooming cloth.","answer":"Polish coat, dry off wet horse, wipe around eyes, nostrils, lips, dock, sheath"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2985","question":"What is a rubber currycomb used for?","answer":"To remove deep dirt, loose hair, saddle marks, mud (accept any)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2986","question":"What is the only reason to use a metal currycomb?","answer":"To remove thick, dry mud or heavy, loose hair"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2987","question":"Why should you NOT use a currycomb on your horse's face or legs?","answer":"You might hurt him (there's less muscle to protect horse from injury)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2988","question":"What motion is most effective when using a currycomb?","answer":"Circular motion"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2989","question":"Which grooming tool roughs up the hair to remove the deep dirt?","answer":"Currycomb"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2990","question":"How do you clean the currycomb when grooming?","answer":"Hit it on something hard or pull the hair out (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2991","question":"What grooming tool is used in a circular motion to loosen hair and dirt?","answer":"Currycomb"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2992","question":"In grooming a horse, where is the currycomb NEVER used?","answer":"Over the bony areas (head and lower legs)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2993","question":"What type of brush is best for sensitive areas of the face and legs?","answer":"Soft brush"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2994","question":"Name ONE function of the body or soft brush.","answer":"Removes the last particles of dust or brings out natural oils"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2995","question":"What is the name for the soft brush with fine bristles that's used to give your horse a finishing touch?","answer":"Body brush, soft brush, or finishing brush (accept any)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2996","question":"2 part question:  What is a dandy brush and what is it used for?","answer":"Stiff brush; used to remove loose hair and dirt"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"2997","question":"What type strokes will remove the most dirt when using a stiff or dandy brush?","answer":"Short, strong strokes with an outward motion away from the body"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2998","question":"What grooming tool is a hard bristled brush used to remove excess hair and loose dirt?","answer":"Dandy brush (stiff brush)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"2999","question":"What grooming aid is used to remove excess water after washing your horse?","answer":"Sweat scraper"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3000","question":"How can bathing your horse dull his coat?","answer":"Removes the skin's natural oils"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3001","question":"How can you remove caked mud and manure from the hoof wall?","answer":"Wash with water and use a stiff brush or use a hoof brush (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"jr bonus","number":"3002","question":"When brushing a horse, what are the LAST 3 parts to be brushed?","answer":"Head, mane, and tail"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"jr bonus","number":"3003","question":"Name 3 important steps in grooming a horse.","answer":"Use curry comb on non-bony parts of body, use stiff brush, use body brush, use face brush, comb mane and tail, clean feet, use grooming cloth, groom before and after riding, cool horse out after exercise"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3004","question":"What practice most helps the appearance of the horse's coat?","answer":"Frequent, thorough grooming"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3005","question":"Why should you brush the horse's belly in the area of the saddle cinch?","answer":"To remove dirt that might chafe the horse or cause sores (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3006","question":"Ideally, how often should horses be groomed?","answer":"Daily"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3007","question":"In grooming a horse, in what direction should the hair be brushed?","answer":"In the direction of its natural lay (in the direction it grows)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3008","question":"Why is it recommended to groom a horse thoroughly before saddling?","answer":"Removes dirt or burrs that might cause sores; you may find new sores (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3009","question":"Give TWO times you should groom a horse that you are exercising.","answer":"Both before and after the workout"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3010","question":"How can you avoid a dull, sunburned appearance to your horse's coat?","answer":"Keep him stabled during the sunniest part of the day or only turn him out to pasture in the early morning or late evening (accept either)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"sr bonus","number":"3011","question":"Name 3 benefits of grooming your horse.","answer":"Improves appearance, cleans hair and skin, brings out natural oils in skin, prevents skin problems, looks for skin problems, massages muscles, increases circulation, removes dirt and external parasites, improves muscle condition"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3012","question":"Give ONE reason why horse's legs should be clipped a couple of weeks before a show.","answer":"To avoid clipper lines or contrasting colors"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3013","question":"To obtain a neat look, which way should clippers be run, against the hair or with the natural lay?","answer":"With the natural lay"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"jr bonus","number":"3014","question":"Name 3 areas of the Western stock horse that are usually clipped for a show.","answer":"Muzzle, under chin, under jaw, bridle path, ears, long hairs around eyes, below knees and hocks"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"3015","question":"When clipping a horse during the winter, why is it advisable to leave an unclipped area for the saddle blanket?","answer":"To protect the horse's back (from abrasions)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"3016","question":"Why is the hair often clipped around the fetlocks of certain breeds?","answer":"To give the legs a neater or cleaner appearance"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3017","question":"What does it mean to body clip a horse?","answer":"Clipping the horse's entire body"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3018","question":"If you body clip your horse, how can you keep him warm in cold weather?","answer":"Blanket him or keep him in a stable (accept either)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"hard","number":"3019","question":"Clipping along the belly, under the neck, and above the thigh is known as what type of body clip?","answer":"Trace clip"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"hard","number":"3020","question":"When a horse has a blanket clip, which parts of the horse are NOT clipped?","answer":"Head, neck, and legs (FYI: With a blanket clip, only the blanket area is clipped.)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"sr bonus","number":"3021","question":"Name 3 types of clips used in grooming horses.","answer":"Blanket clip, trace clip, body clip, hunter clip"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3022","question":"What is docking?","answer":"Cutting the bones of the tail to shorten it"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3023","question":"What term is used for the cutting of the bones of the tail in order to shorten the tail?","answer":"Docking (docked)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"sr bonus","number":"3024","question":"Name 3 effects of hand rubbing your horse.","answer":"Brings out the bloom or shine, stimulates circulation, massages tired muscles, feels good to the horse, helps you bond with your horse (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3025","question":"What is meant by \"picking out\" a mane or tail?","answer":"Separating the hairs with your fingers to keep them from tangling"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"3026","question":"Describe how to pluck or pull a mane.","answer":"Begin on underside of mane with the longest hairs; grasp a few strands of hair close to the roots and jerk sharply removing hair and roots"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3027","question":"When braiding a horse's mane and tail, how many sections should be worked with at one time?","answer":"3 (three) sections"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"3028","question":"Why do some gaited saddle horses have their bridle paths trimmed 6 - 7 inches down the neck?","answer":"To make the horse's neck look longer and finer through the throatlatch"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3029","question":"In reference to grooming, what is a \"bridle path\"?","answer":"Clipped area behind the ears where the crownpiece of the bridle goes"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3030","question":"What is the name for the section of mane at the poll that's trimmed or clipped to allow space for a halter or bridle to rest?","answer":"Bridle path"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3031","question":"How long an area is clipped for the bridle path?","answer":"1½ - 8 inches depending on the breed and style of riding (accept any number within this range) (also accept the length of the ear)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3032","question":"In reference to grooming, what does the term \"hogged\" mean?","answer":"Mane that's cut short or shaved off"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3033","question":"How long is a hogged mane?","answer":"3 (three) inches or less (FYI: Roached mane is clipped close to the skin.)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3034","question":"In reference to grooming, what is roached?","answer":"Mane shaved off or cut short (left standing upright; another name for hogged)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"3035","question":"How are the manes and tails of Arabians prepared for a show?","answer":"Washed and left full"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"3036","question":"What determines the style of the mane and tail of a horse that's being exhibited?","answer":"Breed of horse and/or what type of classes it’s being shown in"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3037","question":"In reference to grooming, what is a banged tail?","answer":"Hair cut straight off below the dock or bony part of the tail"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3038","question":"How far down the tail is a hunter's tail braided?","answer":"8 - 12 inches (accept any number within this range) (also accept to the end of the tail bone)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"hard","number":"3039","question":"How are the tails of Hackney Ponies groomed for Harness classes versus Hackney classes?","answer":"Long tail in Harness classes; cob tail in Hackney classes"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3040","question":"What is the method by which you thin a tail?","answer":"Pulling"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3041","question":"What do you call a tail that's been shortened or thinned by pulling?","answer":"Pulled tail"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3042","question":"What is a rat-tailed horse?","answer":"Horse having little hair in its tail (can be seen in Appaloosas)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3043","question":"When applying a wrap to a horse's tail, why is it important not to pull the wrap too tight?","answer":"You can cut off circulation to the tail"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"3044","question":"What is the term that refers to hair that's clean and glossy, denoting a healthy appearance?","answer":"Bloom"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"medium","number":"3045","question":"In reference to horses, what is meant by the term \"bloom\"?","answer":"Glossy, healthy looking hair coat (luster or shine to coat)"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3046","question":"What is the term for rough, harsh appearance?","answer":"Coarse"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"easy","number":"3047","question":"Give ONE meaning for the term \"curry\".","answer":"Rubber or metal grooming tool; to rub down or groom a horse"},
{"category":"Grooming","level":"novice","number":"3048","question":"What do you call a person who cleans and brushes horses?","answer":"Groom"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3049","question":"What is the key to applying a good bandage?","answer":"Practice"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3050","question":"What type scissors are best for cutting hair away from a wound?","answer":"Blunt end ones (bandage scissors)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3051","question":"Why should leg bandages be wrapped in a spiral fashion from front to back?","answer":"To decrease damage of tendons, nerves, and blood vessels (to decrease the risk of uneven tension on the back of the leg)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3052","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen if a leg bandage is applied with too much tension.","answer":"Can cut off blood supply; can damage tissues (such as tendons)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3053","question":"Most medically indicated bandages have how many layers?","answer":"3 (three) layers"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3054","question":"Name ONE material used for each of the 3 bandage layers.","answer":"Primary or contact layer—Telfa or non-stick pad, release pad, gauze pad; secondary layer—sheet cotton, roll cotton, quilted leg wraps; outer or tertiary layer—vet wrap, Elasticon"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3055","question":"Why should you NOT use cotton or material with loose fibers to wrap a wound?","answer":"Sticks to wound"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3056","question":"Give ONE purpose of the secondary bandage layer.","answer":"Absorbs fluids from wound; provides padding"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3057","question":"Give ONE purpose of the outer bandage layer.","answer":"Holds other layers in place; keeps other layers clean"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3058","question":"Give ONE reason why you would use a HOT poultice on your horse.","answer":"Increase blood supply to the injured area; draw out infection from abscess or puncture wound"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3059","question":"Give ONE reason why you would use a COLD poultice on your horse.","answer":"Decrease inflammation or swelling caused by kick or blow, reduce swelling, heat, or pain of contusion (bruise) or hematoma"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3060","question":"Give 3 uses for a poultice.","answer":"Increase blood supply to area, draw out infection, encourage abscess to open, decrease inflammation"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3061","question":"Name 3 general types of bandages.","answer":"Support, shipping, first aid"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3062","question":"Give 3 purposes of bandaging.","answer":"Support, keep wound clean; protect from infection, dirt, or insects; protect from further trauma, absorbs drainage, travel protection, immobilization, control bleeding, reduce swelling, keeps medication on wound"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3063","question":"What is the purpose of a pressure bandage?","answer":"Control bleeding (also accept decrease swelling)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3064","question":"What is the correct term for a thick, multi-layered bandage that includes wood or metal splints and is used to restrain and support an injured leg?","answer":"Robert Jones bandage"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3065","question":"A horse's body fat can be estimated by using the BCS method of evaluation.  What do the initials BCS stand for?","answer":"Body condition scoring (FYI:  BCS is determined by observing and feeling the fat cover over 6 body sites—back, ribs at mid-barrel, neck, behind the shoulders at the fore-rib, withers, and tail head.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3066","question":"When determining body condition in the winter, it's easy to be misled by what?","answer":"Horse's winter coat or long hair"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3067","question":"A method of assessing a horse's body condition by visually appraising or physically feeling fat cover in several areas is called what?","answer":"Body condition scoring"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3068","question":"In reference to “Body Condition Score”, name 3 of the body sites that are evaluated.","answer":"Neck, withers, back, tail head, behind the shoulder at fore rib, ribs at mid-barrel"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3069","question":"A horse with a body condition score of 9 would be considered to be what?","answer":"Obese"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3070","question":"What is the ideal body condition score for most horses?","answer":"4 - 6 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3071","question":"Give the body condition score for this horse:  slight fat cover over the ribs, but the ribs are easily seen; hook bones appear rounded, but are visible; tail head is prominent; withers, shoulders, and neck are accentuated.","answer":"Body Condition Score of 3 (three)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3072","question":"Give the body condition score for this horse:  prominent crease down the back; ribs are difficult to feel; fat around the tail head is soft; area behind the shoulder is filled; neck is thickened; fat is deposited along the withers and inner buttocks.","answer":"Body Condition Score of 8 (eight)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3073","question":"Give the body condition score of this horse:  topline is level; ribs can be felt, but not seen.","answer":"Body Condition Score of 5 (five)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3074","question":"Racehorses and endurance horses are sometimes maintained at a BCS score of less than 5, yet they are healthy.  Why would you NOT want to maintain a highly competitive horse at a higher BCS score?","answer":"Horse would be carrying extra, unnecessary weight"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3075","question":"Name TWO things that would affect a horse’s body condition or degree of fat covering. ","answer":"Diet; amount of exercise;  pregnancy; lactation; weather changes; parasites; dental problems; overall health; feeding practices; availability of food (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3076","question":"Name ONE reason, other than being overfed, that horses or ponies might get fat.","answer":"High grain diet, unlimited pasture, lack of exercise, easy keepers, dominant horse in herd, Cushing's disease (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"novice","number":"3077","question":"Name ONE thing you can do to help your horse lose weight.","answer":"Increase exercise or decrease calories"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3078","question":"Name 3 health problems that can be caused by overfeeding horses.","answer":"Weight gain, laminitis or founder, colic, infertility, hyperlipidemia, heat stress, respiratory problems (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3079","question":"How many POUNDS can an obese horse safely lose in one month?","answer":"50 pounds"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3080","question":"Give 3 reasons, other than being overfed, that horses or ponies might get fat.","answer":"High grain diet, unlimited pasture, lack of exercise, easy keepers, dominant horse in herd, Cushing's disease (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3081","question":"What does the term \"emaciated\" mean?","answer":"Extremely thin (Body condition score of less than 3)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3082","question":"What is the best approach for rehabilitating a starved horse?","answer":"Feed small, frequent meals of high quality alfalfa for 1st 10 days, then increase hay amounts slowly to free choice.  Grain not recommended until horse is near normal weight"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3083","question":"When a horse loses more than 50% of his body weight, what is the prognosis for recovery?","answer":"Very poor prognosis"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3084","question":"Name ONE cause of starvation in horses.","answer":"Unintentional neglect, intentional neglect, abandoned, ignorance of horse care, economic hardship of owner"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3085","question":"How much time is generally required to get a starved horse back to normal body weight?","answer":"3 - 5 months"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3086","question":"What is the MOST ACCURATE way to weigh your horse?","answer":"Scales"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3087","question":"How is a tape used to estimate the weight of a horse?","answer":"Measure the horse's heart girth with a marked weight tape"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3088","question":"What is the MOST COMMON way to estimate your horse's weight?","answer":"Weight tape (also accept visual estimation or guessing)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3089","question":"Give ONE reason why you should know your horse's weight.","answer":"So you know how much to feed your horse, know how much wormer to give your horse or know how medicine to give your horse"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3090","question":"Name 3 ways to determine a horse's weight.","answer":"Livestock scales, weight tape, visual estimation (guessing), body weight equation (FYI:  Body Weight Equation, height in inches x body length in inches, sum of those divided by 330 = body weight.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3091","question":"What is the term for the condition in which water is lost from the body faster than it's taken in?","answer":"Dehydration"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3092","question":"Skin pliability is a test for what?","answer":"Dehydration"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3093","question":"What is dehydration?","answer":"Condition of the body where more water is lost than is taken in (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3094","question":"How do you check for dehydration in a horse?","answer":"Pull the skin back; if it quickly flaps back into place, the horse isn't dehydrated"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3095","question":"What is the best way to prevent dehydration?","answer":"Make sure your horse in drinking enough water"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3096","question":"Name 3 paths of physiological water loss from a horse’s body.","answer":"Urine, sweat, feces, respiration"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3097","question":"Under NORMAL conditions, what's the best way to replenish your horse's electrolytes?","answer":"Provide a salt or mineral block"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3098","question":"Where is the greatest amount of electrolytes lost?","answer":"Sweat"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3099","question":"For what purpose is the drug Acepromazine used?","answer":"Tranquilizer or sedative (accept either)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3100","question":"What is the correct term for the medication referred to as “Ace”?","answer":"Acetyl promazine (acepromazine)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3101","question":"How is a sublingual medication given?","answer":"Under the tongue"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3102","question":"What are you doing if you are \"drenching\" a horse?","answer":"Giving liquid medication to the horse by pouring it down its throat from a bottle"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3103","question":"What do you call a liquid introduced into the intestine by way of the anus?","answer":"Enema"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3104","question":"What is the name for the syringe-like device used to give large pills to horses?","answer":"Balling gun"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3105","question":"What is a bolus?","answer":"Rounded mass of food or medicine given orally (FYI:  A \"bolus\" of an IV medication can also be given.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3106","question":"2 part question:  Name 3 types of injections and identify the location where they're given.","answer":"SubQ (subcutaneous)—under the skin; IM (intramuscular)—in the muscle; IV (intravenous)—into a vein; intradermal—into the skin; intra-articular—into a joint"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3107","question":"Where is a subcutaneous shot administered?","answer":"Under the skin (FYI:  Sub means under and cutaneous is related to the skin.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3108","question":"What is the general term for a drug that causes the air passages of the lungs to widen?","answer":"Bronchodilator"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3109","question":"Identify this medication:  used to treat severe asthma or anaphylactic reactions; causes contraction of the capillaries and arteries by stimulating the sympathetic nervous system; causes an increase in the heart rate.","answer":"Adrenalin or epinephrine (accept either)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3110","question":"What is immunotherapy?","answer":"Stimulating the immune system as a treatment for tumors or allergies"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3111","question":"What is the term for a chemical substance that inhibits or destroys bacteria or other microorganisms and is used primarily in the treatment of infectious diseases?","answer":"Antibiotic"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3112","question":"An antibiotic is used to control what type of infections?","answer":"Bacterial infections (FYI: Antibiotics are also used to treat some protozoal infections; antibiotics do NOT treat viral infections.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3113","question":"What medication is used to treat bradycardia?","answer":"Atropine (FYI: Bradycardia is a slower than normal heart rate.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3114","question":"What does the drug Lasix treat in racehorses?","answer":"Exercise Induced Pulmonary Hemorrhage"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3115","question":"What type of drug increases the excretion of urine after administration?","answer":"Diuretic"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3116","question":"What is an astringent?","answer":"Drug that causes constriction of tissues and/or decreases secretions (examples: tannic acid, alum, zinc oxide)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3117","question":"What is the term for a liquid medication that is applied to the horse’s legs after exercise to prevent swelling and to reduce soreness?","answer":"Brace, liniment, or astringent (accept any)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3118","question":"Name ONE thing an anti-inflammatory drug does.","answer":"Decreases inflammation, reduces pain, reduces swelling, antipyretic (fever reducer)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3119","question":"What type of medications are Flunixin (floo-NIX-in) meglumine (MEG-glue-mean), Ketoprofen (kee-toe-PRO-fen), and Phenylbutazone (feen-ill-BUTE-ah-zone)?","answer":"NSAID's (non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3120","question":"What is the expected effect of an antipyretic medication?","answer":"Fever reduction"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3121","question":"What is the chemical name for the anti-inflammatory drug Bute?","answer":"Phenylbutazone"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3122","question":"What is the COMMON name for the drug Phenylbutazone?","answer":"Bute"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3123","question":"What is the correct term for the medication referred to as DMSO?","answer":"Dimethyl sulfoxide [FYI:  DMSO can be used orally, topically, or through an IV as an anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, or analgesic (pain killer).]"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3124","question":"Give TWO medical properties or uses for Dimethyl Sulfoxide or DMSO.","answer":"Anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, analgesic"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3125","question":"What term describes a preparation that contains no medication and is administered in order to simulate treatment such as in a research study?","answer":"Placebo"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3126","question":"There are no specific treatments for some poisonings, but horses are usually given activated charcoal and a saline laxative by nasogastric tube.  What is the reason for giving these medications?","answer":"To prevent further absorption of the toxin (FYI: Activated charcoal binds with the toxin and the saline laxative speeds up the passage of toxins through the digestive tract.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3127","question":"What is the name of the medication that's used to counteract a poison?","answer":"Antidote"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3128","question":"What is the use of a prophylactic medication?","answer":"To prevent illness or disease"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3129","question":"A soluble-fiber, bulk agent such as Metamucil or Psyllium would be administered to a horse with diarrhea that is a result of what type of ingestion?","answer":"Sand ingestion"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3130","question":"What is silver nitrate?","answer":"Medication used to stop bleeding or as an antiseptic)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3131","question":"What substance can be applied topically to control bleeding?","answer":"Silver nitrate"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3132","question":"Give ONE purpose of a correct use of a steroid medication.","answer":"Control inflammation; suppress allergic reaction"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3133","question":"What is stocking up?","answer":"Swelling of the lower legs of the horse (FYI: When horses stand still for long periods, fluid can accumulate below the knees and hocks.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3134","question":"What term describes an accumulation of abnormally large amounts of fluid in the horse's body tissue?","answer":"Edema (FYI: \"Stocking up\" is edema of the lower legs.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3135","question":"Name ONE cause of electric shock in horses.","answer":"Lightning, contact with overhead wires, contact with wire fencing, chewing through wires, contact with other sources of electric current (especially if ground is wet)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3136","question":"Name 3 symptoms common to horses who have survived an electric shock.","answer":"Dazed, unconscious, abnormal breathing, weak or slow pulse, dilated or constricted eyes, convulsions, paralysis"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3137","question":"2 part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using a barbiturate overdose for euthanasia.","answer":"Advantages—speed of action, minimal discomfort for horse; disadvantages—requires IV, so horse must be restrained"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3138","question":"What is the correct medical term used to describe the humane or painless death of an animal through the action of a person, usually a veterinarian?","answer":"Euthanasia"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3139","question":"What are the only 3 acceptable methods of euthanasia for a horse?","answer":"Overdose of barbiturates, gunshot, captive bolt"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3140","question":"Give ONE result of NOT exercising your horse.  ","answer":"Weight gain, lameness, stiffness, colic, stable vices, nervousness, loss of cardiovascular fitness, loss of muscle tone, stocking up (swelling) (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3141","question":"How often should horses be ridden or turned out to free exercise?","answer":"At least once daily"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3142","question":"Name 3 things that can happen if horses are confined and can't exercise.","answer":"Loss of cardiovascular fitness, loss of muscle tone, stiffness, lameness, colic, stocking up (swelling of the legs), become nervous, develop stable vices, gain weight"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3143","question":"Name 3 problems that can occur when working an out of condition horse.","answer":"Laminitis or founder, heat exhaustion, exhaustion, heart attack, stroke, lameness, tying up, muscle soreness (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3144","question":"Give TWO ways to increase exercise for horses with chronic lameness.","answer":"Turn out into large paddock or pasture, provide companion, locate feed and water sources far apart, hand walk, swimming"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3145","question":"All eye injuries should be treated as what?","answer":"Emergencies; call the vet!"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3146","question":"What is a corneal ulcer?","answer":"Abrasion, tear, or ulcer of the cornea (accept any) (FYI: Corneal ulcers are caused by trauma and may lead to infection and blindness.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3147","question":"2 part question:  All corneal ulcers should be considered emergencies.  Describe the difference between a simple and a complicated corneal ulcer and give the main treatments for each.","answer":"Simple is superficial and is not infected; treat with topical antibiotics and pain medications; complicated is deep and is infected; treat with antibiotics and pain medications plus it may require surgery"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3148","question":"Give ONE good reason for keeping your horse first aid supplies in a small waterproof box.","answer":"Supplies stay clean and dry; it can be taken with the horse when it travels from home"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3149","question":"What is the name of the aluminum or wooden device worn around the neck of a horse to prevent it from chewing at sores, blankets, or bandages?","answer":"Neck cradle or cradle (Do NOT accept cribbing collar.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3150","question":"What is the term for removal of foreign material and damaged or dead tissue from a wound?","answer":"Debridement (de-BRIDE-ment or de-BREED-ment)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3151","question":"What is the vet doing if he's lavaging your horse's wound? (luh-VAH-zching)","answer":"Washing the wound with a stream of fluid"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3152","question":"Name 3 items found in an equine first aid kit. PART OF THE ANSWER DO NOT READ:  marker, pen and paper, watch, weight tape, flash light and spare batteries, duct tape, small container to hold or mix solutions, hoof pick, hoof knife, syringe, pliers","answer":"Antiseptic, scissors, hemostats, thermometer, stethoscope, nonstick pads, gauze, sheet cotton, quilted cotton, elasticon tape, vet wrap, antibiotic ointment, eye wash, saline rinse, Bute, Banamine, surgical scrub (Betadine), disposable gloves"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3153","question":"Why are ointments less effective in warm weather?","answer":"Heat will cause the ointment to melt (and to escape from wound or bandage)."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3154","question":"What is the reason for NOT treating fibular fractures unless bone fragments need to be surgically removed?","answer":"Tibia acts as a splint and no lameness is involved."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3155","question":"How would you keep a horse with a broken leg on the ground until the vet arrives?","answer":"Sit on its neck and apply pressure to the head"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3156","question":"When can a horse with a fractured limb be moved?","answer":"After a splint has been applied or after evaluation by a vet (accept either)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3157","question":"What do you call the type of bone fracture that breaks the skin?","answer":"Compound fracture (also accept open fracture)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3158","question":"Which is more serious, heat exhaustion or heat stroke?","answer":"Heat stroke"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3159","question":"Under what conditions is the horse's cooling ability significantly reduced to the point where it can be fatal if the horse is stressed?","answer":"When the sum of the temperature and the relative humidity is greater than 180"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3160","question":"Give 3 signs of heat stroke in the horse.","answer":"Rapid breathing, weakness, incoordination, refusal to work, depressed, unwilling to drink, poor gut sounds, high heart rate, high respiratory rate"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3161","question":"Name 3 causes of hyperthermia in horses.","answer":"Hot weather; high humidity; poor stable ventilation; prolonged exposure to direct sunlight; overwork; transportation; obesity; genetic (malignant hyperthermia) [accept any correct answers]"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"novice","number":"3162","question":"Name ONE way to cool out a horse besides walking it.","answer":"Spray him with a hose, sponge him down, give him a couple swallows of water every few minutes"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3163","question":"Name 3 things you can do for an overheated horse.","answer":"Call vet, spray with water, put horse in shade, use fans, put ice on horse, give a few swallows of water (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3164","question":"How soon should a horse with heat exhaustion respond to cooling efforts?","answer":"10 - 15 minutes (FYI: horse will continue to appear very tired, but it should be willing to eat and drink)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3165","question":"What kind of fluid should you give a horse suffering from heat cramps?","answer":"Electrolyte solution (water with electrolytes)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3166","question":"What mammal other than a horse cools itself primarily by sweating?","answer":"Man"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3167","question":"How does sweating cool the horse's body?","answer":"Sweat is evaporated from the horse’s body which cools the horse."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3168","question":"What part of the horse is inflamed with desmitis?","answer":"Ligament"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3169","question":"What is an inflammation of the endometrium called? (in-doe-MEE-tree-um)","answer":"Endometritis (in-doe-mee-TRITE-is)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3170","question":"What is the general term for inflammation of a tendon?","answer":"Tendonitis"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3171","question":"Name 3 signs of inflammation.","answer":"Heat, pain, swelling, redness"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"novice","number":"3172","question":"Who is trained and skilled in the treatment of diseases and injuries of animals?","answer":"Veterinarian"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3173","question":"What is the term for the condition of a horse that is healthy, active, and vigorous?","answer":"Thrifty"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3174","question":"Besides vital signs, name 3 things to consider when evaluating the health of a horse.","answer":"Body condition score; weight; skin and coat condition; skin pliability (check for dehydration); behavior (alert, content, “acting right\"); feeding habits; hoof condition;  movement; lameness; flexibility; soreness; body fluids (urine, feces)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3175","question":"What is a pre-purchase exam?","answer":"Exam made by a veterinarian to determine overall soundness and health of a horse prior to a sale transaction"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3176","question":"You do the math…Approximately 75 percent of a horse's total bodyweight is made up of water.  If your horse weighs 1000 pounds, how much of this total weight is water?","answer":"750 pounds (1000 x 0.75 = 750)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3177","question":"What is an adhesion?","answer":"When structures that normally move freely from each other stick together"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3178","question":"How many years of an equine's life are equal to one year of a human's life?","answer":"3 (three) years"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3179","question":"Give 3 signs of old age in the horse.","answer":"Gray hairs, deep depressions above the eyes, swayback, drooping lower lip, weight loss, arthritis, coarser hair coat, teeth (angle of incidence of teeth, Galvayne's groove, etc.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3180","question":"Give TWO reasons why horses live longer today than in the past.","answer":"Horses aren't worked as hard; horses generally receive better care."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3181","question":"What is anhidrosis?","answer":"Inability to sweat"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3182","question":"What does the term \"biosecurity\" mean?","answer":"Protecting living things from infectious agents"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3183","question":"What is the COMMON term for a localized thickening of the outer layer of the skin due to repeated friction or pressure?","answer":"Callus"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3184","question":"Why is it necessary to know the normal parameters for your horse's vital signs and behavior?","answer":"So you'll know when something's wrong"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3185","question":"Name 3 things you should do to keep your horse in year-round good health.","answer":"Feed properly, take care of feet, regular exercise, deworm, provide shelter, provide clean water, vaccinate (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3186","question":"What term refers to a horse that's fallen or is lying down too close to a wall or fence to get up without assistance?","answer":"Cast"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3187","question":"What is the term for the lodgment of a foreign particle, such as a blood clot or air bubble, in the circulatory system?","answer":"Embolism"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3188","question":"What is an embolism?","answer":"Lodgment of a foreign particle (such as an air bubble or blood clot) in the circulatory system"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3189","question":"Equine sweat is hypertonic.  What does this mean?","answer":"Contains a significant amount of salts"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3190","question":"What is an ion? (EYE-on)","answer":"Atom with an electrical charge"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3191","question":"What is necrosis?","answer":"Death of cells or body tissue while animal is still alive"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3192","question":"What is the purpose of a neurectomy?","answer":"Eliminate pain reception from a body part"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3193","question":"What is the term for cutting the digital nerve to relieve pain?","answer":"Nerving (neurectomy)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3194","question":"An excessive reaction of the skin to sunlight is called what?","answer":"Photosensitivity"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3195","question":"What is the term meaning the prospect of recovery from an injury or disease?","answer":"Prognosis"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3196","question":"What is a spasm?","answer":"Sudden involuntary contractions of a muscle or group of muscles"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3197","question":"Shivering is what type of involuntary physiological response?","answer":"Spasmodic muscle contractions"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3198","question":"What do you call the spasmodic muscle contractions that produce heat in cold weather?","answer":"Shivering"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3199","question":"What do you call the occupational field that emphasizes conditioning, measuring fitness and improving rehabilitation techniques of the horse?","answer":"Equine Sports Medicine"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3200","question":"Equine swimming pools have become popular for conditioning horses.  Name 3 ways in which swimming helps horses improve their condition.","answer":"Improves cardiovascular health; increases respiratory function; increases muscle tone; decreases stress on feet and legs"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3201","question":"What is the proper name for a small sac or blister containing fluid?","answer":"Vesicle (also accept cyst)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3202","question":"Blood is pulled from the peripheral circulation to the internal vital organs in a horse with shock.  How would this physiological process affect the capillary refill time?","answer":"Delayed or slower"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3203","question":"Name 3 symptoms of shock.","answer":"Loss of color of mucous membranes, decreased temperature of extremities, feeble or rapid pulse, decreased or shallow breathing, restlessness, anxiety, loss of blood volume/pressure, inability to stand, sometimes unconscious"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3204","question":"What is the name for the radiopaque dye material given to a horse by mouth to outline the digestive tract on radiographs or X-rays?","answer":"Barium"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3205","question":"What is the term used for a diagnosis based on signs or symptoms?","answer":"Clinical diagnosis"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3206","question":"In reference to medical tests, what do the letters ECG stand for?","answer":"Electrocardiogram"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3207","question":"What is the name for the medical instrument used in the examination of the interior of a hollow organ such as the stomach?","answer":"Endoscope"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3208","question":"In reference to horse health, what is the purpose of a flexion test?","answer":"To determine the flexibility of a joint"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3209","question":"What is the name of this test:  forcibly flexing a joint for 30 - 60 seconds, then jogging the horse?","answer":"Flexion test"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3210","question":"What is the hematocrit?","answer":"Percent of red blood cells in the blood"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3211","question":"What is the COMMON term for measuring the hematocrit or percent of red blood cells?","answer":"Blood count"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3212","question":"What is the term for passage of a tube into either the trachea or the esophagus?","answer":"Intubation (in-tube-AY-shun)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3213","question":"2 part question:  Medically speaking, what is a block and why would one be used?","answer":"Anesthetic injection used to numb certain parts of the body; used to detect the location of lameness and is used for standing surgeries"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3214","question":"What procedure is being described?  Anesthetic injections are given to numb certain parts of the body.  This is used to diagnose the location of lameness or to facilitate standing surgeries.","answer":"Nerve block (also accept local anesthesia)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3215","question":"How can you evaluate back or loin soreness?","answer":"Use thumb and forefinger on each side of withers to apply gentle pressure; move fingers down the back; if the horse is sore; it will drop its back away from the pressure in that area"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3216","question":"What TWO internal body parts are associated with the condition called \"thumps\"?","answer":"Diaphragm and heart"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3217","question":"Why do horses in endurance races often get thumps?","answer":"Decreased blood levels of potassium (or electrolytes)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3218","question":"What are movements of the flank in sync with the heartbeat called that often indicate an electrolyte imbalance?","answer":"Thumps or synchronous diaphragmatic flutter (accept either)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3219","question":"What is the COMMON name for synchronous diaphragmatic flutters?","answer":"Thumps"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3220","question":"What is the normal color of a horse's urine?","answer":"Clear yellow to orange"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3221","question":"Why would the urine of horses fed legume hay smell stronger than the urine of horses fed grass hay?","answer":"Legume hay has more protein so more nitrogen is excreted in the urine."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3222","question":"What would brownish-green urine indicate?","answer":"Jaundice; azoturia, tying-up, or Monday Morning Sickness (accept any)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3223","question":"2 part question:  The color of a horse's urine can indicate health problems.  Name 3 of these problems and give the accompanying urine color.","answer":"Red—bleeding in urinary tract; brownish green—jaundice or liver problems; dark brown or coffee colored—azoturia or tying up"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"novice","number":"3224","question":"How often should horses be immunized for Tetanus, Eastern, and Western Encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Annually (once a year)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3225","question":"How many doses of a vaccine are initially needed to get an adequate immune response?","answer":"2 (two) doses"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3226","question":"Name 3 immunizations given a horse annually as standard procedure.","answer":"Tetanus, West Nile, EEE (Easter Equine Encephalomyelitis), WEE (Western Equine Encephalomyelitis), rhino (rhinopneumonitis), flu (influenza)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3227","question":"Why is vaccinating your horse after he's been exposed to a disease not very effective?","answer":"It doesn't give the horse enough time to develop immunity (to prevent the disease)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3228","question":"Who developed an Anthrax vaccine in 1881?","answer":"Louis Pasteur"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3229","question":"Why is the anthrax vaccine not readily available in the US?","answer":"Anthrax is not very common."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3230","question":"Name 3 of the 5 vaccinations in the AVMA \"core\" group.","answer":"Tetanus, West Nile, EEE (Eastern Equine Encephalomyelitis), WEE (Western Equine Encephalomyelitis), Rabies"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3231","question":"The American Veterinary Medical Association (AVMA) divides vaccinations into TWO categories.  What are they?","answer":"Core and risk-based"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3232","question":"According to the AVMA, vaccinations that protect from diseases that are endemic to a region, with potential public health significance, required by law, highly infectious and/or pose a risk of severe disease are called what?","answer":"Core vaccines"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3233","question":"Name 3 diseases whose vaccinations are considered in the AVMA \"at risk\" group.","answer":"Equine Herpes (rhino, rhinopneumonitis), flu (influenza), strangles, botulism,  equine viral arteritis, Potomac Horse Fever, rotaviral diarrhea, anthrax"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3234","question":"What is a vaccination?","answer":"Substance that artificially stimulates immunity (the production of antibodies) in an animal (without giving the animal the disease)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3235","question":"What is a bacterin vaccine?","answer":"Type of vaccine made of killed bacteria (or live attenuated bacteria) stimulates the animal's immunity"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3236","question":"SPECIFICALLY, what is the name of the immune-stimulating product that's made from killed or live attenuated BACTERIA?","answer":"Bacterin (FYI: Bacterin is a type of vaccine.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3237","question":"Medically speaking, what is a \"booster\"?","answer":"Second or subsequent dose of a vaccine"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3238","question":"What is necessary for the prevention of Eastern, Western, and Venezuelan Encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Vaccination or use of insecticides (accept either)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3239","question":"You should vaccinate your mare for Tetanus, WEE, EEE and Influenza approximately how long before foaling in order to build antibodies that'll be transferred to the foal?","answer":"4 - 6 weeks"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3240","question":"In general, foals born to previously vaccinated mares should begin receiving routine vaccinations at what age?","answer":"6 months"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3241","question":"Name 3 vaccinations that a foal should receive by 6 months of age.","answer":"Tetanus; EEE; WEE; West Nile; Rhinopneumonitis; Influenza; Rabies (also accept Botulism; Potomac Horse Fever; Strangles; Equine Viral Arteritis (males); Leptospirosis)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3242","question":"By what age should Tetanus, WEE, EEE, and West Nile vaccines be given to a foal from a previously vaccinated mare?","answer":"By 4 – 6 months in foals from vaccinated mares (1st dose at 4 – 6 months, 2nd dose at 10 – 12 months, then annually)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3243","question":"By what age should Tetanus, WEE, EEE, and West Nile vaccines be given to a foal from an UNVACCINATED mare?","answer":"By 1 – 4 months (accept any number within this range) (FYI:  Foals from unvaccinated mares get a 3-dose series with 1st doses at 1 - 4 months and then at 4-week intervals.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3244","question":"What can foals with insufficient absorption of antibodies from colostrum receive, in addition to vaccinations, to help prevent infectious diseases?","answer":"Antitoxin"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3245","question":"If you use the nasal Strangles vaccine, why should you NOT give other injectable vaccines at the same time?","answer":"Live bacteria in the Strangles vaccine will form abscesses at the injection site."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3246","question":"What is the correct name of the vaccine used in horses for prolonged protection against Tetanus?","answer":"Tetanus toxoid (FYI: Tetanus antitoxin only provides temporary protection.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3247","question":"What is the difference between Tetanus antitoxin and Tetanus toxoid vaccine?","answer":"Tetanus antitoxin gives immediate short-term protection (it’s given when immunization status of the animal is unknown or not up to date); Tetanus toxoid gives long term protection (and it should be given annually)."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3248","question":"In reference to horse health, what does TPR stand for?","answer":"Temperature, pulse, and respiration"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3249","question":"Name 3 vital signs of the horse.","answer":"Temperature, pulse, respiration, capillary refill time, mucous membrane color, skin pliability"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3250","question":"Name 5 vital signs of the horse.","answer":"Temperature, pulse, respiration, capillary refill time, mucous membrane color, skin pliability"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3251","question":"In reference to horse health, what does CRT stand for?","answer":"Capillary refill time"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3252","question":"How do you test capillary refill time?","answer":"Press your thumb on the horse's gums for a few seconds and then remove; gum should return to normal pink color within 1 - 2 seconds."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3253","question":"In reference to TPR, what is inversion?","answer":"When respiration rate is higher than the heart rate (pulse)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3254","question":"You are the conditioning veterinarian judge for an endurance trail ride.  What condition would these vital signs indicate?  Temperature 102 degrees, heart rate 80 beats per minute, and respiration 100 breaths per minute.","answer":"Inversion (respiratory rate higher than heart rate)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3255","question":"A respiratory rate higher than the pulse rate is known as what?","answer":"Inversion"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3256","question":"What is the appearance of the mucous membranes of a healthy horse?","answer":"Bright, moist, pink color"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3257","question":"When examining a horse, what 3 things would you evaluate when looking at the mucous membranes?","answer":"Color, moistness, capillary refill time"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3258","question":"Name TWO places on the horse's HEAD where the pulse can easily be felt using your fingers.","answer":"Under the jaw (facial artery) and just below eye (transverse facial artery)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3259","question":"Name 3 places where a horse's pulse can be felt using your fingers.","answer":"Under jaw, below eye, below hock, medial side of pastern, hind leg outside cannon bone, along fetlock next to deep digital flexor tendon, front leg inside just below knee, base of tail, behind elbow (also accept specific arteries)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3260","question":"Name ONE area on the horse that the digital pulse can be palpated.","answer":"Back side of the lower leg above the fetlock, over the fetlock, or down the pastern (FYI:  The digital pulses of the medial and lateral digital arteries are normally hard to feel, but they’re “bounding” with laminitis and a hoof abscess.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3261","question":"What is the normal heart rate of an ADULT horse?","answer":"28 - 40 beats per minute (accept any number within this range) "},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3262","question":"How high can a horse’s heart rate be during a prolonged gallop?","answer":"200 - 250 beats per minute (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3263","question":"What is the normal heart rate for a FOAL?","answer":"60 - 120 beats per minute depending on the age of the foal (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3264","question":"Name ONE thing that can cause an elevated heart rate in a horse.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness, pain, stress, fear, excitement, outside temperature, humidity (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3265","question":"Name 3 causes of an elevated RESTING heart rate.","answer":"Fever, illness, pain, stress, fear, excitement, outside temperature, humidity (Do NOT accept exercise because the question asks for RESTING heart rate.) (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3266","question":"Name 3 factors that affect the horse's heart rate.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness, pain, stress, fear, excitement, outside temperature, humidity (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3267","question":"Name 5 factors that affect the horse's heart rate.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness, pain, stress, fear, excitement, outside temperature, humidity (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3268","question":"What is the normal respiration rate for an ADULT horse?","answer":"8 - 16 breaths per minute (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3269","question":"In what units is the respiratory rate measured?","answer":"Breaths per minute"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3270","question":"What is the normal respiratory rate of a FOAL?","answer":"20 - 40 breaths per minute (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3271","question":"With what instrument is the temperature of a horse taken?","answer":"Thermometer"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3272","question":"What is the normal temperature of an ADULT horse?","answer":"99 - 101.5 degrees (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3273","question":"What is the normal temperature for a NEWBORN FOAL?","answer":"99 - 102 degrees (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3274","question":"Name 3 factors that can cause temperature variations in the individual horse.","answer":"Age; sex; time of day; rain or snow; wind; ambient temperature; humidity; disease; level of activity; stress (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3275","question":"To what does the prefix “desmo” refer?","answer":"Ligament"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"hard","number":"3276","question":"What does the prefix “leuko” mean?","answer":"White (as in white blood cells or leuko)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3277","question":"What does the prefix “peri” mean?","answer":"Around"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3278","question":"What does the suffix “itis” mean?","answer":"Inflammation"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3279","question":"What does the suffix “emia” describe?","answer":"In the blood"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3280","question":"What prefix means below normal?","answer":"Hypo"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3281","question":"What does the suffix “oma” mean?","answer":"Tumor (also accept cancer or neoplasm)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3282","question":"Name 3 common conditions or management practices that can result in injury to the horse.","answer":"Barns, stalls, fences, or gates either too small, not designed properly, or in poor repair; improper building materials; uncapped steel posts; sharp edges on waterers, etc. (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3283","question":"What is the difference between a closed wound and an open wound?","answer":"Closed wound—skin is intact; open wound—skin is broken"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"jr bonus","number":"3284","question":"Name 3 common causes of horse wounds.","answer":"Kicks, bites, falls, colliding with objects, trauma, lacerations from fencing (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3285","question":"What is the FIRST step in treating an abscess?","answer":"Open the abscess so it can drain"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3286","question":"What is the term for a localized collection of pus in the body tissue which is often accompanied by swelling and inflammation?","answer":"Abscess"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3287","question":"Name 3 types of closed wounds.","answer":"Contusion, hematoma, sprain, torn muscle, torn ligament, torn tendon, torn cartilage"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3288","question":"Give ONE treatment for a contusion.","answer":"Ice packs or cold hosing, compression or leg wrap, rest, later may apply heat to encourage absorption of excess fluid"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3289","question":"What is a contusion?","answer":"Bruise (closed wound caused by blunt force trauma that causes hemorrhage, bruising, and edema without breaking the skin) (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3290","question":"Your horse has been kicked by another horse and has a contusion.  The trauma is sufficient to break blood vessels, resulting in an abnormal pocket and collection of blood in the body tissue.  What is this called?","answer":"Hematoma"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3291","question":"2 part question:  What is a hematoma and what causes it?","answer":"Abnormal collection of blood in body tissues; caused by trauma or by blood vessel injury"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3292","question":"What is the best way to initially clean a large wound that's contaminated with dirt?","answer":"Hose it with water"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3293","question":"Why should you clip the hair around a wound before cleaning it?","answer":"So the hair doesn't get into the wound (to keep it clean)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3294","question":"You are the veterinarian on call and are examining a horse that sustained a laceration to the front lower leg sometime in the past 12 hours.  There is no active bleeding from the wound.  What would be the main reason to NOT suture the wound?","answer":"Suturing this long after the injury may increase the risk of infection."},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3295","question":"What is the best way to control bleeding of a leg wound?","answer":"Apply pressure (or apply a pressure bandage)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3296","question":"Which is more serious, cutting an artery or a vein?","answer":"Artery"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3297","question":"If blood is spurting from a wound, is an artery or vein cut?","answer":"Artery"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3298","question":"Your horse has been injured and is bleeding.  How would you know if an artery was cut?","answer":"Bright red blood would be spurting from the wound"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3299","question":"What does hemorrhaging mean?","answer":"Uncontrolled bleeding"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3300","question":"2 part question:  Your horse has just sustained a laceration to the leg and it is bleeding profusely. Your veterinarian has been contacted and is coming. Name TWO things you should do prior to the arrival of your veterinarian.","answer":"Control bleeding and keep the wound clean"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3301","question":"Name 3 of the most dangerous locations for bleeding.","answer":"Neck, chest, forelegs, trunk, hind legs (jugular vein, carotid artery, subclavian arteries and vein, aorta, femoral arteries and vein, digital arteries)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3302","question":"After hosing a wound, what should you do next?","answer":"Clean the wound with a mild antiseptic or bandage the wound (accept either)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3303","question":"Name TWO benefits of hosing a leg wound with cold water.","answer":"Cleans wound, decreases swelling, decreases pain, controls bleeding"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"int bonus","number":"3304","question":"Name 3 types of open wounds.","answer":"Incisions, lacerations, punctures, abrasions, penetrating wounds, avulsions"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3305","question":"In reference to a wound, what is meant by the term \"golden period\"?","answer":"Elapsed time from injury to closure (after which, suturing a wound would do little good)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3306","question":"Name 3 tissues of the horse that can be damaged in open wounds.","answer":"Skin, muscle, nerves, blood vessels, tendons, bones, internal organs"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3307","question":"What term describes the type of wound caused by a rope burn or poorly fitted tack?","answer":"Abrasion (FYI: Abrasions are scrapes.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3308","question":"What is an abrasion?","answer":"Scrape (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3309","question":"What is the term for an open sore that forms just behind a horse’s elbow?","answer":"Girth gall (also accept abrasion or saddle sore)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3310","question":"2 part question:  In reference to wounds what are \"galls\" and what is the result if they are left untreated?","answer":"Abrasions or sores caused by the saddle or harness; untreated, may result in white hair spots"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3311","question":"What is the term for a wound with clean, straight edges?","answer":"Incision (may accept cut from juniors)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3312","question":"In reference to wounds, what is an incision?","answer":"Wound with clean, straight edges"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3313","question":"Which type of wound has torn and irregular edges?","answer":"Laceration"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3314","question":"What type of wound would be caused by barbed wire?","answer":"Laceration"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"intermediate","number":"3315","question":"What is a laceration?","answer":"Jagged tear in the skin (wound with torn, irregular edges)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3316","question":"2 part question:  What is a penetrating wound and how should you treat it?","answer":"Wound that penetrates a body cavity or organ; treat as an EMERGENCY—call vet and cover wound with sterile gauze"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3317","question":"What is the biggest danger with puncture wounds?","answer":"Infections (such as Tetanus)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3318","question":"What is a puncture wound?","answer":"Deep wound that has a small skin opening (accept any reasonable explanation)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3319","question":"Horses with puncture wounds should receive what vaccination if it’s been 6 months or more since their last shot?","answer":"Tetanus shot (FYI:  If a horse hasn’t been vaccinated or if its vaccination status is unknown, then it should receive BOTH Tetanus toxoid and Tetanus anti-toxin.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3320","question":"What type of wound would a nail cause?","answer":"Puncture wound"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3321","question":"How can you help keep a puncture wound open while it's healing?","answer":"Soak in warm water and Epsom salts"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3322","question":"Why is drainage encouraged with a puncture wound?","answer":"To remove pus and debris or so the wound will heal from the inside out (accept either)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"easy","number":"3323","question":"Name ONE common complication in the healing of lower leg wounds.","answer":"Proud flesh; infection (FYI: Proud flesh is excess granulation tissue.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"medium","number":"3324","question":"What is proud flesh?","answer":"Excess granulation tissue (FYI:  The best treatment is surgical removal or debridement of proud flesh.)"},
{"category":"Health and First Aid","level":"sr bonus","number":"3325","question":"Name 3 risk factors for the development of proud flesh.","answer":"Lower leg injuries (where there’s little muscle);  injuries in areas where there’s a lot of movement; injuries around joints; infected tissues; wounds left open to heal; limited intact healthy skin to cover the wound"},
{"category":"History","level":"int bonus","number":"3326","question":"Name 3 parts to the scientific classification of animals.  Hint:  The pneumonic is King Phillip Cried “Oh, For Goodness Sakes”.","answer":"Kingdom, Phylum, Class, Order, Family, Genus, Species"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3327","question":"Warm blooded animals that give milk and have hair fall into what zoological CLASS?","answer":"Mammalia (mammals)"},
{"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3328","question":"In the zoological classification, what FAMILY includes the horse?","answer":"Equidae"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3329","question":"What GENUS includes horses, zebras, and asses?","answer":"Equus"},
{"category":"History","level":"intermediate","number":"3330","question":"In the zoological classification, to what KINGDOM does the horse belong?","answer":"Animalia (animals)"},
{"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3331","question":"In the zoological classification, to what ORDER does the horse belong?","answer":"Perissodactyla (odd-toed ungulates)"},
{"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3332","question":"In the zoological classification, to what PHYLUM does the horse belong?","answer":"Chordata (animals with notochords)"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3333","question":"What is the GENUS and SPECIES of horse?","answer":"Equus caballus"},
{"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3334","question":"Name TWO environmental variations that affected the early horses' development.","answer":"Altitude, climate, soil, forage"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3335","question":"Name ONE continent where horses were first domesticated.","answer":"Asia; Europe"},
{"category":"History","level":"intermediate","number":"3336","question":"Although the precise date of domestication of the horse remains unknown, what serves as the first record of man's dependence on the horse?  These records date back to the most ancient of times.","answer":"Cave paintings"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3337","question":"Domestication of the horse had spread to almost every area of Europe, Asia and North Africa by what date?","answer":"1000 BC"},
{"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3338","question":"Name TWO of the earliest areas of the horse's domestication.","answer":"China and Mesopotamia"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3339","question":"What proof do we have of what ancient horses were like?","answer":"Fossils"},
{"category":"History","level":"jr bonus","number":"3340","question":"Name 3 continents where fossil remains of horses have been found.","answer":"Asia, Europe, Africa, North America, South America"},
{"category":"History","level":"jr bonus","number":"3341","question":"Name 3 stages of evolution of the horse.","answer":"Eohippus, Mesohippus, Merychippus, Pliohippus, Equus"},
{"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3342","question":"Name the 5 stages of evolution of the horse.","answer":"Eohippus, Mesohippus, Merychippus, Pliohippus, Equus "},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3343","question":"How tall was Eohippus?","answer":"12 inches (FYI: Eohippus or “dawn horse” had 4 toes on the front feet and 3 toes on the back feet.)"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3344","question":"What does Eohippus mean?","answer":"Dawn horse"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3345","question":"What was the original ancestor of the modern horse?","answer":"Eohippus"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3346","question":"2 part question:  How many toes did Eohippus have on his front feet and back feet?","answer":"Front foot 4 toes; back foot 3 toes"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3347","question":"What type of environment was Eohippus most suited for?","answer":"Forested and swampy environment"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3348","question":"When Equus died out in North America, how did some of the population survive?","answer":"Crossed a land bridge between North America and Asia (between Alaska and Russia)"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3349","question":"What was the final stage of the development of the horse?","answer":"Equus"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3350","question":"How tall was Merychippus?","answer":"Size of a Shetland Pony"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3351","question":"How many toes did Merychippus have?","answer":"3 (three) on each foot (FYI: Only the middle toe touched the ground.)"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3352","question":"How tall was Mesohippus?","answer":"24 inches (FYI: Mesohippus or \"middle horse\" had 3 toes on the front feet and 3 toes on the back feet.)"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3353","question":"What is the second stage in the horse's evolution?","answer":"Mesohippus"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3354","question":"Which toe of Mesohippus was largest?","answer":"Middle toe"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3355","question":"Which toe of Mesohippus became the foot of Equus?","answer":"Middle toe"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3356","question":"How many toes did Mesohippus have?","answer":"3 (three) on each foot (FYI: Middle toe was the largest.)"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3357","question":"Describe the difference between the front legs of Mesohippus and Merychippus.","answer":"Mesohippus—all 3 toes touched the ground; Merychippus—only the middle toe touched the ground"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3358","question":"Which horse ancestor was the first to have only one toe on each foot?","answer":"Pliohippus"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3359","question":"How tall was Pliohippus?","answer":"Size of a pony"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3360","question":"2 part question:  The word “Mesohippus” comes from what language and what does it mean?","answer":"Greek; middle horse"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3361","question":"2 part question:  The word “hors” comes from what language group and what does it mean?","answer":"Anglo-Saxon; swiftness"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3362","question":"How did horses return to North America during the 1500's?","answer":"Spanish explorers"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3363","question":"Geologists suggest our modern horse began his history how long ago?","answer":"58 million years ago (accept any number between 55 – 60 million)"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3364","question":"On what continent did Equus originate?","answer":"North America"},
{"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3365","question":"Name ONE important event in the history of the horse that occurred during the Pleistocene epoch.","answer":"Equus, the final stage of the horse, developed; horses became extinct in North America; Equus crossed the land bridge to Europe and Asia"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3366","question":"What was the significance of the Bering Strait in the evolution of horses?","answer":"It's the area where the horse's ancestors crossed the land bridge to migrate to Asian and Europe."},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3367","question":"Which individual is credited with bringing the first spotted horses to North America?","answer":"Cortez"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3368","question":"2 part question:  When did horses return to North America and who brought them?","answer":"16th century (1500’s); Spaniards"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3369","question":"During what time period did Equus migrate over the land bridges to Asia?","answer":"Ice Age (FYI: about 1 million years ago)"},
{"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3370","question":"Give 3 reasons that are thought to be the cause of the horse's extinction in North and South America during the Pleistocene era.","answer":"Disease, depletion of food sources, insects, early human intervention, sudden climate change, parasites, failure to adapt to environment"},
{"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3371","question":"Early wild horses showed great adaptability in the environments where they lived.  Name TWO of those environments.","answer":"Steppes, forests, deserts, tundra"},
{"category":"History","level":"sr bonus","number":"3372","question":"Name 3 other animals that became extinct from North America about the same time as the horse (during the Pleistocene epoch).","answer":"Rhinoceros, saber-toothed tiger, mastodon, camel, elephant"},
{"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3373","question":"In regards to the history of the horse, what event took place during the Pleistocene epoch in North America?","answer":"Horse became extinct in North America."},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3374","question":"Name ONE of the horse's greatest contributions to human history.","answer":"Use in war, transportation, draft animal, pack animal, food source, pleasure, recreation, sports, showing, rodeo, agriculture"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3375","question":"What animal has played a significant role in warfare since ancient times?","answer":"Horse"},
{"category":"History","level":"easy","number":"3376","question":"Name ONE ability of the horse that had the greatest significance in building civilizations.","answer":"Ability to carry loads, ability to pull loads, ability to serve as a draft animal, transportation ability"},
{"category":"History","level":"hard","number":"3377","question":"The appearance of man in North America during the Paleolithic era coincided with the disappearance of the horse from the continent.  What early use of the horse by man could have contributed to this?","answer":"Use of the horse as a food source"},
{"category":"History","level":"jr bonus","number":"3378","question":"Name 3 ways horses have been used throughout history.","answer":"Use in war, transportation, draft animal, pack animal, food source, pleasure, recreation, sports, showing, rodeo, agriculture (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3379","question":"2 part question:  Who first imported the draft breeds to America and why?","answer":"Farmers in New York and Pennsylvania; they needed heavier horses to haul and plow"},
{"category":"History","level":"medium","number":"3380","question":"Give ONE reason why horses were not widely used in Puritan New England.","answer":"Hilly and rocky fields were better suited for oxen; Puritan ethic discouraged the expense and frivolity of keeping riding horses"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3381","question":"What is the foundation of a horse?","answer":"His feet"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3382","question":"Name 4 parts of the horse's foot.","answer":"Toe, heel, wall, white line, frog, sole, buttress, quarter, bulb, apex of frog, periople, seat of corn, commissure/collateral groove/sulci"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3383","question":"Name 3 things a horse's foot was designed to do.","answer":"Support weight; resist wear; absorb shock; provide traction; conduct moisture; assist in pumping blood; replenish itself"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3384","question":"Give 3 desirable characteristics of a horse's hoof.","answer":"Hard wall; pulses same in both feet; pliable coronet; pliable frog; thick, firm sole; uniform thickness of white line; no discoloration of white line; no founder rings; no bounding pulses; no corns or bruises; no heat; no foul odor; no discharge"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3385","question":"What color are a horse's hooves at birth?","answer":"Usually white"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3386","question":"Name 3 parts of the hoof which furnish nutrition to the hoof.","answer":"Perioplic corium, coronary corium, laminar corium, sole corium, frog"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3387","question":"What are TWO purposes of the digital cushion?","answer":"Helps absorb shock, helps circulation of blood"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3388","question":"What is the PRIMARY purpose of the digital cushion?","answer":"Shock absorption (FYI:  The secondary purpose of the digital cushion is to assist in blood circulation.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3389","question":"What is the fibro-elastic, fatty cushion in the foot that acts as a shock absorber?","answer":"Digital  or plantar cushion (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3390","question":"The digital cushion fills the area between the frog and what tendon?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon (also accept deep flexor tendon)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3391","question":"What is the shape of the digital cushion?","answer":"Wedge-shaped"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3392","question":"What part of the foot is located between the plantar cushion and the insensitive frog?","answer":"Sensitive frog"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3393","question":"What is the name for the soft, spongy, wedge-shaped part of the horse’s foot?","answer":"Frog"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3394","question":"What is the part of a horse's foot provides traction and absorbs shock?","answer":"Frog"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3395","question":"The frog is a wedge-shaped mass that occupies the area between what structures at the heel of the foot?","answer":"Bars (also accept commissures, sulci, or collateral grooves)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3396","question":"What term describes the point of the frog towards the toe?","answer":"Apex"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3397","question":"How many times a year is a frog naturally shed?","answer":"2 (two) times a year"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3398","question":"What is the average hoof growth rate per month?","answer":"3/8 inch (accept any number within the range of ¼ - ½ inch or 0.5 - 1 cm)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3399","question":"Which grows FASTER, the front hooves or the back hooves?","answer":"Front hooves"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3400","question":"What part of the horse's foot grows the FASTEST?","answer":"Toe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3401","question":"How long does it take the hoof to grow out from the coronet to ground at the toe?","answer":"9 - 12 months (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3402","question":"Horse's hooves grow faster in what general temperature?","answer":"Warm temperatures"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3403","question":"Horses' hooves grow at different rates of speed.  Which hooves grow SLOWER?","answer":"Hind feet"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3404","question":"Name 3 things that affect hoof growth.","answer":"Temperature or season; age; nutrition; genetics; exercise; heart rate; moisture; massage of the coronary band; irritation or injury to sensitive structures; individual differences (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3405","question":"The soft, fleshy part of a horse's heel is called what?","answer":"Bulb"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3406","question":"What structure transfers the horse's weight from the bony structure to the hoof wall?","answer":"Laminae"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3407","question":"What is the term for the tiny, folded, accordion-like interlocking projections that connect the coffin bone to the hoof wall?","answer":"Laminae (FYI:  There are sensitive and insensitive laminae.  Sensitive laminae contain many nerves and blood vessels.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3408","question":"What part of the horse's foot contains the LEAST amount of moisture?","answer":"Wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3409","question":"What in the horse's feet helps to maintain their flexibility?","answer":"Moisture"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3410","question":"What part of the horse's foot contains the GREATEST amount of moisture?","answer":"Frog"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3411","question":"What is the function of the tectorial layer of the horse's foot?","answer":"Maintains moisture in the hoof wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3412","question":"Where does the moisture come from that helps maintain flexibility and prevent cracking of the horse's feet?","answer":"Within the foot or in environment (accept either"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3413","question":"What is the moisture content of the following parts of the hoof:  wall, sole, and frog?","answer":"Wall—25%; sole—33%; frog—50%"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3414","question":"What is nature's hoof conditioner?","answer":"Water"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3415","question":"What is the varnish-like layer of the hoof called?","answer":"Periople"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3416","question":"Specifically, what part of the foot produces the periople?","answer":"Perioplic corium (pair-ee-OH-plic CORE-ee-um)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3417","question":"Describe the difference between the sensitive and insensitive structures of the hoof.","answer":"Sensitive areas contain nerves and blood vessels; insensitive areas do NOT contain nerves and blood vessels."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3418","question":"What is the difference in shape between front and back feet?","answer":"Front feet are naturally flat; hind feet are naturally concave, narrower and more pointed  "},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3419","question":"What is the diameter of an average adult light horse's foot?","answer":"4 - 6 inches (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3420","question":"What part of the foot is between the wall and the frog?","answer":"Sole (also accept white line, bars, and commissures, sulci, or collateral grooves)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3421","question":"What part of the hoof should NEVER bear weight?","answer":"Sole"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3422","question":"What is the primary function of the sole?","answer":"Protection (of the coffin bone)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3423","question":"2 part question:  What part of the foot is most important to clean properly and why?","answer":"Deep depressions between the bar and the frog (commissures, sulci, or collateral grooves); most likely place for thrush to start (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3424","question":"What is the function of the commissure in the hoof?","answer":"Gives elasticity to the foot"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3425","question":"Give ONE name for the two grooves that separate the sole from the frog.","answer":"Collateral grooves, commissures, sulci"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3426","question":"The wall of a horse's hoof will be thickest in which area?","answer":"Toe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3427","question":"Where is the GREATEST point of wear on a horse's hoof?","answer":"Toe or breakover point (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3428","question":"Why is the hoof wall harder at the toe than at the quarters?","answer":"Toe is further from the coronary band and is therefore more keratinized."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3429","question":"What happens when the large venous plexuses within the hoof are compressed?","answer":"Blood is pumped back up the leg."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3430","question":"What part of the normal, ideal hoof supports the primary weight of the horse?","answer":"Wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3431","question":"What is the term for the hard, outside part of the hoof?","answer":"Wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3432","question":"What part of the foot separates the wall and the sole?","answer":"White line"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3433","question":"Where is the white line located?","answer":"Between the wall and the sole"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3434","question":"Name 3 basic tools used in trimming or shoeing horses.","answer":"Hoof pick, nippers, rasp, hoof knife, rounding hammer, driving hammer, clinch cutter, pull offs (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3435","question":"Timeline…You are a farrier and are demonstrating how to remove a shoe and trim the hoof.  What is the correct order to use the following 5 farrier tools when accomplishing this task:  nippers, hoof knife, clinch cutter, rasp, pull offs?","answer":"Clinch cutter, pull offs, hoof knife, nippers, rasp"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3436","question":"What is the \"farrier's workbench\"?","answer":"Anvil"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3437","question":"Give ONE purpose of a horse shoer's leather apron.","answer":"Protects the shoer's legs from cuts, nails, or tools; protects against heat when working at the forge; provides barrier between horse and farrier for dirt and moisture; holds small tools"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3438","question":"The part of the horseshoe nail that's bent over after being nailed through the hoof is called what?","answer":"Clinch"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3439","question":"Why should the clinches be cut or straightened before pulling off the shoe?","answer":"To prevent tearing or chipping the hoof wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3440","question":"Which farrier tool is used to cut and/or raise clinches?","answer":"Clinch cutter"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3441","question":"What are the TWO main parts of a clinch cutter?","answer":"Blade and point"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3442","question":"What is the name of the tool that farriers use to bend over the end of a horseshoe nail?","answer":"Clincher or clinching tong (can also use a clinch block and a driving hammer)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3443","question":"A clinch block can be used to turn the head of the nail to start the clinch.  If your horse objects to this procedure, what other tool could be used to turn the clinch?","answer":"Clinchers or clinching tongs "},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3444","question":"Identify the 3 general types of clinchers or clinching tongs.","answer":"Saddle horse, gooseneck, and draft horse"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3445","question":"Which farrier tool is used to make a crease in hand-fullered shoes?","answer":"Fullering iron"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3446","question":"2 part question:  What are the TWO basic types of hammers used by farriers and how are they used?","answer":"Rounding hammer—used for making and shaping shoes; driving hammer—used for driving nails, finishing clinches (claws also used for wringing off the old nails)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3447","question":"Which farrier's hammer is heavier, rounding or driving?","answer":"Rounding hammer (FYI: A rounding hammer weighs 2 – 2½ pounds; a driving hammer weighs less than a pound.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3448","question":"Give ONE purpose of the farrier's driving hammer.","answer":"Driving nails or finishing clinches "},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3449","question":"What type of farrier's hammer is used for making and shaping shoes?","answer":"Rounding hammer or turning hammer (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3450","question":"What farrier tool is used for cutting hot metal?","answer":"Hardy"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3451","question":"In reference to farrier tools, what is a hardy?","answer":"Tool used by farrier to cut hot metal"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3452","question":"What piece of equipment is used by a farrier to determine the angle of the hoof?","answer":"Hoof gauge"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3453","question":"What is the purpose of a hoof gauge?","answer":"Measure the hoof angle or toe length (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3454","question":"What does the farrier remove from the hoof when trimming the hoof with a hoof knife?","answer":"Excess dead tissue from the horse’s frog and sole"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3455","question":"Name 3 uses of a hoof knife.","answer":"Pare away dead sole, trim ragged frog, relieve pressure on corns or cracks, remove foreign bodies from hoof"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3456","question":"What is the name for the piece of equipment that's used to clean out a horse's foot?","answer":"Hoof pick"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3457","question":"What is the safest direction to use a hoof pick?","answer":"Heel to toe or away from you (accept either) (FYI:  If used the opposite way, it could slip and gouge the handler or the horse.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3458","question":"Why should a hoof pick be used from heel to toe?","answer":"Safety! If used the opposite way, it could slip and gouge the handler or the horse."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3459","question":"What is the pincher-like instrument that's used to squeeze the hooves to find a sore spot or cause of lameness?","answer":"Hoof testers"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3460","question":"What is the purpose of hoof testers?","answer":"To identify or locate problems in the hoof"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3461","question":"What are nippers used for?","answer":"Trim hoof wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3462","question":"Name the farrier's tool that's used to remove excess hoof wall.","answer":"Nippers"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3463","question":"What is a pritchel used for?","answer":"Make or enlarge nail holes in a horseshoe (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3464","question":"What farrier tool is used to make or enlarge nail holes in horseshoes?","answer":"Pritchel"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3465","question":"Nippers and pull-offs look similar.  Describe how you can quickly tell one from another.","answer":"Pull-offs have knobs on the end of the handles."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3466","question":"You reach into your toolbox looking for nippers and grab what looks like nippers, but they have knobs on the ends of the handles.  What tool do you have?","answer":"Pull offs"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3467","question":"What is the difference in USE between nippers and pull-offs?","answer":"Nippers are used to trim the hoof; pull-offs are used to remove shoes (FYI:  Pull-offs can also be used to remove nails, nail stubs, and improperly driven nails.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3468","question":"When removing a shoe from a horse, describe 3 steps in how the pull-offs are used.","answer":"Put jaws under one heel of shoe; pull down towards toe and in towards center of hoof; support toe with your knee; work gradually towards the toe, first on one branch of the shoe, then on the other; continue until shoe works loose from foot."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3469","question":"When removing a shoe, why should you pull down on the pull-offs instead of pulling them from side to side?","answer":"So you don't twist the foot or pull a tendon (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3470","question":"What tool is used to file the hoof wall and level the bearing surface of the hoof after it has been trimmed by the nippers?","answer":"Rasp"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3471","question":"A satisfactory trimming job can be accomplished with a hoof knife, nippers, and what else?","answer":"Rasp"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3472","question":"After a farrier's rasp has become too dull for rasping hooves, what can the farrier use it for?","answer":"As a clinching or finishing rasp"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3473","question":"Exercising a horse will help keep his feet what?","answer":"Healthy"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3474","question":"How do extremely wet conditions promote rapid drying of the horse's feet?","answer":"Constant contact with moisture can erode or remove protective films from the horse's feet"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3475","question":"Name 3 important points in the care of a horse's foot.","answer":"Keep them clean (to prevent thrush), remove rocks (to prevent bruises), keep them trimmed properly, prevent the hoof from drying out (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3476","question":"Referring to horses, define the term \"barefoot\".","answer":"Horses with no shoes (unshod)."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3477","question":"Give TWO reasons for letting a horse go barefoot for a few months.","answer":"Increases circulation in foot, makes for healthier foot, in winter -helps keep snow/ice from accumulating in hooves"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3478","question":"Referring to horse's feet, what does \"picking out\" mean?","answer":"Cleaning out a horse's hoof"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"novice","number":"3479","question":"Give ONE reason for cleaning out a horse's foot.","answer":"Clean out dirt and rocks; check for injuries; check for thrush or other diseases; check for loose shoes; check for missing nails; check for abnormal growth, uneven wear, cracks, splitting, dryness (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"int bonus","number":"3480","question":"Name 3 things you should look for when inspecting the horse's hoof.","answer":"Rocks and other debris, puncture wounds, bruises, diseases, loose shoes, loose or missing horseshoe nails, abnormal growth, uneven wear, cracks, splitting, too dry (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3481","question":"In what order should you clean your horse's feet?","answer":"Counter clockwise (near fore, near hind, off hind, off fore)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3482","question":"Why should you follow the same order when cleaning your horse's feet?","answer":"So the horse will know what to expect"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3483","question":"How do you pick up a front foot?","answer":"Stand beside the shoulder, facing the rear; run your hand down the back of the leg to just above fetlock; grasp the fetlock area and pick up the foot; you can pinch the tendon or push the shoulder away to help"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3484","question":"How do you pick up a hind foot?","answer":"Stand to the side of the horse facing its tail.  Put your hand on its hindquarters and run your hand down its leg to its fetlock.  Ask the horse to pick up its foot.  If needed, pinch the tendon or lean into the horse.  (Accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3485","question":"In winter, snow or ice accumulating in hooves can cause what?","answer":"Pain or unstable footing (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3486","question":"When shoeing a horse during fly season, what can you use to make things more comfortable for you horse and farrier?","answer":"Fly spray"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3487","question":"Give TWO names for a person who trims or shoes horses' hooves.","answer":"Farrier, blacksmith, horseshoer, shoer"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3488","question":"Give ONE reason why you should work with your foal's feet.","answer":"Get him used to being handled while he's young, he's easier to control when he's young, he will grow up knowing he won't be hurt"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3489","question":"Name 3 shoeing practices that may contribute to the development of corns.","answer":"Shoe too small, leaving shoe on too long, trimming heel too low"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3490","question":"What is the term used to describe when a nail is being driven too close to the white line?","answer":"Quicking  (also accept “hot nail”)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3491","question":"In reference to shoeing, what is meant by the term \"re-set\"?","answer":"When the farrier uses the same set of shoes for a second time"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3492","question":"What is the term for the type of shoeing job when the farrier uses the same set of shoes for a second time?","answer":"Re-set or re-shod (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3493","question":"Name 3 things that can happen if you leave a shoe on too long.","answer":"Shoes can become loose or fall off, shoes can become thin, foot can get bruised or punctured, tendons and ligaments can become strained, hooves can grow out of proportion"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3494","question":"Name TWO things that can happen when a shod hoof grows out and changes the angle of the foot.","answer":"Puts strain on the ligaments and tendons, can affect the horse’s gait or action, can cause lameness"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3495","question":"What does an uneven wear pattern on a horseshoe indicate?","answer":"Foot is landing out of balance or foot is breaking over at a point other than the toe (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3496","question":"2 part question:  When holding a horse for the farrier, on which side should you stand and why?","answer":"Same side as the farrier; if the horse acts up, you can pull its head toward you and the horse's body will move away from the farrier"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3497","question":"When should the angle of the hoof be changed?","answer":"Only as a corrective measure"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3498","question":"What are the TWO types of balance to consider when trimming the hoof?","answer":"Heel to toe (front to back) and medial to lateral (side to side)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3499","question":"Why do you trim the bars level with the sole?","answer":"So the bars won't be broken or torn on rocks, etc."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"int bonus","number":"3500","question":"Name 3 common faults corrected by trimming.","answer":"Splay foot, pigeon toe, quarter crack, cocked ankle, contracted heels"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3501","question":"Name ONE common fault corrected by trimming.","answer":"Splay foot, pigeon toe, quarter crack, cocked ankle, contracted heels"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3502","question":"A base narrow horse will wear its feet unevenly.  What part of the foot needs to be rasped more in order to bring the foot level?","answer":"Inside wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3503","question":"Correction of a foal's hooves must begin when the foal is a few days old and must be completed before what happens?","answer":"Before the growth plates close"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3504","question":"When trimming the hooves of a pigeon toed horse, which half of the hoof do you trim more?","answer":"Inner half"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3505","question":"By lowering the inside hoof wall, the farrier is correcting what problem?","answer":"Pigeon toe (toe in)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3506","question":"How would you trim a splayfooted horse?","answer":"Trim more off the outer half of the hoof"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3507","question":"What may happen if the hoof is not trimmed and it grows too long?","answer":"Hoof wall cracks, hoof wall breaks off, hoof won't wear evenly (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3508","question":"What poor trimming practice may cause forging or over-reaching?","answer":"Leaving the toe too long"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3509","question":"Careless trimming of a foal's feet can cause what?","answer":"Injury (strained tendons or lameness)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3510","question":"Why should you trim your young foal's feet often?","answer":"So his feet and legs can grow as straight as possible"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3511","question":"How many times a year should a horse be trimmed or shod?","answer":"6 - 12 times a year (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3512","question":"How often should horse's hooves be trimmed?","answer":"Every 4 - 8 weeks (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3513","question":"A normal, healthy mature horse without foot problems has its feet trimmed every 6 - 8 weeks.  How often should FOALS' feet be trimmed?","answer":"Once a month, every 30 days, or every 4 weeks (accept any)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3514","question":"How much should you trim the frog of a horse that's stabled?","answer":"Only enough to remove dead tissue"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3515","question":"Why should you NEVER rasp the walls of the hoof?","answer":"Removes the periople (outer varnish layer) (causing the hoof to dry out)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3516","question":"2 part question:  When trimming a horse that's going to be ridden on rocky ground and/or roads, what part of the foot should NOT be trimmed and why?","answer":"Sole; because it protects the foot"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3517","question":"Name 3 problems that can occur to the feet of horses that are stalled year round.","answer":"Dry hooves, contracted heels, navicular disease"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3518","question":"Where is a foot abscess most common?","answer":"Sole or white line (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3519","question":"An abscess of the hoof may open and drain on its own.  Name ONE thing you can do to encourage the abscess to dry up and heal.","answer":"Soak the foot (in Epsom salts and warm water or iodine solution) or pack the hoof (Animalintex, Ichthammol, etc.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3520","question":"Name 3 steps in treating an abscessed foot.","answer":"Locate and drain abscess; remove dead tissue (avoid excessive tissue removal); use poultice; soak foot in water and Epsom salts; protect hoof with shoe, pad, or bandages; Tetanus booster"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3521","question":"In relation to horses' hooves, what is \"gravel\"?","answer":"Infection that penetrates the white line and abscesses at the coronet (subsolar abscess)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3522","question":"What is an infection that penetrates the white line and abscesses at the coronet?","answer":"Gravel or sub-solar abscess (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3523","question":"In relation to horses' hooves, what is another name for gravel?","answer":"Sub-solar abscess"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3524","question":"Name 3 causes of gravel or subsolar abscess.","answer":"Puncture of white line; bruising; trauma; dirt or bacteria getting in through cracks in white line or wall; wet footing"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3525","question":"Chronic inflammation and swelling of the lateral cartilage resulting in intermittent sub-coronary abscesses is called what?","answer":"Quittor"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3526","question":"What is quittor?","answer":"Inflammation of the lateral cartilages which can cause subcoronary abscesses (wound at the rear quarter of the hoof that discharges pus above the coronet)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3527","question":"What is a deep-seated sore that drains at the coronet and causes severe lameness?","answer":"Quittor (also accept gravel or subsolar abscess)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3528","question":"What is the most common cause of quittor?","answer":"Trauma near the coronary band (or to the lateral cartilages)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3529","question":"What is the term for the condition where a horse's foot may become smaller at ground level than at the top of the foot?","answer":"Contracted heels"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3530","question":"What are contracted heels?","answer":"Heels of hoof are too close (upright for normal foot conformation, frog may be shrunken)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3531","question":"A narrow, shrunken frog and heels that are pulled together are signs of what?","answer":"Contracted heels"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3532","question":"What unsoundness may result from a dried out, shrunken frog?","answer":"Contracted heels or navicular disease (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3533","question":"In referring to the hoof, what can happen if there isn't any frog pressure or contact with the ground?","answer":"Contracted heels may develop"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3534","question":"Name ONE cause of contracted heels.","answer":"Improper trimming or shoeing; leaving shoes on too long; lack of frog pressure; lack of moisture in hoof; genetics; faulty conformation; uneven weight distribution"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3535","question":"Give 3 causes of contracted heels.","answer":"Improper trimming or shoeing; leaving shoes on too long; lack of frog pressure; lack of moisture in hoof; genetics; faulty conformation; uneven weight distribution"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3536","question":"In reference to a horse's foot, where would you find a corn?","answer":"Heel area of the sole"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3537","question":"A specific type of sole bruise occurring in the heel area is called what?","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3538","question":"Name ONE common cause of corns in the horse.","answer":"Improper shoeing, shoe too small, leaving shoe on too long, trimming heel too low"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3539","question":"What is a quarter or sand crack?","answer":"Crack in the side of the hoof wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3540","question":"What is a quarter or sand crack?","answer":"Crack in the hoof wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3541","question":"Why are quarter cracks more common than toe cracks?","answer":"Wall of the hoof is thinner at the quarter."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3542","question":"Name ONE cause of a sand or quarter crack.","answer":"Uneven weight bearing; irregular hoof growth; wire cuts; excessive hoof length; dry conditions"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3543","question":"Name 3 causes of a sand or quarter crack.","answer":"Uneven weight bearing; irregular hoof growth; wire cuts; excessive hoof length; dry conditions"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3544","question":"2 part question:  Will the edges of a crack in the hoof wall, such as a sand or quarter crack, grow back together if the hoof wall is supported and immobilized?   Explain why.","answer":"No; the hoof wall must grow out to eliminate the crack"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3545","question":"Keeping the hoof moist and the toe shortened will help correct which defect?","answer":"Quarter crack"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3546","question":"Name ONE thing that will usually help correct a quarter crack.","answer":"Keep the hoof moist; keep the toe shortened; file a notch across the top of the crack, hold crack together with some material (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3547","question":"Name 3 different variations of a hoof crack.","answer":"Extends partway down from coronary band; extends partway up from ground level; extends full length of wall; horizontal crack"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3548","question":"When should hoof dressing be used?","answer":"When the wall is dry, brittle, or cracked (accept any)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3549","question":"Which farrier tool would be used to correct a flare?","answer":"Rasp"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3550","question":"What causes the hoof wall to flare?","answer":"Unequal weight distribution"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3551","question":"What are outward distortions of the hoof called?","answer":"Flares"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3552","question":"A darkened or moist area on the sole is usually an indication of what?","answer":"Puncture wound (also accept sole bruise or abscess)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3553","question":"What is seedy toe?","answer":"Separation of the sole from the hoof wall near the toe (white line disease)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3554","question":"What is the name of the condition of the hoof when there is a separation of the sensitive and insensitive laminae at the white line in the toe area?","answer":"Seedy toe (also accept white line disease)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3555","question":"A disease of the foot characterized by a pungent odor is called what?","answer":"Thrush"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3556","question":"What is thrush?","answer":"Infection of the frog (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3557","question":"Name the following disease: caused by Fusobacterium necrophorum (an anaerobic bacterium), usually is a result of wet or unsanitary conditions, signs include crumbly frog, black sulci, and a pungent odor.","answer":"Thrush"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3558","question":"Thrush is a black, strong smelling infection of the hoof that causes destruction of the frog. Is it caused by aerobic or anaerobic bacteria?","answer":"Anaerobic bacteria (FYI: Fusobacterium necrophorum)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3559","question":"Name ONE way to treat thrush.","answer":"Keep hooves clean; remove affected tissue;  treat with anti-thrush medication"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3560","question":"What is White Line Disease?","answer":"Infection in the white line that causes separation of the sole and wall (also called seedy toe) (FYI:  White Line Disease or seedy toe can be caused by bacteria, hoof digesting fungi, or a combination of both.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3561","question":"Regarding horses' feet, what is one of the best known quotations in the horse world?","answer":"\"No foot, no horse\""},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3562","question":"What is the first rule to remember in fitting a shoe to a horse's foot?","answer":"Shape the shoe to fit the foot."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3563","question":"How many years have horseshoes been protecting horse's feet?","answer":"More than 2000"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3564","question":"Why should the horseshoe be slightly wider at the heels than at the quarters?","answer":"To accommodate the expansion of the heels when the foot bears weight"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3565","question":"Referring to horseshoeing, what is balance?","answer":"Equal weight distribution (around the center of gravity on the horse's leg)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"int bonus","number":"3566","question":"Name 3 steps in shoeing a horse.","answer":"Observe horse; cut clinches; pull off old shoe; trim hoof wall; trim frog and sole; shape shoe; nail shoe on; clinch nails; rasp"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3567","question":"There are 10 things that distinguish an ideally fitted horseshoe. Name 3. DO NOT READ, PART OF THE ANSWER:  provide confidence for performance without slipping;  minimum weight necessary to last between shoeing intervals or to encourage desired action","answer":"Balanced; stable on hoof; secure; retains natural cupping shape of foot; retains frog traction; protects sole; compensates for low heels; beveled to prevent pulling or injury to another leg; nail holes in front half of shoe at proper angle"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3568","question":"You are spending the day with a farrier.  The farrier has 4 shoes that look identical set aside for the horse he is shoeing.  He would like you to hand him a front shoe.  How will you know which is a front shoe?","answer":"Front shoe is rounder (and is wider at the heel)."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3569","question":"Give 3 reasons why a horse may need horseshoes.","answer":"Protect hoof from wear; protect hoof from hard surfaces; provide traction; correct stance; correct gait; treat abnormal condition (corn, contracted heels, cracks, etc.); ease pain of injured hoof"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3570","question":"What is corrective shoeing?","answer":"Shoeing to correct the stance or gait of a horse"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3571","question":"Name the type of keg shoe that is made of aluminum and is used on racehorses.","answer":"Racing plates or plates"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3572","question":"Aluminum horseshoes have the advantage over steel horseshoes of being lighter in weight, but have what disadvantage compared to a steel shoe?","answer":"Aluminum shoes wear faster."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3573","question":"Racing plates are generally made from what type of metal?","answer":"Aluminum"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3574","question":"Aluminum shoes are most commonly used in what equine sport?","answer":"Racing (FYI:  Racing plates are 1/3 the weight of steel shoes.  Aluminum shoes are also used on the front feet of jumping horses.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3575","question":"How much does an aluminum racing plate weigh?","answer":"2 - 3 ounces (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3576","question":"2 part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of aluminum shoes.","answer":"Advantage—lightweight; disadvantage—wears out quicker than steel"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3577","question":"What alloy can be added to horseshoes to increase traction and life of the shoe?","answer":"Borium"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3578","question":"What metal alloy used in horseshoes maintains the light weight of aluminum, but has the durability of steel?","answer":"Titanium"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3579","question":"Caulks and studs are devices added to horseshoes for what purpose?","answer":"Traction"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3580","question":"In reference to horseshoes, explain the difference between a sticker and a block.","answer":"Both are heel caulks.  Block is set lengthwise on heel and sticker is set so it goes across the foot."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3581","question":"What is the purpose of adding stickers or mud caulks to the heel of a racing plate?","answer":"Increase traction (on a muddy race track)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3582","question":"Where on a horseshoe would you find caulks?","answer":"Ground surface of the shoe (usually at the heels and/or toes)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3583","question":"The Chadwick Spring provides constant outward pressure on the bars of the foot and would be used for what conformation defect of the hoof?","answer":"Contracted heels"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3584","question":"What are toe clips?","answer":"Metal projections on the outside front of shoe (FYI: help hold the shoe on and take stress off the nails.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"intermediate","number":"3585","question":"A thin metal projection on the outside of a shoe that lies against the hoof to give it support is called what?","answer":"Clip"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3586","question":"Give ONE purpose of clips on horseshoes.","answer":"To take stress off the nails; to stabilize the shoe on the foot; to help hold the shoe more securely on thin walled hooves"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3587","question":"What type of shoe modification is used to take the stress off nails and to stabilize the shoe?","answer":"Clips"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3588","question":"What is the name for a removable traction device for horseshoes?","answer":"Studs (FYI: Studs are usually screwed into the shoe; caulks are usually forged into the shoe.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3589","question":"In race horses, why are traction devices such as toe grabs not being used by trainers as commonly as they used to be?","answer":"They produce too many injuries."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3590","question":"A thin protrusion of metal on the GROUND SURFACE of the toe of a racing plate is known as what shoe alteration?","answer":"Toe grab or toe grip (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3591","question":"Referring to horseshoes, what is a \"trailer\"?","answer":"Horseshoe heel that extends ½ inch or more beyond the horse's heel. (FYI:  used on hind feet)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3592","question":"How many nail holes are there in most ready-made horseshoes?","answer":"8 (eight)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3593","question":"What is the position of a properly driven horseshoe nail?","answer":"Parallel to the tubules in the hoof wall"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3594","question":"How far above the horseshoe should horseshoe nails exit the hoof?","answer":"¾ - 1 inch (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3595","question":"Name 3 parts of a horseshoe nail.","answer":"Head, neck, shank, bevel, point, inner face, outer face"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3596","question":"What is the name for the SPECIFIC part of the horseshoe nail that prevents the nail from pulling through the shoe?","answer":"Nail head (also accept clinch)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3597","question":"What is the purpose of beveling on a horseshoe nail?","answer":"Directs the point of the nail to come out the side of the hoof wall instead of going straight into the hoof"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3598","question":"Horse shoe nails have a shank that is flat on one side and the other side is concave.  When driving a nail, the nail should be started with which side facing the outside of the hoof?","answer":"Flat side should be outside"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3599","question":"A horseshoe nail has two sizes of heads, regular and city head.  Which is smaller?","answer":"City head"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3600","question":"What type of horseshoe nail is used to increase traction on icy surfaces?","answer":"Frosthead nail"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3601","question":"Name 3 types of horseshoe nails.","answer":"Regular, cityhead, and frosthead"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3602","question":"In horseshoeing, what are pads used for?","answer":"To protect the bottom of the foot"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3603","question":"When would you use a hospital plate on a shoe?","answer":"When the foot is abscessed or when the sole has an injury (FYI: Hospital plates are easy to remove so you can apply medication to foot bottom; hospital plates also keep out debris.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3604","question":"What is the term for a specialized type of horseshoe pad that can be removed to treat or apply medicine to the hoof and can then be re-attached?","answer":"Hospital plate"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3605","question":"Fullering, web, and branch are parts of what?","answer":"Horseshoe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3606","question":"2 part question:  What happens if the branch of a shoe is too long on a front foot and on a hind foot?","answer":"If the long branch is on the front foot, the hind foot may pull the shoe off.  If the long branch is on the hind foot, nothing usually happens."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3607","question":"What is the width and thickness of the metal in the horseshoe called?","answer":"Web"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3608","question":"How does the thickness of the hoof wall determine the web or width of a horse shoe?","answer":"Web should be TWICE the thickness of the hoof wall."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3609","question":"What is the basic purpose of horseshoes?","answer":"Protect the feet (from wear or damage)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3610","question":"Give ONE reason for shoeing your horse.","answer":"Protection; traction; correction of conformation fault, abnormal gait, or faulty hoof structure or growth; therapeutic—ease pain of diseased or injured hoof (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"int bonus","number":"3611","question":"Name 3 reasons to shoe a horse.","answer":"Protection; traction; correction of conformation fault, abnormal gait, or faulty hoof structure or growth; therapeutic—ease pain of diseased or injured hoof (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3612","question":"Name 3 reasons for hot shoeing.","answer":"Shoes can be made specifically for foot; more secure nailing; less interference with natural hoof function"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3613","question":"You are the ring steward at a horse show.  You found a shoe that an animal in the last driving class lost.  The size of the shoe is triple zero.  What type of equine lost this shoe?","answer":"Pony or a horse with very small feet (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3614","question":"Name 3 things, other than hoof size, that influence what size horseshoe to use.","answer":"Length of shoe heels; position of heel nail holes; web or width; weight of shoe; nail hole size"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3615","question":"What is therapeutic shoeing?","answer":"Shoeing to treat a medical condition of the foot or leg"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3616","question":"Name 3 corrective or therapeutic horseshoes.","answer":"Bar; egg bar; heart bar; Patten shoe; Chadwick spring; trailer; rocker, square, rolled, or wedge toe; half rim; half sole; slippered heels; caulks on heels or at first outside nail hole; lateral toe extension with trailer; bar across breakover point"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"jr bonus","number":"3617","question":"Name 3 types of horseshoes. DO NOT READ, PART OF THE ANSWER:  caulks on heels or at first outside nail hole; bar across breakover point","answer":"Keg (regular); racing plate; sliding plate; rim; polo; weighted shoes for gaited horses; bar; egg bar; heart bar; Patten; glue-on; rocker, square, rolled, or wedge toe; half round; half rim; half-sole; slippered heel; trailer; Chadwick spring"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3618","question":"The kind and weight of shoes worn by horses depends on what?","answer":"Type of work the horse does"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3619","question":"Name 3 things that influence horseshoe style.","answer":"Type of activity horse does; type of terrain horse is worked on; integrity of hoof (how good hoof is); size of horse; weight of horse (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3620","question":"2 part question:  Name TWO types of shoes used specifically for the FRONT feet and give their purposes.","answer":"Half round shoes—harness racing or reining; weighted shoes—enhances the action of gaited horses"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3621","question":"2 part question:  Name TWO types of shoes used specifically for the HIND feet and give their purposes.","answer":"Sliding plates—help horse slide stop; square toe—stabilizes the breakover point"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"sr bonus","number":"3622","question":"Name TWO types of horseshoes that can be used to re-establish frog pressure.","answer":"Bar shoe; slippered or beveled heel; Chadwick spring"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3623","question":"Give ONE reason why your horse might wear a bar shoe.","answer":"Contracted heels; navicular disease; founder or laminitis; corn"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3624","question":"What type shoe can you use to protect the foot while a corn is healing?","answer":"Bar shoe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3625","question":"What kind of shoe is used to support a horse with a navicular problem?","answer":"Egg bar shoe, bar shoe, or heart bar shoe (accept any)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3626","question":"What is the purpose of an eggbar shoe?","answer":"Supports rear portion of the hoof; used for navicular or under-run heels (accept any)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3627","question":"A heart bar shoe would be used temporarily to treat a hoof problem where you want to transfer weight from the hoof wall to what structure of the foot?","answer":"Frog"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3628","question":"What type of horseshoe is commonly used on horses with laminitis to transfer weight from the wall of the hoof to the frog?","answer":"Heart bar shoe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3629","question":"Give ONE reason why hoof boots are used on horses.","answer":"Replace a lost shoe; treat a foot by placing medication in boot; protect hoof from further injury; keep a hoof clean; traction"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3630","question":"What is a fullered shoe?","answer":"One with a crease all the way around the shoe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3631","question":"What type of horseshoes can be used on a horse that temporarily needs shoe protection without damaging the foot with horseshoe nails?","answer":"Glue-on shoes (FYI:  Glue-on shoes are especially useful on very young foals with thin, fragile hoof walls.  They are also used on thin-walled, weak-footed horses that temporarily need protection until the hoof grows out.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3632","question":"Name ONE type of horse that may use half round shoes.","answer":"Harness racing horses; reining horses; occasionally foals"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3633","question":"The most commonly used manufactured or preformed horseshoes are called what?","answer":"Keg shoes"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3634","question":"What is a keg shoe?","answer":"Pre-sized, ready-made shoe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"medium","number":"3635","question":"How does a mule shoe differ from a horse shoe?","answer":"Mule shoe is narrower."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3636","question":"What is the name of the type of shoe that's used to elevate the heels of a horse that's confined to stall rest?","answer":"Patten shoe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3637","question":"What is the name for a type of shoe where the inside rim on the web is raised above the outside rim?","answer":"Polo shoe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3638","question":"What distinguishes a polo shoe from a cowboy shoe?","answer":"Inside rim of the polo shoe is raised above the outside rim."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3639","question":"What characteristic of a polo shoe increases traction?","answer":"Inside edge is raised higher than the outside edge"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3640","question":"Identify ONE advantage of the raised inside rim on polo shoes.","answer":"Increases traction; prevents sliding; enables foot to roll over faster; allows horse to pivot on shoe; allows horse to maintain a toe grip regardless of where foot breaks over"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3641","question":"In order to alleviate tension of the flexor tendons and/or reduce the risk of forging, what horseshoe feature is frequently used in conjunction with an eggbar shoe for horses with navicular disease?","answer":"Rocker toe (FYI:  Rocker toe shoes help horses suffering from limb deformities, posterior heel lameness, navicular disease, and stumbling.  They also reduce the risks of forging or overreaching.)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3642","question":"Why would you choose to use a rocker-toe horse shoe for a healthy young horse?","answer":"Rocker-toe shoe eases the breakover of the hoof to help prevent forging."},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3643","question":"Sliding plate horseshoes will be found on the rear hooves of a horse performing in what kind of competition?","answer":"Reining"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"easy","number":"3644","question":"What kind of special shoes would be found on the hind feet of a horse in a reining competition?","answer":"Sliding plates or sliders (accept either)"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3645","question":"What style of horseshoe can stabilize the breakover of the foot and prevent the horse from landing on either the outside or inside hoof wall?","answer":"Square toe"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3646","question":"How does the farrier choose the proper weight of shoe for the horse?","answer":"Generally, the lightest weight the horse can wear is best; heavier shoes are used on gaited horses to achieve higher action"},
{"category":"Hooves and Hoof Care","level":"hard","number":"3647","question":"What is the approximate weight of a #1 sized horseshoe?","answer":"8 - 12 ounces (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3648","question":"What is the main factor to consider in evaluating the seriousness of a leg conformation fault?","answer":"How it affects the travel and/or durability of the horse (accept either)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3649","question":"Name TWO things you check for when judging the horse at the trot.","answer":"Straightness of action, smoothness of action, lameness"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"sr bonus","number":"3650","question":"When giving oral reasons, name 3 terms to describe a desirable walk.","answer":"Straight, smooth, well-balanced, good stride, quick, elastic"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3651","question":"When determining the quality of a horse's conformation, to what do you compare it?","answer":"Ideal horse for the breed"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3652","question":"What do the following terms have in common:  long hip, sloping shoulder, straight legs, and deep heartgirth?","answer":"They are all essentials in horse judging. (They are all good qualities in horses.)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3653","question":"In horse judging, what is the most important characteristic in equine selection other than the horse's intended use?","answer":"Balance"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3654","question":"When judging a horse, from what position would you view the length and width of the gaskin muscle?","answer":"Rear"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3655","question":"In a horse judging contest, should you prepare your notes before or after making your final placing?","answer":"Before"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"novice","number":"3656","question":"When is the best time to take notes at a judging class?","answer":"When the class is in front of you (during the class)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3657","question":"A horse that does NOT fit the general description of the ideal saddle horse is said to be what?","answer":"\"Off type\""},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3658","question":"Where should your hands be while you're delivering a set of oral reasons?","answer":"Behind your back"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3659","question":"At what distance should one stand from an oral reasons judge while delivering a set of oral reasons?","answer":"6 - 10 feet (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3660","question":"In reference to horse judging, what determines how easy your oral reasons are to follow?","answer":"How you organize them (they should be logical and clear)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3661","question":"In judging, when should you omit a difference in pairs from your reasons?","answer":"When it's minor or when it leaves room for doubt (accept either)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3662","question":"What is the maximum time for giving oral reasons?","answer":"2 (two) minutes"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"int bonus","number":"3663","question":"Name 3 important points in giving a good set of oral reasons in horse judging.","answer":"Accuracy, presentation, mental picture of the class, use of proper terms (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"medium","number":"3664","question":"How is the phrase “I grant” used in horse judging oral reasons?","answer":"Used to explain a desirable feature of a less desirable horse in a judging class"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3665","question":"What is necessary for one to properly place a class and give good reasons?","answer":"Accurate observations (knowing what you're looking at)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3666","question":"Under what conditions should you switch a pair when judging?","answer":"Only on less essential characteristics"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3667","question":"In judging contests, should one make the placing mostly on essential characteristics, less essential characteristics, or both?","answer":"Mostly on essential characteristics"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"novice","number":"3668","question":"In horse judging, what is the key to success in giving oral reasons?","answer":"Practice"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"novice","number":"3669","question":"Name ONE way to develop skills in horse judging.","answer":"Study, practice (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3670","question":"In a halter class, what is the judge looking for?","answer":"Horse that resembles the ideal for the breed"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3671","question":"When judging a halter quality class, besides having knowledge of anatomy, you should also be able to recognize what?","answer":"Unsoundness, blemishes, or conformation faults (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"sr bonus","number":"3672","question":"When judging a quality class of mules, what TWO things should be considered?","answer":"What the mules will be used for and the ideal animal for that purpose"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"sr bonus","number":"3673","question":"Name 3 things halter quality horses are judged on.","answer":"Balance, muscling, structural correctness, structural smoothness, symmetry, way of going, type, conformation, soundness, quality, substance (muscling or condition), sex characteristics (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"sr bonus","number":"3674","question":"When judging halter quality, name 3 things to look for when viewing the front of the horse from a distance.","answer":"Set of front legs; alignment of front legs; width of chest; muscling of chest, arms, and forearm; head; eyes; ears"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"easy","number":"3675","question":"How are horses usually numbered in a judging class?","answer":"1 to 4, from left to right"},
{"category":"Horse Judging","level":"jr bonus","number":"3676","question":"Name 3 ways horses are viewed in a judging class.","answer":"Left side view, front view, right side view, hind view, at the walk, at the trot"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3677","question":"When did the horse and pony program become part of the 4-H organization?","answer":"1960's"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3678","question":"What is the oldest, non-formal youth development organization in the US?","answer":"4-H"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3679","question":"2 part question:  How and why was the Cooperative Extension Service established?","answer":"By the Smith-Lever Act in 1914 as a way to distribute new research information to the states"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3680","question":"What was the name of the government act that established the Cooperative Extension Service in 1914?","answer":"Smith-Lever Act"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3681","question":"When was the Cooperative Extension Service established?","answer":"1914 (FYI: by the Smith-Lever Act)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3682","question":"You do the math…If one horse year is equal to three human years, how old is a 20 year old mare in human years?","answer":"60 years old"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3683","question":"What percentage of horses in this country are aged?","answer":"20%"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3684","question":"What do the initials AHC stand for?","answer":"American Horse Council"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3685","question":"What organization reviews and updates the Horse Industry Handbook and Youth Leaders Manual reference books?","answer":"American Youth Horse Council"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3686","question":"How did George Carlin document the impressive riding skills of the Plains Indians?","answer":"Paintings"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3687","question":"What is meant by the term \"full board\"?","answer":"Stable where your horse is kept will take care of all your horse's needs."},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3688","question":"What is the term for the service when a boarding stable takes care of all your horse's needs?","answer":"Full board"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3689","question":"To be considered a business rather than a hobby by the IRS, how many years must a horse business make a profit?","answer":"2 out of every 7 years"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3690","question":"Referring to leasing a horse, what is the difference between a lessor and a lessee?","answer":"Lessor—one who owns the horse; Lessee—one who's leasing it"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3691","question":"In regards to equine business, what does the Latin expression \"caveat emptor\" refer to?","answer":"Let the buyer beware"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3692","question":"Name 3 types of equine-related contracts.","answer":"Breeding, sales, sales agency agreement, partnership, syndication, boarding, release of liability or waiver, hauling agreement, lease, training (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3693","question":"Name 3 equine-related careers where workers do NOT work hands-on with live horses.","answer":"Cooperative Extension; Department of Agriculture; breed association;, horse council; announcer; feed industry; show organizer; equine insurance; equine lawyer; tack store; judge; barn builder; equine appraiser (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3694","question":"Horse ownership is very expensive.  What is usually the greatest horse related expense each year?","answer":"Feed (accept other correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"jr bonus","number":"3695","question":"In addition to the purchase price, name 3 essential purchases, other than hay and grain, that a new horse owner would need to make.","answer":"Halter, lead rope, bridle, saddle, buckets, fly spray, saddle pad, grooming tools, helmet, harness (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3696","question":"What represents 70% - 80% of the total cost of managing a mare to produce a foal?","answer":"Nutrition (feed)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3697","question":"Name TWO factors of the horse's life that are influenced by light.","answer":"Shedding; estrous cycle; testosterone production; sperm production"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"jr bonus","number":"3698","question":"Name 3 ways to identify a horse by its physical appearance.","answer":"Sex, height, weight, color, markings, coat pattern, brands, lip tattoos, scars, blemishes, cowlicks, hair whorls, muscular dimples or defects, chestnut patterns (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3699","question":"Name TWO things about a horse being sold or purchased that you will find listed on a bill of sale or sales contract.","answer":"Breed, age, date of birth, sex, color, markings, registered name, registration number, buyer, seller, date of purchase, purchase price, barn name (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3700","question":"Name 5 ways to visually identify a horse for registration or Coggins papers besides sex, height, weight, color, markings, and patterns.","answer":"Brands, lip tattoos, scars, blemishes, cowlicks, hair whorls, muscular dimples or defects, chestnut patterns (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3701","question":"Identification of horses or other livestock has always been a problem for owners.  If an identification system is to be successful, the identifying marks must have several characteristics.  Name 3 of these characteristics.","answer":"Visible from a distance; permanent; painless; unalterable; inexpensive; easy to apply; non-damaging; adaptable to data retrieval"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3702","question":"Name TWO types of brands or marks of identification in horses.","answer":"Hot brand, freeze brand, lip tattoo, microchip"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3703","question":"What is one of the oldest methods of marking horses for identification?","answer":"Hot branding"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3704","question":"Where is a Thoroughbred race horse tattooed?","answer":"Inside of the lip"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3705","question":"What is a brand?","answer":"Mark of identification"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3706","question":"What is the name of the branding method that uses extreme cold rather than heat?","answer":"Freeze branding"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3707","question":"If you were reading a freeze brand, what symbol would identify the animal as unregistered or grade?","answer":"Letter E"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3708","question":"When using the Y-Tex Corporation system for freeze branding, the alpha character is used to identify what?","answer":"Breed of horse (FYI:  “E” means grade or unregistered.)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3709","question":"How does freeze branding a gray horse differ from freeze branding a chestnut horse?","answer":"New hair growth after freeze branding comes in white.  When branding a gray horse, the iron is applied long enough to kill the root, thus preventing new growth so the brand can be seen"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3710","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse where brands are applied.","answer":"Cheek, neck, shoulder, hip"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3711","question":"2 part question:  You have just purchased a bay Arabian mare.  Under her mane is a white band with numerous characters composed of bars and angles.  What type of brand is this and what do the characters signify?","answer":"Freeze brand; each symbol represents a number; the entire brand gives the year the horse was born and its registry number"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3712","question":"Most equine insurance policies require you to do what if your horse is injured, ill, or lame?","answer":"Immediately notify the company"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3713","question":"What is a FLT insurance policy?","answer":"Policy that covers injury or death that results from fire, lightning or transportation"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3714","question":"What type of insurance covers the insured against bodily injury or property damage and provides for legal defense in actions alleging negligence?","answer":"Liability insurance"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3715","question":"Name 3 US states that do NOT have Equine Activity Liability Laws.","answer":"California, Maryland, Nevada, New York"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3716","question":"What is liability insurance?","answer":"Insurance that protects the insured against claims of bodily injury or property damage (it also provides for legal defense in actions alleging negligence)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3717","question":"What type of insurance offers coverage in the event that an insured horse suffers from a physical condition that makes it totally and permanently unable to fulfill its intended use?","answer":"Loss of use insurance"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3718","question":"What are the TWO general types of mortality insurance?","answer":"Full Mortality or All Risks and Specified or Named Peril"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3719","question":"What is mortality insurance?","answer":"Insurance that covers the death of the horse.  (FYI:  There are two types of mortality insurance, full mortality and specified peril.  Full mortality covers almost all causes of death.)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3720","question":"What SPECIFIC type of insurance is needed to insure a horse against death from sickness, injuries, disease, or old age?","answer":"Full mortality or all risks mortality insurance (accept either)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3721","question":"Generally, growing horses attain 90% of their adult height by what age","answer":"One year of age"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"novice","number":"3722","question":"Referring to horses, what is a hand?","answer":"Measurement of height (1 hand equals 4 inches)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3723","question":"You do the math...In inches, how tall is a 16 hand horse?","answer":"64 inches (16 x 4 = 64)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3724","question":"You do the math…A horse that is 66 inches tall would be considered to be how many hands tall?","answer":"16.2  hands tall (66 divided by 4 = 16.5 which would 16.2 hands)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"novice","number":"3725","question":"What age horses are generally preferred for novice or first time owners?","answer":"Older horses (5 years of age or older)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3726","question":"What is the main reason people own horses in the US?","answer":"Pleasure"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3727","question":"In choosing a horse or pony for a young child, what is more important than the animal's size?","answer":"Disposition or temperament (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3728","question":"What does it mean when you say a horse is syndicated?","answer":"Horse is owned by a group of people who each own shares in it."},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"int bonus","number":"3729","question":"What are 3 advantages to leasing a horse?","answer":"May satisfy desire to ride and costs less than owning; good way to determine if interest is serious before buying; good way to see if horse is compatible or what you expected; allows you to gain experience that will help you manage your own horse better"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"int bonus","number":"3730","question":"Name 3 things that should be considered in order to select the most appropriate horse for your needs and desires.","answer":"Age of rider and/or horse, experience of rider and/or horse, temperament, intended use, cost, breed, horse and rider combination, management experience, color, registered or grade (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"int bonus","number":"3731","question":"Name 3 questions you should ask the owner before buying a horse.","answer":"Why selling; health problems; soundness problems; behavioral problems; problems trailering, bathing, clipping, tying, worming, giving shots; training; specific cues (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"int bonus","number":"3732","question":"Name 3 life skills that children may develop as a result of horse ownership.","answer":"Responsibility, teamwork, self-confidence, sportsmanship, self-discipline, social skills, greater coordination, strength, and agility, healthy competitive nature"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3733","question":"If you are thinking of buying a horse, what are 3 things you should consider in deciding whether or not be become a horse owner?","answer":"Expensive to buy; expensive to take care of; time for feeding and care; time for riding and training; knowledge of feeding, care, and illnesses; you may need to pass up other activities (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3734","question":"What is a cowboy proverb about kicking a horse?","answer":"\"Kicking never gets you nowhere, less'n you're a mule.\""},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3735","question":"What famous quote about horses is attributed to Will Rogers?","answer":"\"The outside of a horse is good for the inside of a man.\""},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3736","question":"Who is the following quote attributed to, “Good fences make good neighbors”?","answer":"Robert Frost"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3737","question":"REM or deep sleep occurs only when horses are in what position?","answer":"Lying down with their muzzles touching the ground"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3738","question":"What is the name of a military division that's mounted on horseback for fighting?","answer":"Cavalry (FYI: Calvary is a biblical term.)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3739","question":"Referring to horses, what is a \"cavy\"?  (CAVE-ee)","answer":"Collection of horses"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3740","question":"What term refers to the mythological creature that had a head, torso, and arms of a man and the body and legs of a horse?","answer":"Centaur"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3741","question":"Cob or cobby are terms used in the horse industry.  Give 3 examples of how you might use these terms.","answer":"Cob-tailed—docked tail; cob-tail class—type of Hackney Pony class; cob—type of horse (short, heavyweight hunter); COB—form of feed (corn, oats, barley mix); cobby—horse that’s closely coupled and stoutly built"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3742","question":"What is the term that means \"of or pertaining to the horse\"?","answer":"Equine"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3743","question":"What is it called when an animal is roped by the forefeet?","answer":"Fore-footing"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"int bonus","number":"3744","question":"What are TWO definitions of forging as applied to horses?","answer":"Shaping of iron at the forge; striking the forefoot with the hindfoot"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3745","question":"Give 3 definitions of the term \"hack”.","answer":"Horse ridden to a hunt meet; a pleasure ride; a riding horse for hire"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3746","question":"What does the slang term “hat rack” mean when used in describing a horse?","answer":"Emaciated or very thin horse (accept either)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3747","question":"What does the term \"hippophile\" describe?","answer":"Horse lover"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3748","question":"The horse has no equal as a draft animal. Even today, tractors, automobiles, and trucks are rated in what manner reflecting on the horse?","answer":"They are compared in terms of horsepower."},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3749","question":"What does the term “Indian broke” mean?","answer":"Horse is trained to be mounted from either side."},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3750","question":"What are TWO meanings of the term \"jockey\"?","answer":"Person who rides racehorses; small flaps on each side of the saddle"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"sr bonus","number":"3751","question":"In reference to the horse world, give 3 definitions of the term \"maiden\".","answer":"Horse that's never won a race; rider or horse that's never won a ribbon; mare that's never been bred"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"hard","number":"3752","question":"What is the name for the process of heating a food material, usually a liquid, to a specific temperature for a specific length of time for the purpose of destroying bacteria?","answer":"Pasteurization"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"intermediate","number":"3753","question":"A collection of saddle horses at a roundup from which horses are chosen to be used for the day is called what?","answer":"Remuda (ray-MOO-dah)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"medium","number":"3754","question":"To ride a horse to his absolute limit so that he's exhausted and is unable to go farther is called what?","answer":"“Riding him into the ground”"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3755","question":"Give TWO definitions of the term throatlatch.","answer":"Part of the horse: space between the jaw and the neck; part of the bridle: strap that goes around the horse's throatlatch area (and keeps the bridle from slipping over the horse's head)"},
{"category":"Miscellaneous","level":"easy","number":"3756","question":"The horse, although not the fastest animal, possesses great what?","answer":"Endurance"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3757","question":"Name 2 of the 5 types of nutrients.","answer":"Water, energy (fats and carbohydrates), protein, vitamins, minerals"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3758","question":"Name 3 nutrients needed by horses.","answer":"Water, energy (fats and carbohydrates), protein, vitamins, minerals"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3759","question":"Name 5 nutrients needed by horses.","answer":"Water, energy (fats and carbohydrates), protein, vitamins, minerals"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3760","question":"What are the TWO types of nutrients that animals need in relatively small amounts?","answer":"Vitamins and minerals"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3761","question":"What nutrient is vital to life and is essential for all body systems?","answer":"Water"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3762","question":"What is the most essential, easily available, and often overlooked nutrient?","answer":"Water"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3763","question":"What is an advantage to hand watering your horse?","answer":"You can monitor how much they drink."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3764","question":"How do suckling foals meet the majority of their water needs?","answer":"Through mare's milk"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3765","question":"The water intake of individual horses with the same diet and under the same environmental and exercise conditions may vary by how much?","answer":"Up to 50%"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3766","question":"A deficit of what basic nutrient may increase the risk of impaction colic?","answer":"Water"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3767","question":"Name 3 factors that affect the water requirements for horses.","answer":"Work type, work load, diet, environment, temperature, humidity, food intake, type of food, exercise, physiological state, individual variations"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3768","question":"There are many tasks that water performs in the body.  Name 3.","answer":"Necessary for life, transports nutrients to cells, transports waste from cells, makes up most of the blood, regulates body temperature, acts as a lubricant, necessary in most of the body's chemical reactions"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3769","question":"What is the major nutritional function of carbohydrates?","answer":"Energy"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3770","question":"What is the chief form in which carbohydrates are stored in the horse's body?","answer":"Glycogen"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3771","question":"What is the term that refers to the breakdown of carbohydrates, fats, and proteins into energy with the involvement of oxygen?","answer":"Glycolysis, aerobic glycolysis, or aerobic metabolism (accept any)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3772","question":"Sugar is absorbed in what form?","answer":"Glucose (or other simple sugars)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3773","question":"What are the structural components of carbohydrates?","answer":"Simple sugars"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3774","question":"What nutrient is primarily stored in the horse's body as glycogen?","answer":"Carbohydrates (also accept glucose)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3775","question":"What happens to excess simple sugars when the glycogen storage capacity of the kidneys, liver, and muscles are full?","answer":"Stored as fat"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3776","question":"Which nutrients are more easily digested by the horse:  sugars and starches or fats?","answer":"Sugars and starches"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3777","question":"Give ONE reason why your horse's digestible energy or calorie needs may increase.","answer":"Exercise, fever, illness, parasites, growing, reproducing, outside temperature (temperature extremes), humidity (wet weather) [accept any correct answer]"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3778","question":"In reference to feeds, what does \"net energy\" mean?","answer":"Energy or calories that can actually be used by the animal."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3779","question":"2 part question:  Name a time period when the energy requirements for a broodmare increase and give the percentage of increase.","answer":"Last 1/3 of pregnancy (last trimester); increases 10 - 20% above maintenance; also during early lactation; increases 45% above late pregnancy"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3780","question":"What percentage of the available energy in feed do horses actually use?","answer":"20 - 25% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3781","question":"Which has more digestible energy per pound, Timothy hay or oats?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3782","question":"What is the most commonly used fat source in horse diets?","answer":"Vegetable oil (corn oil)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3783","question":"Which is safer to feed to meet an athletic horse's energy needs, fat or grain?","answer":"Fat"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3784","question":"Compared to proteins and carbohydrates, fats contain what percent more digestible energy on a per pound basis?","answer":"2.25%  (FYI: Fats have 9 calories/gram; proteins and carbohydrates have 4 calories/gram.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3785","question":"In the past, horse diets were formulated at 6 - 7% fat, but now some have up to what percent?","answer":"15%"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3786","question":"At room temperature what is the PHYSICAL difference between fats and oils?","answer":"Fats are solids and oils are liquids."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3787","question":"Which nutrient has the HIGHEST energy density?","answer":"Fat (FYI: Fats have 9 calories/gram; proteins and carbohydrates have 4 calories/gram)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3788","question":"Name 3 benefits of adding fat to the equine diet.","answer":"Growth, performance, stamina, body weight, helps reproductive function, helps milk production, reduce gut fill"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3789","question":"Name ONE thing omega 3 fatty acids can do in the horse’s body.","answer":"Enhance the coat; help with allergic skin conditions such as “sweet itch”"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3790","question":"What source of omega 3 fatty acids provides a significant improvement in \"sweet itch\" or other allergic skin conditions when added to the horse's diet?","answer":"Flaxseed"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3791","question":"Name 3 benefits of feeding flaxseed to horses.","answer":"Makes coat glossy (gives “bloom”); softens stools (to prevent impaction); treats allergic skin disease (“sweet itch”)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3792","question":"Give TWO examples of minerals.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, calcium, phosphorus, magnesium, potassium, sulfur; iron, copper, zinc, manganese, iodine, selenium, cobalt"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3793","question":"Iron, copper, and phosphorus are examples of which kind of nutrient?","answer":"Minerals (Do NOT accept micro-minerals because phosphorus is a macro-mineral.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3794","question":"Name ONE thing that minerals influence about other nutrients.","answer":"Absorption, metabolism, excretion of other nutrients"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3795","question":"At what TWO stages of a horse’s life are calcium needs the greatest?","answer":"Growing animals and lactating mares"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3796","question":"Name 3 minerals that should be included in a concentrate feed for foals.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, copper, zinc"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3797","question":"Name 3 minerals that are most important when feeding horses.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, selenium, sodium, chloride"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3798","question":"What is a MACRO mineral?","answer":"Mineral that's needed in large quantities"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3799","question":"Electrolytes are minerals that dissolve in water and are essential for many chemical processes in the body.  Name 3 important electrolytes that are lost in sweat.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, and potassium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3800","question":"Name 4 MACRO minerals.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, magnesium, sulfur, sodium, chloride, potassium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3801","question":"Which forage has a higher calcium content, legumes or grasses?","answer":"Legumes"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3802","question":"What is a readily available storage location in the body for calcium?","answer":"Skeleton"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3803","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen if there’s an excess of calcium in the horse's diet.  ","answer":"Prevents the absorption of phosphorus and other minerals; prevents the utilization of phosphorus and other minerals; can cause bone disease in young horses"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3804","question":"Approximately what percent of body calcium is contained in the bones and teeth?","answer":"99%"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3805","question":"Which mineral aids in muscular activity, blood clotting, blood balance, enzyme activation, and bone formation?","answer":"Calcium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3806","question":"Name 3 functions of calcium in the horse's body.","answer":"Bone or teeth formation; normal muscular action; blood clotting; enzyme action; cell membrane function; temperature regulation; neuromuscular function; blood balance"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3807","question":"Phosphorus should NEVER exceed the amount of what mineral in the horse's diet?","answer":"Calcium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3808","question":"What should the calcium to phosphorus ratio be for horse feeds?","answer":"2 to 1 (accept any ratio within the 1 to 1 to 6 to 1 ratios)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3809","question":"Give ONE result of having an inverted calcium to phosphorus ratio in your horse's ration.","answer":"Impaired calcium absorption; skeletal abnormalities"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3810","question":"What effect does excess phosphorus have on calcium?","answer":"Interferes with calcium absorption"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3811","question":"What TWO minerals are necessary for proper bone and teeth formation?","answer":"Calcium and phosphorus"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3812","question":"What percent of common salt is chloride?","answer":"61%"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3813","question":"What percent of chloride consumed by the horse is absorbed?","answer":"100%"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3814","question":"Name 3 electrolytes that are essential for maintaining fluid balance and nerve and muscle function.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, potassium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3815","question":"Name 3 electrolytes lost in sweat and urine.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, potassium, calcium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3816","question":"Name ONE circumstance when magnesium requirements are high.","answer":"Lactating mares; exercising horses"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3817","question":"60% of the magnesium in a horse's body is found where?","answer":"Skeleton (bones and teeth)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3818","question":"Give 3 results of too little magnesium in a horse's diet.","answer":"Nervousness; muscle tremors; ataxia; potential for collapse; increased respiratory rate (tachypnea); death"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3819","question":"A mare that has hyperkalemia has an abnormally high level of what electrolyte in her blood?","answer":"Potassium (FYI:  The chemical symbol for potassium is K for Kalium.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3820","question":"What is the only mineral that horses have a definite appetite for?","answer":"Sodium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3821","question":"What is the major electrolyte involved in the maintenance of the acid-base balance?","answer":"Sodium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3822","question":"Give TWO signs or symptoms of sodium deficiency.","answer":"Decreased skin turgor; desire to lick sweat-contaminated objects; decreased eating rate; lowered water intake"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3823","question":"What percent of the sodium consumed by the horse is absorbed?","answer":"75 - 100% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3824","question":"Sodium plays an important role in the function of which body system of the horse?","answer":"Nervous system"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3825","question":"Chloride in the horse's diet is usually accompanied by which other mineral?","answer":"Sodium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3826","question":"What TWO minerals are necessary in a horse's diet for the regulation of all body fluids, maintenance of acid-base fluids, and nerve impulses?","answer":"Sodium and chloride"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3827","question":"Name TWO physiological functions that will increase the natural intake of salt in a horse's diet.","answer":"Sweating and lactation"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3828","question":"Sweating and lactation are two physiological functions that will increase the free choice consumption of what mineral supplement?","answer":"Salt (sodium chloride)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3829","question":"Give 3 signs of salt poisoning.","answer":"Colic; frequent urination (polyuria); staggering; excessive thirst (polydipsia); diarrhea; weakness; paralysis of hind limbs (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3830","question":"Name ONE thing sulfur is necessary for in the horse.","answer":"Production of proteins or enzymes; carbohydrate metabolism; helps insulin function properly"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3831","question":"Excess consumption of sulfur may cause a secondary deficiency in what other mineral?","answer":"Copper (FYI:  Sulfur toxicity can result in lack of energy, colic, and eventually death.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3832","question":"What condition can iron deficiency cause?","answer":"Anemia"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3833","question":"What are trace or micro minerals?","answer":"Minerals that are only required in small amounts"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"int bonus","number":"3834","question":"Name 3 MICRO minerals.","answer":"Copper, zinc, iron, manganese, iodine, selenium, cobalt, fluorine, molybdenum, chromium, silicon"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3835","question":"Name 3 of the TRACE minerals in trace mineralized salt.","answer":"Iron, manganese, cobalt, iodine, zinc, selenium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3836","question":"What micro-mineral is essential for the synthesis of vitamin B12?","answer":"Cobalt (FYI: Vitamin B12 is cobalamin.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3837","question":"The Great Lakes basin, Rocky Mountains, Northern Great Plains, upper Mississippi Valley, and Pacific Coast regions are all deficient in iodine.  Name ONE condition that may be caused by this deficiency.","answer":"Hypothyroidism, goiter, cretinism, myxedema"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3838","question":"What mineral is necessary for proper function of the thyroid gland?","answer":"Iodine (FYI:  Thyroid hormones T3 and T4 (thyroxine) are triiodothyronine and tetraiodothyronine, compounds that contain iodine.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3839","question":"Which mineral is necessary in the blood to carry oxygen to the body's cells?","answer":"Iron"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3840","question":"What is the primary cause of iron deficiency?","answer":"Blood loss (from parasites or trauma)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3841","question":"The largest percentage of which mineral is found in the myoglobin or hemoglobin in the horse’s body?","answer":"Iron"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3842","question":"What mineral imbalance results in the condition commonly referred to as Bobtail Disease?","answer":"Excess selenium (FYI:  Bobtail disease is also called Alkali Disease.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3843","question":"Halitosis with an odor of garlic would be an indication of what specific mineral toxicity?","answer":"Selenium (FYI: Halitosis is bad breath.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3844","question":"By itself, selenium doesn't have much antioxidant capacity. Its antioxidant properties become stronger when it’s paired with which vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin E"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3845","question":"Name ONE problem selenium deficiency causes.","answer":"White muscle disease; myopathy (muscle disease); tying up; impaired movement; loss of muscular coordination; difficulty in suckling and swallowing; respiratory problems; heart problems"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3846","question":"It's important to know if your region's soil is deficient in this mineral before supplementing.  Which mineral is it?","answer":"Selenium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3847","question":"What is the main cause of selenium toxicity?","answer":"Over supplementing it"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3848","question":"Name TWO of the eight states in the U.S. that has excessively selenium-rich soils due to native plants.","answer":"California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Oregon, South Dakota, Utah, Wyoming"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3849","question":"Give 3 signs of selenium toxicity.","answer":"Blind staggers; hair loss; rough hair coat; change in hooves; horizontal hoof cracks; lameness; garlic-odor halitosis; muscle tremors; respiratory problems; death (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3850","question":"Which nutrient supplies the material from which body tissue is made?","answer":"Protein"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3851","question":"Why would a horse need a protein supplement?","answer":"When the horse isn't getting enough protein in his current diet or if his protein requirements increase (accept either)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3852","question":"What element do proteins contain that carbohydrates and fats do not?","answer":"Nitrogen"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3853","question":"Give TWO ways protein is used in the horse's body.","answer":"Formation of tissue; muscle function; production of hormones, enzymes, and antibodies"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3854","question":"Trypsin converts proteins and partially hydrolyzed proteins into what TWO things?","answer":"Peptides and amino acids"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3855","question":"When comparing the nutrient value of Timothy and orchard grass in a hay sample, which provides the highest percent of crude protein?","answer":"Orchard grass"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3856","question":"All proteins contain carbon, hydrogen, nitrogen, and oxygen.  Name ONE other element that some proteins contain.","answer":"Sulfur, phosphorus, or iron"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3857","question":"What is \"crude protein\"?","answer":"Total protein content of feed"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3858","question":"What happens when excess protein is fed?","answer":"Nitrogen is separated from the compound and is excreted in the urine; the rest of the molecule is used for energy."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3859","question":"At weaning time, most foals six months of age should be fed a diet containing what protein level?","answer":"16% (accept any number between 14% - 18%)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3860","question":"What plant provides high quality protein, high levels of lysine, and is used as a common protein supplement?","answer":"Soybean"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3861","question":"Cottonseed meal is used as what in a horse's diet?","answer":"Protein supplement"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3862","question":"What is digestible crude protein?","answer":"Amount of nitrogen content that's available to the horse during digestion"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3863","question":"What protein is the key structural component of hair and hoof horn?","answer":"Keratin"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3864","question":"After nitrogen is removed from proteins, what happens to the rest of the molecule?","answer":"It's converted into energy or stored as fat (accept either)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3865","question":"The National Research Council (NRC) recommends horse rations be balanced on percentages of what TWO things?","answer":"Crude protein and lysine"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3866","question":"What percent of proteins in grain-based diets is digested to amino acids and is absorbed from the small intestine?","answer":"50 - 70% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3867","question":"What type of feed will provide the horse with the greatest amount of crude protein?","answer":"Alfalfa (alfalfa hay)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3868","question":"What is the most economical protein supplement?","answer":"Soybean meal"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3869","question":"What are the \"bricks and mortar\" from which bodies are made?","answer":"Proteins"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3870","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse’s body that are made of the protein keratin.","answer":"Skin, hair, and hooves"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3871","question":"Give TWO reasons why additional protein is NOT a good source of energy for athletic horses.","answer":"Produces excessive body heat; increases electrolyte deficiencies; increases water loss (due to increased sweating); more expensive"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3872","question":"Name 3 protein supplements fed to horses.","answer":"Soybean meal, cottonseed meal, linseed meal, peanut meal, bone meal, fish meal, Brewer's grains, urea, milk protein"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3873","question":"Name 4 elements that make up proteins.","answer":"Carbon, hydrogen, oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, iron, phosphorus (phosphates)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3874","question":"Give 3 results of protein deficiency in horses.","answer":"Poor growth, unthrifty, weight loss, poor hair coat, decreased reproduction, poor hoof growth"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3875","question":"Give 3 reasons why it is NOT good to feed horses too much protein.","answer":"Expensive; not good for horse with kidney problems; may affect acid-base balance; may cause calcium imbalance; can't be stored (as protein) for later use"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3876","question":"What determines the quality of the proteins?","answer":"Amount of essential amino acids (FYI: The higher the essential amino acids, the higher the quality.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3877","question":"Protein supplements should contain a good mixture of what?","answer":"Essential amino acids"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3878","question":"What are considered to be the building blocks of protein?","answer":"Amino acids"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3879","question":"How many of the 22 amino acids are essential to the horse?","answer":"10 essential amino acids"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3880","question":"How many amino acids are found in proteins?","answer":"22 amino acids"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3881","question":"Where in the horse's digestive tract are amino acids synthesized?","answer":"Large intestine or hindgut (accept either)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3882","question":"Protein is composed of a chain of smaller units called what?","answer":"Amino acids (also accept polypeptides)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3883","question":"During digestion, proteins are broken down into what?","answer":"Amino acids (also accept polypeptides)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3884","question":"During rapid growth, foals need more of which TWO amino acids?","answer":"Lysine and threonine"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3885","question":"What is an essential amino acid?","answer":"Amino acid that must be supplied in the diet"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3886","question":"Name 3 essential amino acids.","answer":"Phenylalanine, tryptophan, leucine, isoleucine, lysine, methionine, valine, histidine, threonine, arginine"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3887","question":"Which protein supplement contains more lysine than most other vegetable proteins?","answer":"Soybean meal"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3888","question":"Name the amino acid necessary for growth and milk production.","answer":"Lysine"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3889","question":"Which amino acid has been found to be the most essential to the horse?","answer":"Lysine"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3890","question":"Of a weanling, yearling, or two year old, which one needs the most protein?","answer":"Weanling (FYI:  Weanlings need 14 - 18%, yearlings need 12 - 14%, and mature idle horses need 8 - 12% protein in their diets.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3891","question":"What percent protein is required by yearlings?","answer":"12 - 14% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3892","question":"A mature, idle horse needs what percentage of crude protein?","answer":"8 - 12% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3893","question":"A feed containing 10% crude protein and 15% crude fiber would be appropriate for what type of horse?","answer":"Mature idle horse (horse that's not working, growing, or producing)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3894","question":"The protein requirements are greatest and most critical during what 3 phases of a horse's life?","answer":"Growth, reproduction, and lactation"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3895","question":"What TWO vitamins are found in good quality hay?","answer":"Vitamins A and D"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3896","question":"What is one of the most unstable nutritional components of hay?","answer":"Vitamins"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3897","question":"Name the two GENERAL TYPES of vitamins.","answer":"Fat soluble and water soluble (FYI: Fat soluble vitamins are ADEK; water soluble vitamins are B and C.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3898","question":"What is required in the diet to aid in the absorption of vitamins A, D, E, and K?","answer":"Fat"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3899","question":"Why is an excess of fat soluble vitamins more detrimental than an excess of water soluble ones?","answer":"Water soluble ones are easily excreted from the body (fat soluble vitamins can be stored in the liver or in the fat)."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3900","question":"Name ONE disease condition that has been linked to excessive free radicals or a deficiency of key antioxidants.","answer":"Equine motor neuron disease (EMND), chronic rheumatic disease, degenerative joint or bone disease"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3901","question":"Name the 4 fat-soluble vitamins.","answer":"A D E K"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3902","question":"2 part question:  What vitamins are essential in the horse's diet and why?","answer":"A and E; because they can't be synthesized in the body"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3903","question":"Which TWO vitamins are water soluble?","answer":"Vitamin C and B vitamins (B complex)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3904","question":"What kind of compounds are vitamins?","answer":"Organic compounds"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3905","question":"What is the name of the essential organic compounds that are needed in small amounts by the horse?","answer":"Vitamins (FYI: Minerals are needed in small amounts, but they are not organic compounds.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3906","question":"How do vitamins differ from minerals?","answer":"Vitamins are organic (which means they contain carbon)."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3907","question":"Name 3 vitamins and give ONE thing each does in the horse's body.","answer":"Vitamin A—helps with vision, immune response; Vitamin B—most help with enzyme processes; Vitamin C—antioxidant; Vitamin D—calcium absorption and balance; Vitamin E—antioxidant; Vitamin K—blood clotting, bone metabolism, vascular health"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3908","question":"Give 3 reasons horses would need supplemental vitamins.","answer":"Prolonged drug therapy; high grain low forage diet; poor quality hay; stress; poor diet; heavy exercise; nervous horse; diseases (such as anemia); vitamin deficiencies (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3909","question":"Lack of what nutrient can cause a horse to go blind?","answer":"Vitamin A"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3910","question":"What vitamin comes from the carotene in green grass?","answer":"Vitamin A"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3911","question":"Which vitamin is higher when grass is green?","answer":"Vitamin A"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3912","question":"Name TWO things vitamin A does in the horse's body.","answer":"Needed for vision (especially night vision); needed for healthy skin, muscles, and bones; needed for a healthy immune system; involved in reproductive function; antioxidant"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3913","question":"Deficiency of what vitamin is rare if good quality hay or pasture is available?","answer":"Vitamin A"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3914","question":"What are 3 symptoms of Vitamin A deficiency?","answer":"Excessive tearing; night blindness; reduced feed intake; slow growth; reduced fertility; rough, dry, brittle, or long hair coat"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3915","question":"What is the precursor of Vitamin A?","answer":"Beta-carotene (also accept carotene)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3916","question":"What yellow pigment found in plant material is used to form Vitamin A in the horse?","answer":"Carotene or beta-carotene (accept either)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3917","question":"Why does the carotene level in old hay decrease over time?","answer":"Carotene is easily oxidized."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3918","question":"What is carotene?","answer":"Plant pigment that is converted to Vitamin A."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3919","question":"Name TWO B vitamins that brans contain.","answer":"Thiamine (B1) and Niacin (B3)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3920","question":"What vitamins are synthesized in the large intestine?","answer":"B vitamins"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3921","question":"Name 3 B vitamins by name or number.","answer":"Vitamin B1—thiamine; vitamin B2—riboflavin; vitamin B3—niacin; vitamin B5—pantothenic acid; vitamin B6—pyridoxine; vitamin B7—biotin; vitamin B9—folate (folic acid); vitamin B12—cobalamin"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3922","question":"Give the scientific name for 3 of the B vitamins.","answer":"Vitamin B1—thiamine; vitamin B2—riboflavin; vitamin B3—niacin; vitamin B5—pantothenic acid; vitamin B6—pyridoxine; vitamin B7—biotin; vitamin B9—folate (folic acid); vitamin B12—cobalamin"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3923","question":"What vitamin may be expected to maintain or improve the condition of the hooves?","answer":"Biotin (FYI: Biotin vitamin B7.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3924","question":"What forage has the highest concentration of biotin?","answer":"Alfalfa (FYI: Biotin is Vitamin B7.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3925","question":"In what TWO areas of the body is thiamin converted to its active form?","answer":"Kidneys and liver (FYI:  Thiamine is Vitamin B1.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3926","question":"Which vitamin is not needed in the horse's diet, but a lack of it in human diets causes scurvy?","answer":"Vitamin C (FYI:  Horses produce an enzyme (L-gulonolactone oxidase) in their liver that converts glucose into vitamin C.)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3927","question":"What is rickets?","answer":"Weak, deformed bones due to deficiency of calcium, phosphorus, or vitamin D"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3928","question":"Where do horses get Vitamin D?","answer":"Sunlight or sun-cured hay (accept either)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3929","question":"Why would horses stalled 24 hours a day need supplemental vitamin D?","answer":"Vitamin D comes from sunlight; if they're in the stall, they're not in the sun."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3930","question":"Which vitamin is responsible for the strength and proper development of the bones?","answer":"Vitamin D"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3931","question":"Name ONE thing Vitamin D is responsible for.","answer":"Bone strength; proper development of bones; mineral balance; calcium absorption"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3932","question":"Vitamin D regulates the absorption of what important mineral?","answer":"Calcium"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3933","question":"A deficiency of Vitamin E can cause white muscle disease.  What general age horse does this predominantly affect?","answer":"Young horses (horses less than 11 months)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3934","question":"Name TWO things vitamin E does in the body.","answer":"Antioxidant (maintains and protects cell membranes from oxidation); enhances immunity; involved in DNA production; enhances absorption and storage of Vitamin A"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3935","question":"Decreased immune function is associated with what vitamin deficiency?","answer":"Vitamin E"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3936","question":"The lack of which vitamin can cause white muscle disease?","answer":"Vitamin E"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3937","question":"Which VITAMIN is essential for blood clotting?","answer":"Vitamin K"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3938","question":"When does oxidative stress occur?","answer":"When the antioxidant defense system in the body is overwhelmed"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3939","question":"What does an antioxidant do?","answer":"Helps decrease the negative effects of free radicals"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3940","question":"What is fiber made of?","answer":"Very complex carbohydrates (such as cellulose)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3941","question":"2 part question:  When reading a feed tag, what is the best indicator of energy content and why?","answer":"Fiber content; as fiber content increases, energy content decreases"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3942","question":"Fibrous feedstuffs are broken down into volatile fatty acids.  What percent of the horse's energy needs do these acids provide?","answer":"80%"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3943","question":"Why is it important to know the fiber content of feed?","answer":"Feeds with higher fiber content have less digestible energy (because fiber is hard to digest)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3944","question":"The percentage of water and sugar in mare's milk is higher than that of cow's milk.  Name TWO components in which the mare's milk is lower.","answer":"Protein, fat, ash"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3945","question":"How is a nutritional calorie defined?","answer":"Amount of energy required to raise 1 gram of water 1 degree Celsius"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3946","question":"2 part question:  What are maltase, sucrase, and lactase and what does each do in the body?","answer":"Sugar-digesting enzymes; maltase breaks down maltose; sucrase breaks down sucrose; lactase breaks down lactose"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3947","question":"What is the most common form of malnutrition in horses in the US?","answer":"Obesity"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3948","question":"When the percentage of water, minerals, fats, and fiber are added together, the total will be somewhat less than 100 percent.  The difference is referred to as what?","answer":"Nitrogen free extract"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3949","question":"Name 3 things that many commercial supplements may include.","answer":"Vitamins, minerals, amino acids, protein, carbohydrates, fats, herbs, probiotics, microbials (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3950","question":"Name 3 nutrients that are absorbed in the small intestine.","answer":"Protein; fat; carbohydrates; vitamins—ADEK; minerals (calcium, phosphorus); components of above such as sugars, amino acids, glycerols"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3951","question":"Many factors can influence digestibility of nutrients in the digestive tract.  Name 3.","answer":"Source of feed, level of maturity, method of processing, quantity fed, frequency of feeding, rate of passage, compounds that interfere with digestion, individual differences"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3952","question":"Give ONE advantage of knowing the amount of nutrients in feed.","answer":"To determine the quality of the feed; to determine if you're feeding your horse the right feed for its needs"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"int bonus","number":"3953","question":"Energy nutrients are chemically similar to what 3 fuels we use?","answer":"Gas, coal, and oil"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3954","question":"Name 3 ways in which grains differ NUTRITIONALLY.","answer":"Energy, crude proteins, vitamins, minerals, fiber"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"int bonus","number":"3955","question":"Name 3 things that a good quality legume hay is higher in than a good quality grass hay.","answer":"Energy, protein, calcium, phosphorus, vitamin A, vitamin B"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3956","question":"Name 3 problems that can be caused by feeding either too much or too little vitamin or mineral supplements.","answer":"Muscle disorders, bone problems, hormone imbalances, poor hair coat, eye problems, decreased immune function (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3957","question":"Name TWO nutrients that are required in lesser amounts in horses with chronic renal failure.","answer":"Protein, calcium, and phosphorus"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3958","question":"Why should you feed overweight or underweight horses separately?","answer":"So you can control the amount of feed each horse gets (accurately monitor their feed intake)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3959","question":"Name ONE factor that influences a horse's nutritional requirements.","answer":"Age, size, exercise, fever, illness, injury, temperature, humidity, growth, pregnancy, lactation, breed, metabolic rate, individual differences (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3960","question":"2 part question:  Name a type of diet that is beneficial for highly competitive horse activities and name a type of diet that's detrimental to them.","answer":"Beneficial—high fat; detrimental—high protein"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3961","question":"What is the #1 principle of ration balancing?","answer":"Determine the nutrient requirements of the horse and formulate a diet to satisfy those requirements."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3962","question":"Foals can develop a metabolic bone disease called Developmental Orthopedic Disease (DOD) if fed excessive amounts of what?","answer":"Protein or phosphorus (accept either)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3963","question":"Determining whether requirements are being met for most nutrients, other than energy, is difficult without doing what?","answer":"Analyzing the diet and comparing it to animal's nutritional requirements."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3964","question":"Give ONE reason why some older horses may have higher energy requirements.","answer":"Older horses may have problems chewing, digesting, and/or absorbing nutrients."},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"jr bonus","number":"3965","question":"Name 3 factors that influence a horse’s nutritional requirements.","answer":"Age, size, exercise, fever, illness, injury, temperature, humidity, growth, pregnancy, lactation, breed, metabolic rate, individual differences (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3966","question":"Name ONE result of energy deficiency in young animals.","answer":"Slow growth; poor condition; fatigue (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"easy","number":"3967","question":"Name ONE nutrient exercising horses need more of than non-exercising horses.","answer":"Energy, water, electrolytes (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3968","question":"When are the nutrient requirements of pregnant mares greatly increased?","answer":"Last 3 months of pregnancy (third trimester)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"medium","number":"3969","question":"Water, trace mineralized salt, and good pasture or good quality hay can supply all needed nutrients for what type of horse?","answer":"Mature idle horse (mature horse that's not growing, reproducing, or working hard)"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3970","question":"To formulate or change a horse's diet, you must know what 3 things?","answer":"Animal's nutrient requirements; nutrient content of feed; amount being fed; amount needed to provide the nutrients"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3971","question":"Name TWO ways you can use Nutrition Requirement Tables.","answer":"Check to see if ration being fed is balanced; formulate an adequate ration for your horse"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"sr bonus","number":"3972","question":"Horses can be divided into classes relative to their nutritional requirements.  Name 3 of these classes.","answer":"Maintenance (mature idle), growing, pregnancy, lactating, working"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"intermediate","number":"3973","question":"In reference to feeds, what is TDN?","answer":"Total Digestible Nutrients"},
{"category":"Nutrition","level":"hard","number":"3974","question":"What is the term for the digestible organic nutrients such as protein, fiber, nitrogen-free extract, and fat?","answer":"TDN or Total Digestible Nutrients"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3975","question":"What is the difference between external and internal parasites?","answer":"External parasites live on the outside of an animal; internal parasites live inside the animal."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3976","question":"What is the difference between an ectoparasite and an endoparasite?","answer":"Ectoparasite—attaches to the skin or body openings on horse (external parasite); endoparasite—lives in the internal organs, body cavities or tissues (internal parasite)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3977","question":"What are organisms called that are in the very early stages of development such as those before hatching from the egg?","answer":"Embryos"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3978","question":"What is a plant or animal that depends on another living animal for its food and shelter?","answer":"Parasite"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3979","question":"What is a parasite?","answer":"Plant or animal that lives in or on another living organism at whose expense it gets food and shelter (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3980","question":"What is the term for a parasite that cannot survive away from the host animal?","answer":"Obligate parasite"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3981","question":"What are obligate parasites?","answer":"Parasites that can't live away from their host"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3982","question":"Which type of parasite is easier to eradicate or get rid of, external or internal?","answer":"External"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3983","question":"What are larvicides?","answer":"Insecticides designed to kill larvae"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3984","question":"What do external parasites use for comfort and shelter?","answer":"Horse's body temperature or hair (accept either)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"3985","question":"Name 3 ways insects and other arthropods adversely affect their hosts.","answer":"Suck blood, feed on mucous discharges, spread diseases, cause pain, cause sores, interfere with digestion"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3986","question":"How many pairs of wings do flies have?","answer":"1 (one) pair"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3987","question":"What are some of the most persistent pests of horses?","answer":"Flies"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3988","question":"What is \"sweet itch\"?","answer":"Hypersensitivity (allergic reaction) to the saliva of flying insects   (FYI:  Sweet itch is also called “Summer Itch” and Summer Seasonal Recurrent Dermatitis or SSRD.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3989","question":"Name ONE major breeding site for flies.","answer":"Manure, decomposing organic matter, garbage"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3990","question":"What is the easiest, non-chemical means of breaking the fly's life cycle?","answer":"Good sanitation (removing the breeding material)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3991","question":"Name TWO prerequisites for successful completion of the life cycle of house flies and stable flies.","answer":"Breeding materials, moisture, warmth"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"3992","question":"What is an excellent non-chemical way to keep flies out of areas such as feed rooms, tack rooms and box stalls?","answer":"Use screens or fans (accept either)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"int bonus","number":"3993","question":"Other than good sanitation, name 3 types of fly control.","answer":"Baits, foggers, mists, fly spray, fly tapes or strips, fly wipes, biological control (parasitic wasps)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3994","question":"Why is it more difficult to control face flies than stable flies and house flies?","answer":"Face flies feed on the face where it's difficult to apply insecticide (also accept they only land on the horse for a short period each day)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"3995","question":"When using parasitic wasps or fly predators for fly control, what must be done to be effective?","answer":"Re-apply at set intervals"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"3996","question":"What is meant by \"biological control\" of pests such as flies?","answer":"Using other insects (such as parasitic wasps) to break the life cycle"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3997","question":"The best way to control flies is to keep the barn what?","answer":"Clean"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"3998","question":"Removal of waste and decaying vegetable matter is a major factor in controlling what external parasite?","answer":"Flies"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"int bonus","number":"3999","question":"Name 3 areas that are commonly missed when cleaning up horse properties to help with fly control.","answer":"Around fence posts; outside or under fences, feeders, or hayracks; corners of stalls; around silos or other feed storage areas; around water source areas"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4000","question":"Why can continual use of insecticides to control flies have the opposite effect?","answer":"Flies can develop a resistance to the insecticide."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4001","question":"What is the most common form of commercial fly bait?","answer":"Granules"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4002","question":"What is a maggot?","answer":"Larva of an insect such as a fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4003","question":"Name the 4 stages of the fly's life cycle.","answer":"Egg, larva, pupa, adult"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"novice","number":"4004","question":"Name ONE type of fly that is a pest to horses.","answer":"House fly, stable fly, deer fly, horse fly, yellow fly, black fly, face fly, horn fly, mosquito, sand fly or biting midge, bot fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4005","question":"Name ONE type of fly that is commonly found in PASTURES.","answer":"Face fly, horn fly, horse fly, deer fly, yellow fly, eye gnat, mosquito"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4006","question":"Name ONE type of fly that is known for the female's vicious bite.","answer":"Horse fly, yellow fly, or deer fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4007","question":"Name TWO flies that have bayonet-like mouthparts.","answer":"Horse fly and deer fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"4008","question":"Name 3 types of flies that are pests to horses.","answer":"House fly, stable fly, deer fly, horse fly, yellow fly, black fly, face fly, horn fly, mosquito, sand fly or biting midge, bot fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4009","question":"2 part question:  Which fly, the house fly or the stable fly, is a more severe pest to horses and why?","answer":"Stable flies; because they have painful bites and they suck blood"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4010","question":"Name 3 types of flies that are commonly found in PASTURES.","answer":"Face fly, horn fly, horse fly, deer fly, yellow fly, eye gnat, mosquito"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4011","question":"Besides fly spray or wipes, what can you use to prevent black flies from feeding in horse's ears?","answer":"Put petroleum jelly (Vaseline) on the inside of the ears or use a fly mask with ear coverings (accept either)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4012","question":"Where on a horse do black flies feed?","answer":"Inside the ears"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4013","question":"Although black flies can infest horses, what animal do they primarily feed on?","answer":"Birds"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4014","question":"Which external parasite usually feeds on the inside ear folds and may cause a horse to be head shy?","answer":"Black flies or buffalo gnats (accept either)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4015","question":"What is another name for black flies?","answer":"Buffalo gnats"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4016","question":"Why are blowflies problematic for horses?","answer":"They lay their eggs in tissues (and their larvae feed on flesh)."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4017","question":"Which flies lay eggs in wounds?","answer":"Blowflies"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4018","question":"What fly that hovers about the horse, then quickly darts toward the animal and glues individual eggs to the hair in a matter of seconds?","answer":"Bot fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4019","question":"What fly feeds on the mucous membranes of the horse's eyes and nostrils?","answer":"Face fly (FYI:  The face fly is Musca autumnalis.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4020","question":"What do face flies feed on?","answer":"Mucous secretions from the horse's eyes and/or nostrils"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4021","question":"Where do FACE FLIES lay their eggs?","answer":"Cattle manure"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4022","question":"What is another name for cattle grubs?","answer":"Heel flies or bomb flies"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4023","question":"Which sex of the deer fly or horse fly bites?","answer":"Female"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"4024","question":"Where do HORSE flies deposit their eggs?","answer":"Plants near water, NOT manure (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4025","question":"2 part question:  After hatching, where do the larvae of the horse fly go and when do they emerge as adults?","answer":"Larvae burrow into the mud; emerge the next spring as adults"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4026","question":"Horse fly larvae spend a year burrowed in the mud.  Name ONE thing they feed on during that time.","answer":"Earthworms, insects, or small crustaceans"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4027","question":"How big is a horse fly?","answer":"1/3 - 1 inch long (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4028","question":"What is a Tabanid?","answer":"Horse fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4029","question":"How many species of tabanids (horse flies) are there?","answer":"More than 100"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4030","question":"Adult house flies can act as intermediate hosts for what parasite?","answer":"Stomach worms (Habronema)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4031","question":"Name ONE time of the day when mosquitos are most active.","answer":"Dusk or dawn"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"int bonus","number":"4032","question":"Name 3 ways to reduce your horse's exposure to mosquitos.","answer":"Keep stabled at night, keep stable lights off, have lights 50 yards away from stables, eliminate locations that serve as mosquito breeding sites, clean water troughs weekly, use mosquito repellent (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4033","question":"What is another name for biting midges?","answer":"Punkies, no-see-ums, or sand flies (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4034","question":"What part of the horse do stable flies bite?","answer":"Legs (especially the lower front legs)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4035","question":"What is the scientific name for the stable fly?","answer":"Stomoxys calcitrans (stoe-MOX-is CAL-si-trans)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4036","question":"How many eggs can a stable fly produce?","answer":"Up to 20 batches of 50 eggs each"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4037","question":"Where do STABLE FLIES prefer to lay their eggs?","answer":"In rotting hay or straw mixed with horse or cattle urine or feces"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4038","question":"What parasite causes ringworm?","answer":"Fungus"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4039","question":"Name 3 treatments for ringworm in horses.","answer":"Clip excess hair; remove hard crusts; use antifungal shampoo; apply Betadine solution; apply Nolvasan scrub; use white vinegar solution; prevent spread to other animals by disinfecting equipment"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4040","question":"If ringworm penetration is deep enough, a secondary infection may occur causing what?","answer":"Abscesses"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4041","question":"Who should you contact for information on recommended insecticides for your area?","answer":"Your vet or County Extension agent"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4042","question":"What causes most insecticide resistance problems?","answer":"Over use of insecticides"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4043","question":"A horse that has pediculosis is infested with what type of external parasite?","answer":"Lice"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4044","question":"2 part question:  During what season are lice more of a problem and why?","answer":"Winter because lice can reproduce and spread easier in long hair"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4045","question":"Name 3 areas of the horse where lice are usually first noticed.","answer":"Head, mane, neck, tail"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4046","question":"Name TWO ways lice can be spread from one horse to another.","answer":"Direct horse to horse contact; indirect contact (carried on harness, saddle, blanket, brushes, etc.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4047","question":"Where do adult lice attach their eggs?","answer":"To the hair"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4048","question":"What are nits?","answer":"Lice eggs"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4049","question":"How long can lice live off the host animal?","answer":"3 (three) days"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4050","question":"Name 3 symptoms of lice infestation.","answer":"Unthriftiness, rubbing, biting, patches of skin without hair"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4051","question":"Name 3 treatments for lice in horses.","answer":"Insecticides (permethrin); dewormers (Ivermectin or Moxidectin); dandruff shampoos (keratolytic, selenium sulfide); clip long hair; prevent spread by washing equipment; repeat treatments as recommended by vet"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4052","question":"Which parasite of the horse comes in two main types, biting and sucking?","answer":"Lice"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4053","question":"Name the TWO general kinds of lice.","answer":"Biting and sucking"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4054","question":"What parasite causes communicable dermatitis by burrowing into the skin to feed, live, and reproduce?","answer":"Mite or mange mite (accept either)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4055","question":"Name TWO types of external parasites that infest horses that are in the class Arachnida and are “related” to spiders.","answer":"Mites and ticks (FYI:  Arachnids have 8 jointed legs and are, therefore, NOT insects which have 6 jointed legs.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4056","question":"What small arthropod causes mange?","answer":"Mites"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4057","question":"Where do sarcoptic mites reproduce and lay their eggs?","answer":"Under the skin"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4058","question":"How do you verify a mange infestation?","answer":"By skin scrapings"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4059","question":"How does stage to stage transition occur in mites?","answer":"By molting"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4060","question":"Irritation, itching, inflammation, loss of hair, crusty scab formation, and skin folding are symptoms of what condition caused by external parasites?","answer":"Mange (FYI:  Mange is caused by mites.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4061","question":"Name 3 symptoms of mange.","answer":"Irritation, itching, inflammation, loss of hair, crusty scabs, skin folding"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4062","question":"Name 3 treatments for mange in horses.","answer":"Insecticides (permethrin); dewormers (Ivermectin or Moxidectin); special shampoos; clip long hair; prevent spread by washing equipment; lime-sulfur solutions; steroids for pruritus (itching); repeat as recommended by vet"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4063","question":"A horse with mange has to be treated how often to avoid re-infestation?","answer":"Every 7 days"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4064","question":"There are 3 types of mange:  sarcoptic (sar-COP-tic), psoroptic (sore-OP-tic), and chorioptic (core-ee-OP-tic).  Name the part of the horse that each affects.","answer":"Sarcoptic (sahr-COP-tic)—head, neck, and shoulders; psoroptic (sore-OP-tic)—sheltered parts of body such as under the forelock, mane, and tail (wet mange); chorioptic (core-ee-OP-tic)—lower parts of legs (leg mange)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4065","question":"Name 3 mites that cause mange in horses.","answer":"Sarcoptes (sahr-COP-tees), Psoroptes (sore-OP-tees), Chorioptes (core-ee-OPT-tees), Demodex"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4066","question":"Which type of mite may cause foot mange resembling scratches?","answer":"Chorioptes (core-ee-OP-tees)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4067","question":"Which mite causes lumps or knots under the skin?","answer":"Demodex"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4068","question":"Why is psorptic mange called \"wet\" mange? (sore-AHP-tic)","answer":"Psorptic mite feeds by breaking the skin which causes oozing (that covers the feeding mite)."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4069","question":"Wet mange is caused by which mite?","answer":"Psorptes equi (sore-AHP-tees ee-kweye)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4070","question":"What is a pupa?","answer":"Life cycle stage of an insect (usually motionless) between the larval and adult stage (also accept chrysalis)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4071","question":"What is molting?","answer":"Shedding hair, feathers, horns, or outer layer of skin (accept any)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4072","question":"How do ticks breathe?","answer":"By means of spiracles or holes found on the abdomen"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4073","question":"Name 3 things heavy tick infestations can cause—other than specific diseases.","answer":"Blood loss (anemia); tick bite paralysis (caused by toxins); loss of appetite; weight loss (emaciation); depression; debilitation"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4074","question":"Name 3 parts of the body that ticks normally infest.","answer":"Ears, neck, withers, mane, tail, flanks, chest, under chin"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4075","question":"Which external parasite attaches to its host and feeds on its blood?","answer":"Tick"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4076","question":"What do ticks feed on?","answer":"Blood"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4077","question":"What is another name for the 6-legged larva of the tick?","answer":"Seed tick"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4078","question":"Name the 4 life cycle stages of the tick.","answer":"Egg, larva (seed tick), nymph, adult"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4079","question":"Name 3 types of ticks that can infest horses.","answer":"Lone Star tick, Cayenne tick, Gulf Coast tick, winter tick, American dog tick, Tropical Horse tick, Western black legged tick, spinose ear tick, Rocky Mountain wood tick, deer tick, bear tick"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4080","question":"Although the American dog tick is not a known vector of disease in horses, extreme infestations can result in several problems. Name ONE.","answer":"Blood loss (anemia); tick bite paralysis (caused by toxins); loss of appetite; weight loss (emaciation); depression; debilitation"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4081","question":"The American dog tick is a 3 host tick.  What does that mean?","answer":"Each life stage feeds on a different host."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4082","question":"Which tick carries Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever?","answer":"American dog tick or Rocky Mountain wood tick (accept either)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4083","question":"Which tick is a vector for Lyme disease?","answer":"Ixodes ticks (such as deer tick, bear tick, or Western black-legged tick) (accept any)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4084","question":"Which tick is a vector for Equine Piroplasmosis?","answer":"Tropical horse tick"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"4085","question":"Name the 3 of the 5 most common external parasites.","answer":"Flies, lice, mites, ticks, ringworm (fungus)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4086","question":"Which TWO external parasites are communicable to man?","answer":"Ringworm and mites (mange mites)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4087","question":"If a horse suddenly starts rubbing its tail or rump, it's commonly thought to be caused by pinworms.  However, there are other parasites that can cause this.  Name TWO other parasite that would cause this behavior in horses.","answer":"Lice, mange mites, biting midges (also called punkies or no-see-ums)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4088","question":"Name the 5 most common external parasites.","answer":"Flies, lice, mites, ticks, ringworm (fungi)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4089","question":"Name ONE general type of horse that is very susceptible to internal parasites.","answer":"Young, thin, old, or horses in poor condition"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4090","question":"What age horses are affected by strongyles and bots?","answer":"All ages"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"int bonus","number":"4091","question":"Name TWO types of internal parasites that affect horses of all ages.","answer":"Strongyles, bots, tapeworms, pinworms"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4092","question":"Internal parasites are particularly harmful to foals and young horses up to what age?","answer":"18 months to 2 years (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4093","question":"Name ONE internal parasite that is found more commonly in young horses.","answer":"Roundworms (ascarids); threadworms (strongyloides)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4094","question":"As a rule of thumb, about 20% of the horses in any herd are responsible for what percent of internal parasite egg production?","answer":"80%"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4095","question":"The tendency of some horses to harbor large numbers of internal parasites and, therefore, shed large egg amounts is due to what?","answer":"Genetic traits"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4096","question":"Horses can be grouped into low, medium, and high \"contaminators\" according to their fecal egg counts. Give the approximate egg count for each group.","answer":"Low:  counts below 200; medium:  counts between 200 – 500; high:  counts above 500"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"4097","question":"To eliminate parasite problems from your horse, all of your parasite control procedures are directed to accomplishing what key event?","answer":"Interruption of the parasite life cycle"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4098","question":"What is it called when medication is given to decrease the number of internal parasites in horses?","answer":"Deworming (also accept \"worming\")"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4099","question":"What is an anthelmintic? (ant-hell-MINT-ic)","answer":"Dewormer (\"wormer\")"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4100","question":"Explain how to determine which drugs are still effective against the internal parasites on your farm.","answer":"Worm horses. 4 months later do fecal egg counts on 10% of the herd. Worm those horses with the drug of interest. Do another fecal egg count 2 weeks later to test the effectiveness of the drug."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4101","question":"What is ERP or egg reappearance period?","answer":"Time between deworming and the reappearance of eggs in the manure"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4102","question":"Generally, what is the egg reappearance period for the following drug classes:  a) Piperazine, Benzimidazole, and Pyrantel, b) Ivermectin, and c) Moxidectin","answer":"a) 4 weeks or less, b) 6 - 8 weeks, c) 10 - 12 weeks"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"4103","question":"How can you evaluate the effectiveness of dewormers?","answer":"Have a vet do a fecal egg count."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4104","question":"What is a fecal egg count?","answer":"Lab procedure used to determine the number of parasite eggs in a fecal sample"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4105","question":"Why should you rotate or alternate chemical deworming products?","answer":"Worms can develop resistance."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4106","question":"What may happen if horses are dewormed too frequently?","answer":"Parasites may develop resistance."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4107","question":"What is \"anthelmintic resistance\"?","answer":"Ability of worms to survive doses of anthelmintics (dewormers) which had previously been effective"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4108","question":"A fecal egg count reduction test can tell you if resistance has occurred on your farm.  Below what percent of the number of eggs shed by a horse indicates resistance?","answer":"80% (FYI:  Perform fecal egg count, deworm, and repeat fecal egg count in two weeks.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4109","question":"What is “tubing” a horse?","answer":"Inserting a nasogastric tube to release gas or to give medications such as dewormers or medicines for colic"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4110","question":"What is the most common form of anti-parasitic compound for horses?","answer":"Paste"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4111","question":"Give 3 examples of purge deworming.","answer":"Paste; nasogastric or stomach tube; using feed as carrier"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4112","question":"How often should horses be dewormed?","answer":"As recommended by your vet; 2 times a year (spring and fall); 4 times a year; every 2 months; daily with certain types of wormers (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4113","question":"Name TWO times of the year that are most important to deworm horses.","answer":"Spring and fall (FYI:  Time deworming to when parasite eggs are at their peak in the environment.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4114","question":"Give TWO reasons why no deworming schedule fits every horse.","answer":"Local parasite resistance, fecal egg count of horse, age of horse, health of the horse, number of horses on farm, climate"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4115","question":"No deworming schedule fits all horses.  Name 3 factors that would influence your deworming program.","answer":"Climate, humidity, rainfall, season, concentration of horses, size of pasture, age of horses, parasite infection history, travel of horses out of facility, fecal egg count"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4116","question":"Explain why a boticide should be given one month after the first frost?","answer":"First frost will kill the adult flies; if a boticide is used one month later, the hatched larvae (that have migrated to the stomach) will be killed."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4117","question":"Customizing your internal parasite control program will reduce your cost and diminish resistance in parasites.  Give the general recommended worming schedule for low, medium, and high contaminators.","answer":"Low (fecal egg counts of less than 200)—2 times a year in spring and fall; medium (fecal egg counts of 200 – 500)—3 times a year; high (fecal egg count over 500)—4 times a year"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"4118","question":"2 part question:  When deworming, what stage of the worm's life cycle do you particularly want to destroy and why?","answer":"Adult; so they can't lay eggs"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4119","question":"Fenbendazole, Piperazine, Pyrantel and Ivermectin are examples of what type of medication?","answer":"Anthelminitic (dewormer)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4120","question":"Give 3 generic wormer names.","answer":"Ivermectin, Pyrantel, Fenbendazole, Oxibendazole, Moxidectin, Praziquantel, Piperazine"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4121","question":"Name the dewormer that's available in alfalfa-flavored pellets that is designed to be fed on a daily basis.","answer":"Strongid C"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4122","question":"Praziquantel and pyrantel pamoate are both effective for the control of tapeworms. How does the dosage of pyrantel pamoate need to be altered when treating tapeworms?","answer":"Give twice the standard dose"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4123","question":"What anthelmintic is the most effective against tapeworms?","answer":"Praziquantel (found in Equimax, Quest Plus, and Zimectrin Gol d[FYI:  Pyrantel pamoate is effective, but twice the standard dose must be given.]"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4124","question":"Which TWO external parasites are intermediate hosts for Habronemiasis?","answer":"House fly and stable fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4125","question":"What is the COMMON name for dermatitis granulosa?","answer":"Summer sores (FYI: caused by Habronema larvae)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4126","question":"What causes summer sores?","answer":"Stomach worms (Habronema larvae)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4127","question":"What skin problem of horses is a possible result of the internal parasite Habronema?","answer":"Summer sores (dermatitis granulose)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4128","question":"Horses infected with lungworms have generally been exposed to what animal?","answer":"Donkey"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4129","question":"What type of parasite usually only occurs in horses that are grazed in pastures with donkeys?","answer":"Lungworms"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4130","question":"What is the most obvious clinical sign of pinworm infestation?","answer":"Rubbed tail or rump; bare patches on the tail head or buttocks (accept any)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4131","question":"Name ONE parasite that causes a horse to rub his rump against posts, trees, or other objects.","answer":"Pinworms, mites, or lice"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4132","question":"Name ONE area where pinworm eggs be found.","answer":"Around the horse’s anus; in the pasture, feces, bedding, feeding areas, or water"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4133","question":"Where do pinworms mature?","answer":"Large intestine"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4134","question":"Which is more important in parasite control, treatment or prevention?","answer":"Prevention"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4135","question":"How does dragging, harrowing, or mowing pastures kill internal parasites?","answer":"Breaks up manure piles and exposes larvae to sun and high temperatures which kill them. (FYI:  Horses can return to the pasture within 3 weeks after dragging.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4136","question":"Give ONE reason why horses should never be fed on the ground.","answer":"Horses can get parasites; horses can eat sand and develop colic."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4137","question":"In reference to parasites, what can happen if a pasture is overgrazed?","answer":"Horse can get worms (Pasture can become a serious source of parasite infections.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"intermediate","number":"4138","question":"Besides deworming, name TWO management practices that help reduce internal parasite infestations.","answer":"Have vet do fecal egg counts; remove bot eggs; good feeding practices (don’t feed on the ground, provide clean water, don’t overcrowd pastures, rotate pastures); manage manure properly (clean stalls, compost manure, drag pastures)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4139","question":"What is a DISADVANTAGE of harrowing or dragging your pasture in the fall?","answer":"High temperatures are needed to kill parasite eggs.  If you drag the pasture in the fall when it has gotten cooler, it can leave the pasture uniformly contaminated until the following spring."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4140","question":"Name 3 management practices, NOT including deworming, that have been found to be effective in reducing parasite numbers.","answer":"Have vet do fecal egg counts; remove bot eggs; good feeding practices (don’t feed on the ground, provide clean water, don’t overcrowd pastures, rotate pastures); manage manure properly (clean stalls, compost manure, drag pastures)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4141","question":"2 part question: In reference to parasites, what are refugia and why should they be kept as large as possible?","answer":"Refugia are the worms that have not been exposed to chemicals; reason—the resistant genes will be diluted by the susceptible genes of the refugia"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4142","question":"What is a nematode?","answer":"Roundworm (includes ascarids, filarias, hookworms, pinworms, and whipworms)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4143","question":"What is the COMMON name for Parascaris equorum?","answer":"Roundworms (also accept ascarids or nematodes)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4144","question":"What parasite may cause fever, cough, and nasal discharge and is commonly referred to as a “summer cold” in foals?","answer":"Roundworms (ascarids, nematodes, or Parascaris equorum)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4145","question":"Why might a horse showing pulmonary symptoms of ascarids have a negative fecal count?","answer":"These symptoms are associated with immature worms, not egg-laying adults."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4146","question":"The more mature ascarids are, the more they are susceptible to what?","answer":"Deworming agents"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4147","question":"Why are horses older than 18 months not commonly infected with ascarids?","answer":"They develop immunity after being exposed early in life."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4148","question":"Generally speaking, what age horses are ascarid or roundworm infections restricted to?","answer":"Young horses (generally under 18 months)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4149","question":"Name TWO organs where you might find Parascaris equorum as either adults or larvae.","answer":"Small intestine, lungs, liver (also are briefly in the stomach)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4150","question":"How long is the life cycle of the ascarid?","answer":"2 - 3 months or 10 - 12 weeks (accept any number within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4151","question":"Describe 3 life cycle stages of ascarids or roundworms.  (FYI:  Ascarid life cycle is about 3 months.)","answer":"Eggs passed out to pasture; eggs are swallowed; larvae hatch in intestinal tract; larvae migrate through blood stream to the liver and lungs; larvae are coughed up and swallowed; worms mature and reproduce in the small intestines"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4152","question":"Which internal parasite's eggs are very resistant to the outside environment and may survive as long as a decade?","answer":"Ascarids or roundworms (accept either)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4153","question":"Where do ascarid larvae go after penetrating the stomach wall?","answer":"Into the bloodstream (where they migrate to the liver and lungs)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4154","question":"How do ascarid larvae get out of the lungs to the small intestine?","answer":"They're coughed up and then swallowed."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4155","question":"Where do ascarid larvae develop into mature worms?","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4156","question":"Give 3 examples of problems caused by ascarids.","answer":"Chronic enteritis; disruption of digestive system; decreased absorption of nutrients; pulmonary or lung problems; destruction when migrating through liver or lungs; peritonitis; intestinal obstruction or rupture"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4157","question":"How long are ascarids or roundworms?","answer":"5 - 15 inches (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4158","question":"What is the most common cause attributed to coughing, pot bellies, and rough hair coats in young horses?","answer":"Worms (specifically ascarids or roundworms)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"int bonus","number":"4159","question":"Name 3 signs of internal parasite infestation.","answer":"Rough coat, pot belly, un-thriftiness, slow growth, weight loss, tail rubbing, diarrhea, colic, cough, lameness, blood clots, death, depression, bronchitis, pneumonia, decreased work efficiency, poor utilization of feed, bacterial or fungal disease"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4160","question":"Describe stage 5 of the ascarid life cycle.","answer":"Develop into mature worms and begin egg production"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4161","question":"What happens in stage 4 in the life cycle of an internal parasite?","answer":"Migration of immature worms through the horse's tissues"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"int bonus","number":"4162","question":"Describe 3 general stages of the life cycle of internal parasites.","answer":"Eggs passed out to pasture; eggs hatch and become infective; larvae crawl up grass and are eaten by horse; immature worms migrate; mature worms reproduce"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4163","question":"In reference to parasites, what are larvae?","answer":"Immature, worm-like developmental stage of certain parasites"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4164","question":"In the 5 stage cycle of the life cycle of a parasite, what happens in stage 1?","answer":"Eggs are passed out to pasture."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4165","question":"Tapeworms live at the junction of the small intestine and cecum.  The presence of large numbers of tapeworms may result in what?","answer":"Intestinal blockage (colic)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4166","question":"The orbatid mite is the intermediate host for which internal parasite?","answer":"Tapeworm"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4167","question":"Tapeworms infect horses through which intermediate host?","answer":"Mites (specifically oribatid mite)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4168","question":"What is the GENUS of this parasite?  Adult horses rarely have clinical problems.  This parasite primarily affects nursing foals.  The small, thread-like adult worms in the small intestine can cause diarrhea and un-thriftiness.","answer":"Strongyloides (FYI: Genus and species is Strongyloides westeri.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4169","question":"Give ONE way foals are infected with strongyloides or threadworms.","answer":"Ingest larvae in mare's milk; ingest in pasture or paddock; threadworm penetrating skin"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4170","question":"Which type of worm affects foals almost exclusively causing diarrhea, dehydration, and weight loss?","answer":"Threadworms, strongyloides, or Strongyloides westeri (accept any) (Do NOT accept strongyles.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4171","question":"Most foals infected with threadworms don't show any symptoms.  For those that do, what is the main symptom?","answer":"Diarrhea"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4172","question":"Why is it important to know the life cycle of various parasites?","answer":"So you can control them (so you can have an effective parasite control program)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"jr bonus","number":"4173","question":"Name 3 internal parasites of horses.","answer":"Bloodworms (strongyles), roundworms (ascarids), threadworms (strongyloides), pinworms, bots, tapeworms"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4174","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC name for 3 of the following 4 types of parasites:  large pinworms, bloodworms, roundworms, and threadworms.","answer":"Oxyuris equi (large pinworms); Strongylus vulgaris (bloodworms); Parascaris equorum (roundworms); Strongyloides westeri (threadworms)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4175","question":"Name 4 types of internal parasites of horses.","answer":"Strongyles (bloodworms), ascarids (roundworms), strongyloides (threadworms), pinworms, bots, tapeworms"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4176","question":"Name TWO internal parasites that are the most problematic in horses.","answer":"Strongyles (bloodworms) (most dangerous; cause blood clots, anemia, and emaciation); small strongyles (cyathostomes) (most resistant); tapeworms (anoplocephala) (increased in numbers; can cause ulcers, obstruction, intussusception, etc.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4177","question":"Environmental conditions are critical to the transmission of Strongyles.  Eggs will only hatch and develop into infective larvae at what temperature?","answer":"45 - 85 degrees (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4178","question":"What internal parasite causes damage to the arterial walls?","answer":"Strongyles (also called bloodworms or Strongylus vulgaris)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4179","question":"Give the SCIENTIFIC name of the following parasite:  life cycle takes 6 - 11 months; adults are in the large intestine; larvae migrate to the cranial mesenteric artery and may form clots.","answer":"Strongylus vulgaris (FY: Other species of large strongyles are Strongylus edentatus and Strongylus equinus.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4180","question":"What is another name for strongyles?","answer":"Bloodworms"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4181","question":"What forms as a result of the bloodworms migrating in the arteries?","answer":"Blood clots"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4182","question":"Which internal parasite is the most common and most significant?","answer":"Strongyles (also called bloodworms or Strongylus vulgaris)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4183","question":"What blood vessel is damaged by Strongylus vulgaris?","answer":"Cranial mesenteric artery"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4184","question":"Approximately what percent of horses in a herd are able to maintain relatively low numbers of strongyles without any deworming?","answer":"50%"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4185","question":"What are the scientific names for the three types of large strongyles?","answer":"Strongylus vulgaris, Strongylus edentatus, Strongylus equinus"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4186","question":"Describe 3 life cycle stages of strongyles or bloodworms.  (FYI:  Strongyle life cycle is 8 - 11 months.)","answer":"Eggs passed out to pasture; two larval stages outside the horse; 3rd larval stage ingested by horse; 4th larval stage leaves large intestine and migrates to the cranial mesenteric artery; worms mature and reproduce in the large intestines"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4187","question":"How long are most strongyles?","answer":"Less than one inch long (FYI:  Most are so small that they are difficult to see without a magnifying glass or microscope.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4188","question":"Small strongyles are almost universally resistant to what drug class?","answer":"Benzimidazoles (also accept pyrantel) (FYI:  Small strongyles belong to the cyathostome family, they live in the cecum and large colon of the horse, and they cause significant problems.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4189","question":"How can you totally eradicate large strongyles from a closed herd?","answer":"Use 1 larvicidal treatment every 6 months; since the life cycle is approximately 6 - 8 months, all will be eradicated within 18 months in a closed herd"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4190","question":"Which internal parasite of the horse spends its adult life outside of the horse?","answer":"Bot fly"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4191","question":"What insect does the adult bot fly look like?","answer":"Honeybee"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4192","question":"During what seasons do bots detach themselves from the stomach wall and are passed outside in the feces?","answer":"Spring and summer"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4193","question":"How long does the mature bot fly take to emerge from the pupa case?","answer":"1 - 2 months (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4194","question":"How long does it take for the bot egg to mature in the stomach?","answer":"8 months (FYI:  Larvae can live within the horse for up to one year.)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4195","question":"Describe 3 life cycle stages of common bots.  (FYI:  Common bots are Gasterophilus intestinalis and their life cycle is 9 - 12 months.)","answer":"Bot fly lays eggs; horse bites or licks eggs; eggs hatch in mouth; 1st larval stage migrates; 2nd larval stage; 3rd larval stage attaches to stomach wall; larvae passed out in feces; pupae develop in soil; adult flies"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4196","question":"During what time of the year are adult bot flies most active?","answer":"Late summer to early fall (accept either)"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4197","question":"Where on the horse do bot eggs hatch?","answer":"In the horse's mouth"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4198","question":"What causes bot eggs to hatch?","answer":"Moisture and warmth from the horse's tongue"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"easy","number":"4199","question":"How can you remove bot eggs?","answer":"Scrape them off"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"int bonus","number":"4200","question":"Name 3 areas on the horse where the bot fly lays her eggs.","answer":"Legs, shoulders, flank, mane, belly, chin, under the jaw, nose, chest, neck"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4201","question":"When the horse licks or bites itself where bot fly eggs are attached, what does this do?","answer":"Stimulates the hatching of the bot eggs"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4202","question":"Where in the horse’s digestive tract do bot larvae attach?","answer":"Stomach"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4203","question":"How do bot fly larvae usually get into the horse's mouth?","answer":"Horse bites or licks at areas where eggs are laid which stimulates the hatching of the eggs."},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4204","question":"A large infestation of bots can cause paralysis of what part of the digestive tract?","answer":"Esophagus"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"medium","number":"4205","question":"How many species of bot fly are there?","answer":"At least 3 species of bot flies"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"sr bonus","number":"4206","question":"2 part question:  There are 3 types of Gasterophilus or horse bot flies.  Give either their common name or scientific name and identify one area on the horse where they deposit their eggs.","answer":"Gasterophilus intestinalis (common bot fly)—legs, chest, neck, stomach, flanks; Gasterophilus nasalis (throat bot fly)—under jaw, throat; Gasterophilus hemorrhoidalis (nose bot fly)—upper and lower lips"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4207","question":"What is the scientific name for the common horse bot?","answer":"Gasterophilus intestinalis"},
{"category":"Parasites","level":"hard","number":"4208","question":"What color are the eggs of the nose bot fly?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4209","question":"What are sex characteristics?","answer":"Masculinity in the stallion and femininity in the mare"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"jr bonus","number":"4210","question":"What are the terms used for a baby horse, a baby female horse, and a baby male horse?","answer":"Baby horse—foal; baby female horse—filly; baby male horse—colt"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4211","question":"In reference to male horses, what does it mean to alter or geld?","answer":"Castrate a male horse"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4212","question":"In reference to male horses, what does \"alter\" mean?","answer":"To castrate or geld a horse"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"int bonus","number":"4213","question":"Give 3 advantages to gelding a horse.","answer":"Safer for children and novice horsemen; no accidental pregnancies; less prone to injuries; easier to care for; easier to haul; can keep in pen with mares; can keep in pen with geldings"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4214","question":"Give 3 terms that mean the removal of the testicles in a horse.","answer":"Alter, geld, castrate"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4215","question":"What is the mother of a horse called?","answer":"Dam"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4216","question":"What is the term for a young or immature female horse?","answer":"Filly"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4217","question":"What is a filly?","answer":"Young or immature female horse (female horse 3 years old and younger)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4218","question":"The owner of the mare at the time of breeding is called what?","answer":"Breeder"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4219","question":"What is the breeding term for the offspring of a DAM?","answer":"Produce"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4220","question":"What is a mare?","answer":"Mature female horse (female horse 4 years old and older)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4221","question":"What is a colt or filly under one year of age called?","answer":"Foal"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4222","question":"What is a foal?","answer":"Colt or filly under one year of age (baby horse)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4223","question":"What is a weanling?","answer":"Weaned foal (FYI: Foals are weaned at 4 - 6 months.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4224","question":"What is a \"long yearling\"?","answer":"Horse between 1 and 2 years of age (that's closer to 2)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4225","question":"What does the term \"proud cut\" mean?","answer":"Gelding that shows stallion-like behavior"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4226","question":"What is the correct term for a male foal or an immature male horse?","answer":"Colt"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4227","question":"What is a colt?","answer":"Male foal or immature male horse (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4228","question":"What is another name for a ridgling?","answer":"Cryptorchid"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4229","question":"What is the term used when a male horse has retained one or both testicles in his body cavity?","answer":"Ridgling or cryptorchid (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4230","question":"What is a \"ridgling\"?","answer":"Male horse that has retained one or both testicles in his body cavity."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4231","question":"What is the term for an altered or castrated male horse?","answer":"Gelding"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4232","question":"What is a gelding?","answer":"Castrated male horse"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4233","question":"What is the breeding term for the offspring of a SIRE?","answer":"Get"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4234","question":"In reference to reproduction, what does the term \"entire\" mean?","answer":"Stallion (Male animal that has not been castrated.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4235","question":"What is the father of a horse called?","answer":"Sire"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"novice","number":"4236","question":"What do you call an unaltered male horse?","answer":"Stallion (also accept stud)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4237","question":"2 part question:  Define sex organs and name the sex organs of the mare and of the stallion.","answer":"Organs that produce sex cells; ovaries and testes"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4238","question":"Name 3 parts of the reproductive tract of the mare.","answer":"Ovaries, oviducts or fallopian tubes, uterus, cervix, vagina, vulva"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4239","question":"What are the two, tough sheet-like structures that suspend the uterus?","answer":"Broad ligaments"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4240","question":"Weakening of the broad ligaments can cause a downward tilting of the uterus and can predispose a mare to uterine infections and infertility.  Other than injury and illness, name TWO things that would contribute to the weakening of these ligaments.","answer":"Age of mare; number of pregnancies the mare has had"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4241","question":"What is the corpus luteum?","answer":"Mass that forms on the ovary after ovulation (in the ovulation fossa) that produces the hormone progesterone (that helps maintain pregnancy)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4242","question":"What is the funnel-like membrane which surrounds the ovary and catches the egg when it's released?","answer":"Infundibulum"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4243","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is the infundibulum?","answer":"Funnel-like membrane that surrounds the ovary and catches the egg"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4244","question":"What organ is responsible for the production of estrogen and progesterone?","answer":"Ovary"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4245","question":"What is ovulation?","answer":"Release of egg from the ovary"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4246","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is a follicle?","answer":"Bubble-like structure on the ovary which contains the egg"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4247","question":"What is the primary sex organ of the mare?","answer":"Ovary"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4248","question":"How many follicles are on an ovary?","answer":"Hundreds"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4249","question":"What is an ovary?","answer":"Female sex organ that produces eggs (and sex hormones such as estrogen and progesterone)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4250","question":"2 part question:  What are the size and the shape of the ovaries?","answer":"2 - 3 inches long; bean shaped"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4251","question":"What tube in the mare carries the egg from the ovary to the uterus?","answer":"Oviduct or Fallopian tube (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4252","question":"What is another name for the oviducts?","answer":"Fallopian Tubes"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4253","question":"Name ONE function of the cilia in the oviducts.","answer":"Helps move egg down the oviduct; helps move sperm up the oviduct"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4254","question":"What is the scientific name for the egg?","answer":"Ovum (FYI: Ovum is singular; ova is plural.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4255","question":"What are the names of the sex cells that ovaries produce?","answer":"Ova (eggs)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4256","question":"What is mastitis?","answer":"Inflammation or infection of the udder (mammary gland)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4257","question":"On a mare's udder, how many teats does she have?","answer":"2 (two) teats"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4258","question":"What is another name for the mare's mammary gland?","answer":"Udder"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4259","question":"What is the term for a bacterial infection of the udder?","answer":"Mastitis"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4260","question":"Which layer of the mare's uterus is responsible for the powerful contractions which expel the foal at birth?","answer":"Myometrium (middle layer)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4261","question":"What is the main purpose of the myometrium?","answer":"Contractions that expel the foal at birth"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4262","question":"What is the reproductive organ that holds the fetus from conception to birth?","answer":"Uterus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4263","question":"What is the largest part of the female reproductive system?","answer":"Uterus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4264","question":"What is the name for the inner lining of the uterus?","answer":"Endometrium (in-doe-MEE-tree-um)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4265","question":"What is name of the muscular tissue that is a physical barrier between the vagina and uterus?","answer":"Cervix"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4266","question":"What is the name for the structure in the abdomen that's multi-layered, hollow, Y-shaped, and is suspended by the broad ligaments?","answer":"Uterus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4267","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is the endometrium? (in-doe-MEE-tree-um)","answer":"Inner lining of the uterus "},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4268","question":"Name the 3 layers of the uterus.","answer":"Endometrium, myometrium, and serosa (perimetrium)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4269","question":"Into what organ in the mare does a stallion deposit sperm during mating?  The foal also passes through this during birth.","answer":"Vagina"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4270","question":"2 part question:  What is the birth canal and what organs does it consist of?","answer":"Canal through which the unborn animal passes at birth; consists of cervix and vagina"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4271","question":"What is the purpose of a Caslick's operation?","answer":"Seal the vulva (to prevent air and/or debris from being sucked into reproductive tract of the mare)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4272","question":"Name the operation performed on mares where the upper part of the vulva is stitched to reduce infection?","answer":"Caslick's"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4273","question":"How long is the estrous cycle of the mare?","answer":"21 - 23 days (accept any number within this range) (FYI: EstrOUS is the whole 21 - 23 day cycle; estrUS is the 6 day heat period.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4274","question":"What is the difference between estrus and diestrus?","answer":"Estrus or heat is the period when a mare is receptive to a stallion and encourages mating; diestrus is the period in which the mare is NOT receptive to the stallion."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4275","question":"What are the TWO distinct phases of the mare's estrous cycle?","answer":"Estrus and diestrus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4276","question":"In comparison to the horse, how is the length of the estrous cycle of donkeys and ponies different?","answer":"Estrous cycles are longer in donkeys and ponies (25 days instead of 19 - 22 days)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4277","question":"What term describes when a mare undergoes multiple estrous cycles only during a specific part of the year?","answer":"Seasonally polyestrous"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4278","question":"What is meant by the term “seasonally polyestrous”?","answer":"Mare undergoes multiple estrous cycles only during certain times of the year"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4279","question":"When using the system for scoring of behavioral estrus in mares, what behavior is seen in a mare scoring 1 (one)?","answer":"Mare isn't aggressive towards the stallion; mare looks away; mare isn't interested (accept any)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4280","question":"During what season would a mare be naturally in anestrus?","answer":"Winter"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4281","question":"What word means without estrus?","answer":"Anestrus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4282","question":"What is the name of the long period between breeding seasons when the ovaries are inactive?","answer":"Anestrus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4283","question":"At what part of a mare's estrous cycle is she NOT responsive to the stallion?","answer":"Diestrus (also accept anestrus)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4284","question":"Name 3 behaviors of a mare in diestrus towards a stallion.","answer":"Biting, kicking, striking, squealing, tail switching, not interested (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4285","question":"During which stage of a mare's reproductive cycle will she exhibit eversion of the vulva?","answer":"Estrus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4286","question":"What is the average length of estrus or heat period?","answer":"6 (six) days"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4287","question":"What is another name for the heat period when mares are receptive to stallions?","answer":"Estrus (also accept \"in season\" or \"in heat\")"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4288","question":"What is foal heat?","answer":"Mare's first heat after foaling"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4289","question":"Frequent urination and eversion of the vulva or winking will occur during what phase of the mare's reproductive cycle?","answer":"Estrus or heat (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4290","question":"During what stage of the mare's estrous cycle is she receptive to the stallion?","answer":"Estrus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4291","question":"When during the estrous cycle is conception rate the highest in mares?","answer":"At the end of estrus, 1 - 2 days prior to ovulation, or during foal heat (accept any)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4292","question":"When during the estrous cycle does ovulation usually occur?","answer":"At the end of estrus (24 - 28 hours before end of estrus) (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4293","question":"What is the term for the rhythmic opening and closing of the labia as exhibited in mares during estrus?","answer":"Winking"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4294","question":"What is it called when a mare ovulates, but fails to show behavioral signs of estrus?","answer":"Silent heat"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4295","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is \"silent heat\"?","answer":"Ovulation without outward signs of estrus"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4296","question":"What event triggers the end of estrus or heat?","answer":"Ovulation (FYI: Ovulation usually occurs 24 - 48 hours before the end of estrus.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4297","question":"When scoring behavioral estrus in mares, give 3 examples of behavior that would indicate a score of 4.","answer":"Mare shows intense interest in stallion, turns hindquarters towards him, leans towards him, squats, lifts tail, calls, urinates, winks vulva"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4298","question":"Name 3 signs of estrus in the mare.","answer":"Frequent urination; flexed pelvis or squatting; winking; elevated tail; acceptance of stallion"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4299","question":"Ovulation will usually occur within how many days after the discontinuation of treatment with Regumate?","answer":"12 days"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4300","question":"Prostaglandin, human chorionic gonadotropin, and progesterone (Regumate) are 3 hormones that can be used to do what?","answer":"Manipulate estrus in mares"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4301","question":"Use of an artificial lighting program to induce early estrous cycling and ovulation should include 16 hours of light each day and begin how long before the desired breeding season?","answer":"2 - 3 months (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4302","question":"Other than hormones, what can be used to bring mares into heat earlier than the normal breeding season?","answer":"Artificial lights (FYI:  Mares need 16 hours of light to 8 hours of darkness for 2 - 3 months to induce heat.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4303","question":"What ratio of daylight to darkness seems to bring mares into heat?","answer":"16 hours of daylight to 8 hours of darkness"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4304","question":"What is the most important environmental cue in inducing estrus in mares?","answer":"Light (more daylight hours)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4305","question":"What type of lights makes photo-stimulation of estrous cycles effective?","answer":"Regular bulbs on a timer or fluorescent bulbs (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4306","question":"What is short-cycling a mare?","answer":"Giving hormones to return mare to heat before their next natural cycle"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4307","question":"What TWO hormones increase just before ovulation in the mare?","answer":"Estrogen and Luteinizing Hormone"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4308","question":"What are the TWO ovarian hormones that control the mare's estrous cycle?","answer":"Estrogen and progesterone"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4309","question":"Hormones that stimulate the development and maintenance of feminine sexual characteristics are called what?","answer":"Estrogens (estrogenic hormones) "},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4310","question":"What hormone causes the cervix of the mare to become relaxed during estrus?","answer":"Estrogen"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4311","question":"What hormone does the maturing follicle on the ovary release to stimulate the sexual behavior of mares during heat?","answer":"Estrogen"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4312","question":"What are the 3 principal estrogenic hormones?","answer":"Estradiol, estrone, and estriol"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4313","question":"What does FSH cause in the mare?","answer":"Follicle growth"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4314","question":"What hormone causes follicle growth?","answer":"Follicle Stimulating Hormone (FSH)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4315","question":"In response to GnRH release from the hypothalamus, what structure releases FSH and LH?","answer":"Pituitary gland (FYI:  GnRH is gonadotropin releasing hormone.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4316","question":"Name ONE thing that luteinizing hormone does in the horse.","answer":"Causes ovulation; initiates the formation of the corpus luteum"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4317","question":"Give TWO reasons for injecting a mare with oxytocin.","answer":"Help with delivery of foal; stimulate milk let down"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4318","question":"What hormone is responsible for both milk let-down and contractions during parturition?","answer":"Oxytocin"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4319","question":"What does PMSG stand for?","answer":"Pregnant mare serum gonadotropin"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4320","question":"What is PMU?","answer":"Pregnant Mare Urine (FYI:  PMU is used as a source of human hormone replacement therapy.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4321","question":"Regumate is the synthetic form of which hormone?","answer":"Progesterone"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4322","question":"Which hormone do the luteal cells within the corpus luteum secrete?","answer":"Progesterone"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4323","question":"Once the follicle has ruptured and released the ova, the luteal phase begins.  The corpus luteum begins to form and is responsible for the release of what hormone?","answer":"Progesterone"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4324","question":"Name ONE thing the hormone progesterone does in the horse's body.","answer":"Encourages glandular development; encourages greater muscle tone in myometrium; keeps mare out of estrus; helps maintain pregnancy in early stages"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4325","question":"What does the hormone prolactin do?","answer":"Initiates lactation"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4326","question":"What hormone released by the uterus if the mare isn't pregnant is responsible for the regression of the corpus luteum and the return of the mare cycling?","answer":"Prostaglandin"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4327","question":"What is the term for the change that occurs in an animal that results in the animal being able to produce sex cells?","answer":"Puberty"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4328","question":"At what age are most mares capable of reproduction?","answer":"3 (three) years of age "},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4329","question":"What is the average age of puberty in the mare?","answer":"12 - 15 months (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4330","question":"Name 4 parts of the stallion's reproductive system.","answer":"Scrotum, testes (testicles), epididymis, vas deferens, seminal vesicles or vesicular glands, prostate, bulbourethral or Cowper's glands, urethra, penis"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4331","question":"The vesicular gland is responsible for adding what to the semen?","answer":"Gel fraction"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4332","question":"What are the glands called that are located along the urethra of the male horse and that produce fluids that nourish and preserve the sperm?","answer":"Accessory glands"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4333","question":"What are the 3 accessory glands located along the urethra in the stallion?","answer":"Prostate; seminal vesicles or vesicular glands; Cowper's glands or bulbourethral glands"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4334","question":"Name ONE function of the epididymis.","answer":"Store sperm; area where sperm undergo modification and maturation"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4335","question":"In what part of the stallion's reproductive tract do sperm undergo modifications or maturation?","answer":"Epididymis"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4336","question":"Mares are often placed under lights to bring them into heat earlier.  Why would stallions be placed under lights?","answer":"Increase testicular activity (FYI:  Use of artificial lights may increase libido and sperm counts during the winter months.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4337","question":"Why are the testicles suspended outside the body cavity?","answer":"Cooler temperatures are needed for normal development of sperm."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4338","question":"What is the function of the cremaster muscle?","answer":"Raises and lowers the scrotum (to assist in temperature regulation)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4339","question":"What is the name for the muscle that raises and lowers the scrotum?","answer":"Cremaster"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4340","question":"Which structure of the horse is responsible for maintaining proper temperature for sperm production?","answer":"Scrotum"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4341","question":"What is the sack-like pouch that suspends the testicles outside the male animal?","answer":"Scrotum"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4342","question":"How does the scrotum regulate testicular temperature?","answer":"By raising or lowering the testicles close to or away from the body"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4343","question":"As compared to body temperature, should the temperature of the scrotum and testicles be higher, lower, or the same?","answer":"Lower "},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4344","question":"Give ONE function of the scrotum.","answer":"Encloses testes; controls the temperature of the testes"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4345","question":"What are the components of semen?","answer":"Sperm mixed with fluids from the accessory glands"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4346","question":"Which TWO criteria used to evaluate semen are NOT affected by the length of day or season of year?","answer":"Morphology and motility"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4347","question":"How is semen usually collected from stallions to use in artificial insemination?","answer":"By using artificial vaginas, jump mares, or breeding phantoms (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4348","question":"How long can sperm cells survive in the female reproductive tract?","answer":"48 - 72 hours"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4349","question":"What is the general term for the substance emitted by a stallion during the breeding of a mare?","answer":"Semen or seminal fluid (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4350","question":"Name the 3 parts of the sperm cell.","answer":"Head, midpiece, and tail"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4351","question":"What are 3 reasons for doing a semen evaluation?","answer":"Monitor stallion’s semen quality; estimate the number of mares that could be bred; maximizing use of single time breeding; shipping cooled semen; freezing semen for later use; quality control"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4352","question":"Name 3 of the criteria used to evaluate stallion semen.","answer":"Concentration, motility, volume, morphology"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4353","question":"What do the sebaceous glands in the prepuce of a stallion produce?","answer":"Smegma"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4354","question":"2 part question:  What is smegma and where is it found?","answer":"Waxy substance that builds up in a horse's sheath"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4355","question":"What is the term for the black, waxy substance that can build up in a horse's sheath?","answer":"Smegma"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4356","question":"2 part question:  What is a bilateral cryptorchid stallion and explaining your answer, can he be used for breeding?","answer":"Stallion that's retained both testicles in its body cavity; no, he can’t be used for breeding because he's infertile."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4357","question":"Where in the testes does spermatogenesis occur?","answer":"Seminiferous tubules"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4358","question":"What is spermatogenesis?","answer":"Process of producing sperm cells"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4359","question":"The process of the production of sperm cells is called what?","answer":"Spermatogenesis"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4360","question":"Where in the stallion is sperm produced?","answer":"Testes (specifically in the seminiferous tubules)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4361","question":"What is the primary sex organ of the stallion?","answer":"Testis (also accept testicle) (FYI: Testis is singular; testes is plural.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4362","question":"What is the tube through which both semen and urine pass?","answer":"Urethra"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4363","question":"What is the vas deferens?","answer":"Tube that carries sperm from the epididymis to the urethra"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4364","question":"What tube carries sperm from the epididymis to the urethra?","answer":"Vas deferens"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4365","question":"At what age can you start using a stallion for breeding purposes?","answer":"2 (two) years of age (only for limited breeding)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4366","question":"At what age does puberty occur in stallions?","answer":"1 (one) year of age"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4367","question":"What is the primary purpose of FSH in the stallion?","answer":"Stimulates spermatogenesis (production of sperm)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4368","question":"The Sertoli cells located in the seminiferous tubules of the stallion's testes stimulate spermatogenesis in the stallion.  What hormone from the pituitary gland controls the Sertoli cells?","answer":"FSH (follicle stimulating hormone)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4369","question":"Which hormone stimulates spermatogenesis or the production of sperm in the stallion?","answer":"FSH (Follicle Stimulating Hormone)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4370","question":"Leydig cells in the stallion are responsible for the production of what TWO hormones? (LIE-dig)","answer":"Testosterone and estrogen"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4371","question":"What is the primary hormone that's produced and secreted by the Leydig cells in the testes? (LIE-dig)","answer":"Testosterone"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4372","question":"What hormone regulates testosterone in the stallion?","answer":"LH (Luteinizing Hormone)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4373","question":"Name ONE major cause of infertility in mares.","answer":"Health problems; infections; hormone imbalances; anatomical problems; endometriosis; nutritional factors; human management (breeding for certain traits, breeding outside natural season); age; psychological problems"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4374","question":"Name 3 general causes of infertility in mares.","answer":"Health problems; infections; hormone imbalances; anatomical problems; endometriosis; nutritional factors; human management (breeding for certain traits, breeding outside natural season); age; psychological problems"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4375","question":"Give 3 causes of infertility in the stallion.","answer":"Health problems; pain; injury; infection; hormone imbalance; anatomical problem; nutritional factors; human management (rough handling, overuse as a teaser, overbreeding); psychological problems (anxiety, scared by aggressive mares); masturbation"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4376","question":"What is the slang term for a horse breeding establishment?","answer":"Stud or stud farm (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4377","question":"What is the term for the stallion that is used to determine if a mare is receptive to breeding?","answer":"Teaser"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4378","question":"What is a common method used to determine if a mare is in heat?","answer":"Teasing"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4379","question":"Of all our domestic animals, which animal has the lowest reproductive efficiency?","answer":"Horse"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4380","question":"What do you call the charge for breeding services rendered by a stallion?","answer":"Stud fee"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4381","question":"You recently purchased a new stallion for your breeding program.  The previous owner stated that the stallion had a respiratory illness accompanied by a high fever 30 days ago.  What impact would this have on the stallion’s fertility?","answer":"You'd expect a lower sperm count for 65 days after the illness.  (FYI:  Spermatogenesis takes 49 days; then the sperm undergo modification and maturation in the epididymis for about 16 days.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4382","question":"How is it determined that a stallion has ejaculated while breeding a mare?","answer":"Tail flagging"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4383","question":"Reproductive ability in the mare decreases after what age?","answer":"15 years of age (accept any number within the 15 - 18 age range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4384","question":"What is the name for the specialized building where mares are bred?","answer":"Breeding shed"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4385","question":"Give TWO reasons why horses highly managed by humans have lower reproductive efficiency than horses in the wild.","answer":"Humans try to breed mares outside their natural reproductive season (to have foals born close to January 1st); humans breed horses for certain qualities such as performance, pedigree, beauty, etc. instead of reproductive efficiency"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4386","question":"Name ONE of the main concerns when handling breeding stallions.","answer":"Safety; prevention of injury to stallion, mares or handlers; prevention of infections"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4387","question":"What is a breeding shed?","answer":"Specialized building where mares are bred"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4388","question":"What are TWO meanings of the term “stud”?","answer":"Stallion; an establishment at which horses are kept for breeding purposes"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4389","question":"You’ve just opened a Quarter Horse breeding operation.  You think you've found the ideal stallion for your program.  His conformation is nearly flawless.  Give 3 other things you should consider when buying a stallion that will be used for breeding.","answer":"Temperament; overall health; reproductive health; no infections; no parasites; soundness; no genetic diseases; semen; libido; prepotency; record of settling mares (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4390","question":"Give 3 negative aspects of breeding your horse.","answer":"Mare:  breeding fees, breeding complications, out of use, pregnancy complications, birth complications, expenses; Foal:  might be a “dud”, years before you can ride foal, medical expenses, illnesses, problems selling"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4391","question":"Give 3 positive aspects of breeding your horse.","answer":"Good learning experience; can train foal; can plan mating to produce type of offspring you want; possible income from sale of foal or pregnant mare"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4392","question":"Name 3 methods used to breed mares.","answer":"Live breeding (pasture breeding and hand breeding); artificial insemination; embryo transfer"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4393","question":"What has been one of the most important advances in commercial horse breeding?","answer":"Artificial insemination"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4394","question":"AI is accepted in most breed associations.  Name ONE breed that requires live cover breeding.","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4395","question":"In reference to reproduction, what do the initials AI stand for?","answer":"Artificial insemination"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4396","question":"Name 3 DISADVANTAGES of artificial insemination.","answer":"Initial costs to stallion owner; need skilled staff; costs of semen shipping; evaluation of mare for AI; communication between owners of mare and stallion; semen must be ordered in advance (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4397","question":"What do you call a mare that was bred, but didn't produce a foal?","answer":"Barren"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4398","question":"What is a \"barren mare\"?","answer":"Mare that was bred, but is not in foal"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4399","question":"What is a \"maiden mare\"?","answer":"Mare that's never been bred"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4400","question":"What do you call a mare that's never been bred?","answer":"Maiden mare"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4401","question":"What is an \"open mare\"?","answer":"Mare that's currently not pregnant (not bred this season, but has been bred in the past)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4402","question":"What does the term \"in foal\" mean?","answer":"Mare is pregnant."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4403","question":"What is the difference between a barren mare and an open mare?","answer":"Barren mare was bred, but is not pregnant; open mare has had foals in the past, but was not bred this season."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4404","question":"Give 5 reproductive classifications of mares.","answer":"Maiden; barren; open or yeld; pregnant or in foal; lactating, wet, or nursing"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"int bonus","number":"4405","question":"2 part question:  Reproductively, name TWO ways mares can be classified and explain each classification.","answer":"Maiden—never been bred; barren—been bred, but isn't in foal; open or yeld—had foals in the past, but isn't in foal this year; in foal—pregnant; lactating or wet—nursing a foal"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"jr bonus","number":"4406","question":"Give 3 of the 5 reproductive classifications of mares.","answer":"Maiden, barren, open, pregnant, lactating"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4407","question":"What does \"return privilege in season\" mean?","answer":"You may bring your mare back until she's in foal for that breeding season only; a second fee will be charged after the current season if the mare is returned."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4408","question":"What breeding policy involves payment in advance of the entire price for the season with the payment non-refundable?","answer":"No guarantee"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4409","question":"When the breeder guarantees a \"live foal\", what TWO things must the foal do to fulfill the guarantee?","answer":"Stand and suck (nurse)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4410","question":"What breeding policy involves payment of the stud fee when the mare is pronounced in foal at a 42 day exam?","answer":"Guaranteed in foal"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4411","question":"What is embryo transfer?","answer":"Transfer of a fertilized egg from a donor mare to a recipient mare who carries it to term"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4412","question":"This type of breeding is not accepted by all breed associations.   It is the process of recovering a fertilized egg from the uterus of one mare and transferring it to the uterus of another for gestation. What is this type of breeding?","answer":"Embryo transfer"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4413","question":"The most common cause of a spontaneous abortion is a placental or uterine infection.  Prior to the current widespread use of ultrasound, what accounted for about 25% of abortions and was considered to be the second most common cause?","answer":"Twinning (twins)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4414","question":"What is the term for the expulsion of the fetus before the time of normal foaling?","answer":"Abortion (also accept premature birth)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4415","question":"Name 3 causes of equine abortion.","answer":"Infections; improper fetal implantation; twins; fetal abnormalities; placental abnormalities; umbilical cord problems; uterine abnormalities (endometrial fibrosis); trauma; drugs; plants (tall fescue); hormone imbalance; nutritional deficiencies"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4416","question":"If a mare must be moved to another facility before foaling, why should you do it no later than 3 - 4 weeks prior to the expected foaling date?","answer":"To allow her to acclimate to the new surroundings or to reduce stress (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4417","question":"Why should you deworm your pregnant mare 30 days before her foaling date?","answer":"To decrease passage of parasites to the foal"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4418","question":"Name 3 vaccinations that are often given to a broodmare 4 - 6 weeks before foaling.","answer":"Tetanus, Rhinopneumonitis (EHV), Influeneza, WEE, EEE, VEE, West Nile, Rabies, Botulism, Strangles, Potomac Horse Fever, Rotavirus, Equine Viral Arteritis"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4419","question":"2 part question:  What substances in the urine and in the blood are used to test for pregnancy in horses?","answer":"Urine—estrogen; blood—PMSG (pregnant mare serum gonadotropin)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4420","question":"What technique of pregnancy diagnosis is the easiest and the most accurate.  It can detect pregnancy as early as two weeks after conception?","answer":"Ultrasound"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4421","question":"Name ONE method of diagnosing pregnancy in mares.","answer":"Ultrasound; rectal palpation; blood test for PMSG (pregnant mare serum gonadotropin); urine test for estrogen; failure to come into heat"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4422","question":"Name 3 methods of diagnosing pregnancy in mares.","answer":"Ultrasound; rectal palpation; blood test for PMSG (pregnant mare serum gonadotropin); urine test for estrogen; failure to come into heat"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4423","question":"Mares of what draft breed have a gestation length 15 - 20 days longer than other draft mares?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4424","question":"You do the math…A mare that was bred on May 20th should foal in what month the next year?","answer":"April"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4425","question":"The length of time (usually 11 months) for the development of the foal from the time of breeding until birth is called what?","answer":"Pregnancy or gestation period"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4426","question":"In MONTHS, what is the gestation period of the Rangerbred?","answer":"11 months"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4427","question":"How long is the gestation period or pregnancy for horses?","answer":"11 months or 335 - 342 days (accept any number within 320 – 400 day range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4428","question":"The gestation period of a mare carrying a horse foal is approximately how many days shorter than it would be if she were carrying a mule foal?","answer":"10 days shorter"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4429","question":"On average, how many days longer are colts carried than fillies?","answer":"2 - 7 days (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4430","question":"Give 3 factors that affect the length of gestation.","answer":"Time of year (foals due in late winter or early spring may be foaled 5 – 10 days later); fetal sex; maternal nutrition; environmental stress; ingestion of toxins (fescue); breed (Belgians) (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4431","question":"What are the 3 membranes of the placenta?","answer":"Amnion, allantois, and chorion"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4432","question":"The amnion, allantois, and chorion comprise what structure?","answer":"Placenta"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4433","question":"What is the placenta or afterbirth?","answer":"Membranous organ that attaches the fetus to the uterus (and transports nutrients and wastes between the fetus and the uterus via the umbilical cord)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4434","question":"What is the name of the hard disc-like structure found in the placental fluids after birth?","answer":"Hippomane"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4435","question":"What is the name of the innermost membrane of the fetal placenta that forms the water bag for the developing fetus?","answer":"Amnion"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4436","question":"What is the first thing to do with the placenta after it has been passed by the mare?","answer":"Examine it to make sure it's all there."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4437","question":"How do nutrients get from the mare to the fetus after it's attached to the uterus?","answer":"Through the placenta (via the umbilical cord)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4438","question":"What is the correct name for the membranous organ referred to as the afterbirth?","answer":"Placenta"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4439","question":"What term describes plant toxins that cross the placental barrier during pregnancy and cause defects in the foal?","answer":"Teratogenic toxins"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4440","question":"In what SPECIFIC area of the uterus does the fertilized egg attach and the fetus develop in a normal horse pregnancy?","answer":"Uterine horn"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4441","question":"What is an unborn animal that is developing in the uterus called?","answer":"Fetus (called an embryo in the early stages)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4442","question":"What is a zygote?","answer":"Fertilized egg"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4443","question":"What is the process of the uniting of the sperm and egg?","answer":"Fertilization (FYI: Fertilization occurs in the oviducts.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4444","question":"When does the most rapid period of fetal growth take place?","answer":"During the last 3 - 4 months of pregnancy (last trimester)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4445","question":"How many days does it take for the fertilized egg to migrate to the uterus?","answer":"4 - 6 days (accept any number within this range) "},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4446","question":"Where does fertilization occur?","answer":"Oviducts (Fallopian tubes)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4447","question":"Name 3 signs that indicate a mare is starting the first stage of labor.","answer":"Seeks isolation from other horses; stops eating; becomes restless; swishes tail; sweats; urinates frequently; wax on the end of the teats may fall off; milk starts to drip from teats"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4448","question":"What general type of equine has the LOWEST incidence of twin pregnancies?","answer":"Ponies"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4449","question":"Which breed has the highest incidence of twinning?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4450","question":"How are identical twins produced?","answer":"Single fertilized egg (zygote) divides and produces offspring with identical genetic makeup."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4451","question":"Within a few days of birth, what begins to form on the mare's teats?","answer":"Wax "},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4452","question":"How long before birth will pregnant mare's teats begin to wax?","answer":"1 - 6 days (accept any number within range) "},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4453","question":"In reference to reproduction, what is dystocia?","answer":"Difficulty giving birth (foaling problems)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4454","question":"When a foal is in the transverse ventral presentation for delivery, what part of the foal’s body is lodged against the pelvis of the mare preventing delivery?","answer":"Foal’s back"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4455","question":"During the second stage of labor, you notice the appearance of a red, velvety bulb at the vulva which looks like a basketball. This is commonly referred to as a “red bag”. What does this indicate?","answer":"Premature placental separation (This is an emergency requiring immediate rupture of this membrane to expedite delivery of the foal.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4456","question":"A “red bag delivery” is most commonly observed in mares that have grazed on what type of pasture?","answer":"Tall fescue (fescue)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4457","question":"Give ONE cause of dystocia or difficulty foaling.","answer":"Abnormal presentation; foal too large for mare’s pelvis; twins; “red bag” (premature separation of the placenta) (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4458","question":"What is the term for the type of delivery in which the foal's rump or hind feet present first in the birth canal?","answer":"Breech"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4459","question":"What can be done to delay foaling until the veterinarian arrives if there is an indication of abnormal presentation of the foal?","answer":"Walk the mare or keep her standing (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4460","question":"A broodmare whose foal is in a “flexed carpi” position would need what problem corrected to enable normal vaginal delivery?","answer":"The foal's knees are bent so the foal’s front legs would need to be straightened into a normal presentation for delivery."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4461","question":"In a normal birth, which legs appear first?","answer":"Front legs"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4462","question":"During what time of day are most foals born?","answer":"Night"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4463","question":"How soon after birth should a mare pass her placenta?","answer":"3 (three) hours"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4464","question":"What is parturition?","answer":"Birth"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4465","question":"In the pregnant mare, the first stages of foaling can often mimic what condition?","answer":"Colic"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4466","question":"What is the LAST event to occur in the mare's labor?","answer":"Expulsion of the placenta (afterbirth) (FYI:  The placenta should be passed within 3 hours of birth.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4467","question":"What is the correct medical terminology for giving birth?","answer":"Parturition"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4468","question":"Lactation means the production of what?","answer":"Milk"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4469","question":"What is lactating?","answer":"Producing milk"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4470","question":"What does agalactic mean?","answer":"Without milk"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4471","question":"Lactation increases the energy requirements of a mare above maintenance by what percentage?","answer":"50 - 70% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4472","question":"On average, how much milk in pounds is a light horse mare capable of producing per day?","answer":"23 - 29 pounds of milk per day or 2 – 3% of her body weight per day (accept any number within these ranges)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4473","question":"Abnormal maternal aggression towards the foal is commonly caused by what?","answer":"Painful udder"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4474","question":"What is a \"nurse mare\"?","answer":"Mare that will take care of a strange foal (and let it nurse)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4475","question":"What is the term used for a lactating mare that takes care of an orphaned foal as her own?","answer":"Nurse mare"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4476","question":"In mare's milk, which is higher, milk fat or lactose?","answer":"Lactose"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4477","question":"What breed type of horse is often used as nurse mares because they produce more milk?","answer":"Draft or draft-cross mares (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4478","question":"What percent of mare's milk is water?","answer":"90%"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4479","question":"Lactating mares have an increased need for water due to what?","answer":"Milk production or lactation"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4480","question":"What is colostrum?","answer":"First milk a mare produces after the birth of a foal"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4481","question":"What is the nutritious, first milk for the foal called?","answer":"Colostrum"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4482","question":"What are the proteins in colostrum that provide the foal with temporary immunity against infectious diseases?","answer":"Immunoglobulins (antibodies)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4483","question":"How long before foaling does colostrum develop?","answer":"2 - 3 weeks (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4484","question":"How long does the mare produce colostrum?","answer":"Up to 48 hours after birth of the foal (FYI: Foal absorbs antibodies from colostrum for 36 hours.)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4485","question":"Colostrum is especially important to the foal because it contains what TWO things?","answer":"Antibodies (proteins) that protect the foal from infection and laxatives (fats) that help the foal pass meconium."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4486","question":"What is the percentage of live foal birth births in feral horse populations?","answer":"80 - 90% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4487","question":"What is the national average for live foal births in human-controlled breeding operations?","answer":"50 - 60% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4488","question":"About how long does it take for a foal's immune system to become functional and produce significant levels of antibodies?","answer":"2 - 4 months (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4489","question":"For how long will the foal’s digestive tract absorb the antibodies in colostrum?","answer":"36 hours"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4490","question":"A nursing foal's nutrient requirements exceed those provided by the dam's milk within how many months?","answer":"2 (two) months"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4491","question":"Why is creep feeding of foals recommended when foals are 30 - 60 days old?","answer":"Mare's milk production declines."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4492","question":"Foals should nurse for the first time within how many hours of birth?","answer":"2 - 3 hours (accept any number within this range) [FYI:  The average time from birth to first time of nursing is 11 minutes.]"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4493","question":"A foal is normally weaned at what age?","answer":"4 - 6 months (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4494","question":"Give ONE reason why you'd keep a foal in familiar surroundings during the weaning process.","answer":"Decrease stress; decrease exposure to diseases"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4495","question":"When weaning a foal, why is it recommended to reduce the mare's food?","answer":"To help the drying up process (to decrease mare's milk production)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4496","question":"Give 3 physical signs of immaturity in a newborn foal.","answer":"Underweight; silky hair; floppy ears; weakness; poor suckle reflex; illness or septicemia"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4497","question":"What is the name of the first feces that the foal excretes?","answer":"Meconium (FYI:  The next feces is called \"milk feces\".)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4498","question":"What is meconium?","answer":"First manure passed by the foal (dark tarry stool formed prior to birth that normally begins to pass 30 minutes to 6 hours after birth)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4499","question":"Name 3 symptoms of meconium impactions in newborn foals.","answer":"Depression; not interested in nursing; flagging tai; increased heart rate (tachycardia); increased respiration rate (tachypnea); abdominal distension"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4500","question":"What is the VERY FIRST step in taking care of a foal immediately after birth?","answer":"Remove anything from the foal's nostrils that might restrict its breathing."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4501","question":"Pandiculation is an indication of the well-being of a foal.  It usually occurs within 4 hours after birth. What is pandiculation?","answer":"Stretching"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4502","question":"Why should you treat the naval stump of a newborn foal with iodine or antiseptic?","answer":"To prevent bacteria from entering the body through it"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4503","question":"What care should be given to the navel stump of a newborn foal?","answer":"Apply a mild iodine solution or an antiseptic (to prevent bacteria from entering the body)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4504","question":"Why should the foal's umbilical cord NOT be broken too soon after birth?","answer":"Foal would be deprived of about 30% of the blood that flows from the mare to the foal immediately after birth."},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4505","question":"In the newborn foal the navel stump is a site that allows easy access for the invasion of what microorganism into the body?","answer":"Bacteria"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4506","question":"The umbilical cord connects which TWO structures?","answer":"Fetus and placenta"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4507","question":"What does the urachus do?","answer":"Takes urine away from the foal during pregnancy"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4508","question":"Name ONE cause of colic in newborn foals.","answer":"Meconium impaction; gastric ulcer; enteritis; inguinal hernia; overo lethal white foal syndrome"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"hard","number":"4509","question":"What is the slang term for a foal that’s born with septicemia and is semi-comatose?","answer":"Sleeper or sleeper foal (accept either)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"sr bonus","number":"4510","question":"Premature separation of the placenta during parturition resulting in hypoxia is a known cause for neonatal maladjustment syndrome.  Give 3 terms used to describe these foals as they progress through the stages of this disorder.","answer":"Wanderer, dummy, convulsive or barker foal"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"easy","number":"4511","question":"How does a healthy foal normally sleep?","answer":"On its side"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"intermediate","number":"4512","question":"How much weight will a foal typically gain per day during the first 3 months of life?","answer":"2.25 - 3 pounds per day (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4513","question":"You do the math…A newborn foal normally weighs 9 - 10% of the mare’s body weight.  What would be the approximate weight of a foal if the mare weighs 1200 pounds?","answer":"108 to 120 pounds (accept a number within this range)"},
{"category":"Reproduction","level":"medium","number":"4514","question":"A normal foal weighs what percent of the mare's body weight at birth?","answer":"8 - 10% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4515","question":"When catching a horse, what area of the horse should you walk towards?","answer":"Neck or shoulders (accept either) (FYI:  Avoid the biting and kicking ends!!  Horses' prey response tells them to run or kick at things approaching them from the rear.)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4516","question":"Why should you speak to your horse when approaching it from the rear?","answer":"To let him know you're there. (Horses can't see directly behind; if you startle him, he may kick.)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4517","question":"Why is electrical wiring in a barn always run in conduits?","answer":"To protect the horse from getting shocked (FYI: Conduits are coverings for electrical wires and are often made out of metal.)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4518","question":"When considering barn safety, human carelessness and lack of safety knowledge are considered the single most significant factors in what tragic event involving equine facilities?","answer":"Barn fires"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"intermediate","number":"4519","question":"For fire safety, a building for hay storage should be located at least how many feet from any other structure?","answer":"At least 100 feet"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"int bonus","number":"4520","question":"Name 3 things that cause WINTER barn fires.","answer":"Appliances such portable heaters, animals chewing through wires, dust or cobwebs on electrical surfaces, smoking (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4521","question":"Give 3 possible causes of a stable fire.","answer":"Smoking, lightning, spontaneous combustion, problems with electrical wiring, heaters, flammable substances, machinery (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4522","question":"What are the TWO most common causes of summer barn fires?","answer":"Lightning and spontaneous combustion"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4523","question":"Give 3 general fire safety rules for barns.","answer":"NO smoking, flammable substances, vehicles or machinery, portable heaters; HAVE fire extinguishers, automatic sprinklers, smoke alarms,  inside water supply and hose, exterior stall doors, space between buildings (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"intermediate","number":"4524","question":"Name ONE area where fire extinguishers should be hung in a barn.","answer":"All exterior doorways; in the middle of long aisles; next to the electrical panel box; at least 75 feet apart"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"medium","number":"4525","question":"What is a critical, but often overlooked, item of a barn escape plan?","answer":"Providing for a holding area at a distance from the barn that's big enough to hold all the horses"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4526","question":"Why should smoking NEVER be allowed in a barn?","answer":"It could cause a fire."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4527","question":"Why should you keep a halter and lead rope by each stall?","answer":"In case of emergency (so you can lead horses out quickly)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4528","question":"In case of an emergency, what TWO pieces of equipment should be outside every horse's stall?","answer":"Halter and lead rope"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4529","question":"An ignition source is something that can cause an accelerant or flammable material to ignite or smoke.  Name 3 common ignition sources.","answer":"Cigarettes; matches; sparks; motors; heaters; electrical appliances; fence chargers; electrical fixtures; wires; batteries; broken glass; chemicals"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4530","question":"An accelerant is a substance that increases the speed at which a fire spreads.  Name 3 common accelerants.","answer":"Gasoline, kerosene, oil, aerosol cans, paint thinner, charcoal lighter fluid (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4531","question":"Name 3 highly flammable materials found in barns.","answer":"Hay; straw; bedding (such as sawdust and shredded newspaper); cobwebs; dust; grain dust; horse blankets; paint; fertilizer; pesticides; herbicides (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4532","question":"Give TWO fire safety rules for barns.","answer":"NO smoking, flammable substances, vehicles or machinery, portable heaters; HAVE fire extinguishers, automatic sprinklers, smoke alarms,  inside water supply and hose, exterior stall doors, space between buildings (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4533","question":"Horses kept in tie stalls must be taught to do what before you walk in beside them?","answer":"Move over (so you're not crowded against the wall)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4534","question":"What part of the horse's body should you NEVER strike or kick?","answer":"Head or legs (FYI: because those areas injure more easily than the rest of the body)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4535","question":"If you have to work around a horse's hindquarters, why is it important to stay close?","answer":"If the horse kicks, you won't receive the full impact."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4536","question":"What is the safest way to comb a horse's tail?","answer":"Stand off to the side and bring the tail around to you."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4537","question":"When working on a horse, what position is considered the safest for you to be in?","answer":"As near the shoulder as possible (so you can stay away from the mouth and the hind legs)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4538","question":"In showing your horse at halter, how much space should be left between your horse and another horse?","answer":"1 horse length or 8 feet (accept either)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4539","question":"A horse length equals how many feet?","answer":"8 (eight) feet"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4540","question":"When riding in groups, what kind of distance should you keep between horses?","answer":"1 horse length or 8 feet (accept either) (FYI:  On trail rides, the distance between horses should increase as the pace increases.)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4541","question":"What is the safest position from which to lead a horse?","answer":"Between his head and shoulder (on his left side)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4542","question":"What is the safest way to turn your horse loose in a pasture or stall?","answer":"Lead him completely through the gate or door, turn him to face the direction from which you just came, remove the halter or bridle, don't let him bolt away because it’s a bad habit and you might get kicked (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4543","question":"What should you NEVER do with a lead rope or reins?","answer":"Never wrap them around your hand, wrist, or body"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4544","question":"What should you do if your horse rears up while you are leading it?","answer":"Release the hand nearest the halter so you can stay on the ground."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4545","question":"What is the safest way to lead a horse through a narrow opening or gate?","answer":"Step through first and move to one side to avoid being crowded."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4546","question":"Describe how the halter lead rope should be held.","answer":"Right hand holds the lead near the halter; left hand holds the excess lead either folded in a figure 8 or coiled loosely."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4547","question":"What direction should you turn the horse when leading it?","answer":"Away from you or to the right (so you don't get stepped on)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4548","question":"If your horse resists while you are trying to lead it, what should you NOT do?","answer":"Don't get in front and try to pull him"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4549","question":"Disregarding simple safety rules in handling horses can result in what?","answer":"Serious injury"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4550","question":"When using a hay net for feeding horses, why should it be tied at the eye level of the horse?","answer":"Safety (so the horse can't get its foot caught)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4551","question":"What should you do as a safety precaution if your horse is known to kick?","answer":"Put a red ribbon in its tail."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4552","question":"Why is it important to learn and practice safety rules?","answer":"So they'll become habits (and will keep you safe)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4553","question":"Name 3 safety features you should incorporate when building a barn.","answer":"Adequate ventilation; proper temperature; adequate lighting; safe, convenient electrical outlets; safe, convenient waterers; windows; alley width; stall door width; stall size, safe stall doors (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4554","question":"For safety, what MUST a rider wear while jumping?","answer":"Helmet"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4555","question":"When riding a young or green horse, what's the SAFEST way to cross a paved road?","answer":"Dismount and lead him across"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"int bonus","number":"4556","question":"Name 3 safety precautions for riding in a group.","answer":"Don't run past other horses, keep horses spaced, red ribbon in tail, cross roads together, ride on same side of road, most experienced in lead, least experienced in middle, don’t leave riders behind, warn other riders of obstacles, take cell phone"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4557","question":"If a rider should fall from the horse when jumping, what should be done?","answer":"DON'T move him; CALL 911 if he's injured"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4558","question":"Why shouldn't you run past other horses and riders?","answer":"It will make the other horses want to run and someone could get hurt (also accept startles the horses)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4559","question":"Why is it a good safety practice to face the rear of the horse when mounting?","answer":"Easier to keep your balance or easier to your control horse (accept either)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4560","question":"Why is it important to keep your horse under control and to keep a secure seat?","answer":"Horses are easily frightened by unusual objects and noises (also accept so you won't fall off)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4561","question":"Do NOT show a horse until you are sure of what?","answer":"That you can control the horse."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4562","question":"On what side of the road should you ride?","answer":"With traffic or the side required by state law (accept either)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4563","question":"When riding, if an obstacle frightens your horse, what should you do?","answer":"Steady him and give him time to overcome his fear and then ride by the obstacle (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4564","question":"What should you tell someone who's going to ride your horse?","answer":"Tell them what to expect."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4565","question":"Why is it NOT a good idea to pair a young rider and a young horse?","answer":"Both are inexperienced (and don't know how to react in an emergency)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4566","question":"When going up and down hills, you should always use which gait?","answer":"Walk (let him pick his own way so he doesn't slip or fall)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4567","question":"While riding, what should you do if your horse becomes frightened and tries to run away?","answer":"Do a one rein stop (Turn him in a circle and tighten the circle until he stops.)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4568","question":"How can you prevent many riding-related head injuries?","answer":"Wear a helmet"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4569","question":"Why should you NEVER mount or dismount near fences, barns, or overhanging projections?","answer":"You may get hurt."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4570","question":"Which gait should you use when riding on rough ground or in sand, mud, ice, or snow?","answer":"Walk (let him pick his own way so he doesn't slip or fall)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4571","question":"When trail riding in a group with riders and horses of varying experience, describe the riding order—experience-wise—that's the safest.","answer":"Most experienced in lead, least experienced in middle, and strong rider bringing up rear."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"jr bonus","number":"4572","question":"Name 3 times you should check your cinch.","answer":"After saddling, after walking a few steps, after mounting and riding a short distance"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4573","question":"Why should you recheck the cinch just before mounting the horse?","answer":"Because the cinch often loosens after you walk your horse around"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4574","question":"When using a double-rigged saddle, which cinch should you LOOSEN FIRST?","answer":"Back cinch"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4575","question":"In using a double rigged saddle, which cinch should you buckle FIRST?","answer":"Front cinch"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4576","question":"What should you check on your saddle just before you mount or get on?","answer":"Cinch"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4577","question":"When saddling your horse, what may happen if you drop the saddle down quick or hard on the horse's back?","answer":"You might scare the horse or hurt his back."},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4578","question":"When using a double-rigged saddle, which cinch should you BUCKLE LAST?","answer":"Back cinch"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4579","question":"What are TWO basic knots every horse person should know?","answer":"Quick release, bowline, square knot, half hitch, double half hitch"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"easy","number":"4580","question":"What type of knot should be used when tying a rope around a horse’s neck?  This type of knot will not slip or tighten and choke the horse.","answer":"Bowline"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4581","question":"What is the only thing you should tie your horse with?","answer":"Lead rope, halter rope, or halter and lead rope (accept any)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4582","question":"Why should you NEVER tie a horse with the reins?","answer":"He might pull back, break the reins, or injure his mouth (accept any)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4583","question":"Why should you tie your horse far away from strange horses?","answer":"So they won’t fight"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4584","question":"When your horse is tied, what should you ALWAYS do before removing the halter?","answer":"Untie the horse (so if the horse pulls back, you won't get hurt)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4585","question":"You should NEVER tie a horse with what?","answer":"Reins or bridle (accept either)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4586","question":"What is the recommended knot for tying a halter rope to a fixed object?","answer":"Quick release knot"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"novice","number":"4587","question":"NEVER tie a horse at a level below what point of the horse?","answer":"Withers or shoulders (accept either)"},
{"category":"Safety","level":"sr bonus","number":"4588","question":"What are 3 features of a good knot?","answer":"Easy to tie; strong; holds firmly; easy to untie if used for livestock"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4589","question":"2 part question:  What is the MINIMUM height for an indoor arena and why is a higher ceiling more desirable?","answer":"14 feet minimum; the higher the ceiling, the better lit the arena will be(fewer shadows) (FYI:  Indoor arenas used for jumping should be at least 16 feet tall.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4590","question":"What is the MINIMUM size for a training arena?","answer":"60 x 100 feet"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4591","question":"What is the MINIMUM size for an arena used for shows or for the public?","answer":"120 x 100 feet"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4592","question":"What is usually the most limiting factor of new barn and fence construction?","answer":"Cost"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4593","question":"When building a barn, what is a common mistake regarding the installation of electrical outlets?","answer":"Not providing enough electrical outlets (FYI: There should be at least one double outlet for every two stalls.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4594","question":"Give 3 safety features for barn electrical systems.","answer":"Follow code, safe panel boxes, protected switch boxes, protected outlets, wires in conduits, thermostats on  water heaters, protected light bulbs, grounded appliances, power shutoff prominently marked, lightning rods, no portable heaters"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4595","question":"Which type of barn lighting—incandescent, fluorescent, or LED—is the most energy efficient?","answer":"LED"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4596","question":"Give 3 basic steps of a barn escape plan.","answer":"Escape plan, holding area, fire drills, personnel trained in horse handling, simulated emergency for horses and handlers, emergency equipment with knowledge of use, don’t lock stall doors, have two stall doors, have blindfolds available"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4597","question":"Give 3 requirements of a good feed room.","answer":"Conveniently located; protects feed from moisture, protects feed from horses, protects feed from vermin such as mice; good ventilation; not too hot or cold; dry; clean (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4598","question":"Name TWO factors to be considered when buying building materials for barns.","answer":"Cost; attractiveness; fire resistance; durability; maintenance; safety"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4599","question":"Name 3 advantages of using wood for barn construction.","answer":"Strong; attractive; good insulator; easier to install ventilation system"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4600","question":"How should the stall partitions be placed so the horse's legs can't get caught under them?","answer":"Flush with or slightly below the floor"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4601","question":"2 part question:  When constructing a horse stall, what spacing should be used for the partition bars and why?","answer":"3 ½ - 4 inches spacing so that the horse’s foot can’t get stuck between the bars (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4602","question":"When building a stall, should the stall door be placed to swing in towards the stall or swing out towards the aisle?","answer":"Swing out"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4603","question":"Give ONE major purpose of a stall door.","answer":"Keep the horse safely in the stall; to let the horse into the stall; to let the horse out of the stall"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4604","question":"In addition to keeping a horse in the stall, give TWO other functions of a stall guard.","answer":"Better ventilation; more light; more fresh air; allows horse to hang its head out of the stall; decreases respiratory problems; decreases boredom and vices; provides a fire exit (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4605","question":"Name 3 types of stall doors.","answer":"Full wood; full mesh; half wood and half mesh; bars; half wood and half bars; sliding; Dutch (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4606","question":"2 part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using hinged double doors on stalls.","answer":"Advantages—top door can be left open which allows horse to stick his head out, get more ventilation, get more light; disadvantages—tend to sag, possibility that one door may not be closed tightly"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4607","question":"Give 3 advantages of using Dutch or open top exterior doors for each horse stall.","answer":"Better ventilation; more light; more fresh air; allows horse to hang its head out of the stall; decreases respiratory problems; decreases boredom and vices; provides a fire exit (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4608","question":"What type of stall door is the safest and the easiest to use around horses?","answer":"Sliding door"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4609","question":"When using wire mesh as a stall front, why should the holes be 2 x 2 inches or smaller?","answer":"Safety (so horses can’t get their foot caught) (FYI: A foal’s foot can be as small as 2 inches wide.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4610","question":"What substance helps to reduce the ammonia level in stalls?","answer":"Hydrated lime (lime)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4611","question":"Name ONE thing that should be done to prepare stall floors before installing rubber mats.","answer":"Make sure the floor is level; make sure the floor is well-packed; make sure there's adequate drainage."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4612","question":"Horses that are kept in stalls for any length of time depend on a good stall floor for comfort and safety.  Name 3 factors you would look for in choosing flooring material for your horse.","answer":"Durable; non-slip; absorbent; easy to clean; resistant to pawing; cost; amount of bedding needed; availability; non-toxic (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4613","question":"Name 3 of the more commonly used materials for stall floors.","answer":"Clay; clay and sand mix; limestone dust; wood; concrete, asphalt; rubber mats (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4614","question":"What type of stall floor material has many of the same disadvantages as concrete?","answer":"Asphalt"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4615","question":"What is the most popular base floor material for a box stall?","answer":"Hard-packed clay"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4616","question":"2 part question:  Give TWO advantages and TWO disadvantages to using concrete floors in stalls.","answer":"Advantages—drains quickly if properly sloped, doesn't collect urine, rat-hole proof, easy to clean; disadvantages—cold, hard, needs more bedding, slippery, can have poor drainage, associated with leg problems        "},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4617","question":"When properly applied, what type of stall floor material will be as hard as concrete, but without concrete’s disadvantages?","answer":"Limestone dust"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4618","question":"In order to resist pawing, how thick should rubber mats used as stall flooring be?","answer":"5/8 inch (also accept around ½ inch)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4619","question":"Name ONE disadvantage of using wood floors in stalls.","answer":"Slippery when wet; prone to attract rodents; difficult to clean; harbor odors (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4620","question":"Why should wood floors in stalls be at least two inches thick?","answer":"To decrease risk of rotting or decay"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4621","question":"What is the MINIMUM size recommended for a box stall?","answer":"10 feet x 10 feet"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4622","question":"What size should a stallion stall be?","answer":"14 feet x 14 feet"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4623","question":"What is the MOST POPULAR box stall size?","answer":"12 feet x 12 feet"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4624","question":"What is the ideal stall size for a draft horse?","answer":"14 feet x 14 feet"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4625","question":"What is the MINIMUM size of a foaling stall?","answer":"12 feet x 14 feet (also accept 12 x 16, 16 x 16, 16 x 20) "},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4626","question":"Name ONE general type of horse that is commonly housed in a tie stall.","answer":"Draft, hack, carriage, livery "},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4627","question":"What is the MINIMUM height for a stall wall?","answer":"8 (eight) feet"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4628","question":"Why should you use treated lumber for the bottom boards of stall partitions?","answer":"To prevent rotting"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4629","question":"Name TWO things that should be considered when constructing interior stall walls.","answer":"Safety and durability (smooth, rugged materials free from any projections that can injure the horse)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4630","question":"2 part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using concrete when building stalls.","answer":"Advantages—easy to paint, easy to keep clean; disadvantages—can cause injury to horse if it hits it, must be reinforced so it won’t fall, more expensive"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4631","question":"Name ONE problem with using “green” oak for partitions, windows, or doors when building stalls.","answer":"It will shrink and/or twist as it dries."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4632","question":"What is one of the most desirable materials for building a stall?","answer":"Wood"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4633","question":"Name ONE horse health problem that can be caused by a poorly ventilated or drafty barn.","answer":"Respiratory problems (such as heaves, pneumonia, etc.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4634","question":"Give ONE reason why horse barns must be well ventilated.","answer":"Prevent condensation; prevent odor buildup; decrease humidity; improve air quality; help prevent respiratory problems"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4635","question":"Horses can do well in almost any environment if what two conditions are met?","answer":"Humidity held to comfortable level; good ventilation"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4636","question":"What is the rule of thumb ventilation guide?","answer":"1 (one) foot of ridge ventilation for each horse or stall in the barn"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4637","question":"Barns constructed with aluminum or steel can be hot in the summer and cold in the winter unless what TWO things are ensured?","answer":"Adequate insulation and adequate ventilation"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4638","question":"The biggest mistake in most barns is that they are built for human comfort, not for equine health. What is the primary fault found in these barns?","answer":"Poor ventilation"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4639","question":"In the stable, adequate ventilation is necessary to reduce the presence of air contaminants.  Name TWO examples of air contaminants.","answer":"Dust; mold; irritating gases (such as ammonia or methane); airborne bacteria; microscopic debris"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4640","question":"2 part question:  Name two barn conditions that are the most detrimental to a horse's health and explain why.","answer":"Extreme temperatures and high humidity; can cause respiratory problems (can harm the respiratory system or allow the inhalation of pathogens)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4641","question":"Adequate ventilation of a stable area is defined as how many air changes per hour?","answer":"4 - 8 changes per hour (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4642","question":"What is the main purpose of a cupola on a barn roof?","answer":"Ventilation"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4643","question":"Name ONE structure commonly found on a barn roof that functions to properly ventilate a barn.","answer":"Cupola; ridge vents"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4644","question":"You do the math…Following the rule of thumb recommendation for adequate ventilation in a barn, a barn with 8 stalls would require how much ridge ventilation?","answer":"At least 8 feet of ridge ventilation (1 foot per stall)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4645","question":"The temperature inside a barn should be no more than 5 degrees above what?","answer":"Outside temperature"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4646","question":"Keeping the air temperature in the barn at no more than 5 degrees above the outside temperature will provide the air quality the horse needs, but may be inconvenient for whom?","answer":"Handlers (people)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4647","question":"You do the math…If it's 70 degrees outside, what should the MAXIMUM temperature be inside the barn?","answer":"75 degrees (FYI:  The inside of the barn should be no more than 5 degrees hotter than the outside of the barn.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4648","question":"What is the GENERAL term used for materials placed on stall floors that absorb moisture and provide comfort to the horse?","answer":"Bedding"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4649","question":"What is bedding?","answer":"Material used to cover the stall floor to provide comfort for the horse and to absorb moisture. (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4650","question":"What are 3 factors that should be considered when selecting the appropriate bedding for your horse's stall?","answer":"Absorbency; dust content; availability; easily disposable; cost; unpalatable; specific use; non-toxic (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4651","question":"Name 3 functions of bedding.","answer":"Encourages horse to lie down or rest; cushions horse’s feet and legs; soaks up urine and moisture"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4652","question":"Name ONE of the most popular kinds of bedding.","answer":"Shavings, straw, sawdust, cornstalks, shredded newspaper, peanut shells, peat moss, rice hulls, wood pellets"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4653","question":"Name 3 types of bedding.","answer":"Shavings, straw, sawdust, cornstalks, shredded newspaper, peanut shells, peat moss, rice hulls, wood pellets"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4654","question":"What is the most common symptom in horses that have been stabled on hardwood shavings that contain black walnut?","answer":"Lameness (due to laminitis)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4655","question":"2 part question:  When using wood shavings for bedding, what specific wood should be avoided and why?","answer":"Black walnut; it can cause laminitis or founder"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4656","question":"What type of shavings range in color from coffee brown to purplish black?","answer":"Black walnut"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4657","question":"Name 3 advantages to using recycled newsprint for bedding","answer":"Less dust; no pollen; very absorbent; softer and more comfortable than shavings or straw; less respiratory disease; inexpensive; eco-friendly"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4658","question":"2 part question:  Give TWO advantages and TWO disadvantages of using sawdust or wood shavings for bedding.","answer":"Advantages—less volume, less labor, easier disposal, less combustible, seldom eaten, less odor, absorbent, good for compost; Disadvantages—cost, dusty, may cause respiratory problems, some types can cause problems (oak, black walnut, and cedar)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4659","question":"You are trying to decide between straw and wood shavings for bedding for your 10 horse boarding facility.  Straw is cheaper, but why would it be more economical to use shavings?","answer":"Shavings are less labor intensive so you'd save on labor expenses."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4660","question":"2 part question:  Give TWO advantages and TWO disadvantages of using straw for bedding.","answer":"Advantages—cheap, absorbent, comfortable, attractive, low dust, doesn’t stick to newborn foal’s nostrils or clog airway; Disadvantages—highly combustible, horses will eat it, labor intensive (large volume of debris, hard to dispose of)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4661","question":"What is the ideal bedding for a foaling stall?","answer":"Straw (FYI: Shavings or sawdust can get stuck in the newborn's nostrils.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4662","question":"Why is straw preferred over shavings in bedding for a foaling stall?","answer":"Shavings can stick to the nostrils of the newborn foal."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4663","question":"In regards to biosecurity, identify 3 ways to diminish the possibility of transferring infective agents with your boots.","answer":"Disinfect boots using a spray disinfectant; wear disposable boots or boot covers; disinfect boots with a boot dip; change boots (between farms or between clean and dirty areas)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4664","question":"When introducing new horses into a herd, biosecurity measures would include isolating the new horses for a MINIMUM of how many days?","answer":"14 days"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4665","question":"The US horse industry uses two types of feed management systems.  One is grazing full time.  What is the other?","answer":"Confined feeding (feeding hay or grain in a stall or paddock)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4666","question":"Why can foals and growing horses usually be fed in groups with little problems?","answer":"Dominance hierarchies or pecking orders have not yet become strongly established."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4667","question":"Hay should be fed in what?","answer":"Some type of feeder (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4668","question":"Give TWO reasons why a horse owner should take its horse's feed and water buckets with it when traveling.","answer":"Familiar containers reduce stress; reduces risk of disease from contaminated mangers or water tanks"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4669","question":"What is the name of the structure that allows foals to eat without interference from the mare?","answer":"Creep feeder"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4670","question":"Give 3 general features of a good horse fence.","answer":"Strong; high; tight; highly visible; safe"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4671","question":"What are TWO considerations when installing a paddock gate?","answer":"Location—not in a corner or in a low, wet area; size—is it people, horses, or machinery; material—is it durable, is it safe for horses; gate should be level with the top of the fence; handler should be able to open and close it with one hand"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4672","question":"Name TWO places where a gate should NOT be placed in a pasture.","answer":"Corner of fence line; low or wet areas; area with unsuitable terrain or footing"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4673","question":"What is the minimal width of a gate that will be used to move equipment in and out of a pasture?","answer":"12 feet (FYI:  Gates used for hay equipment should be at least 16 feet wide.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4674","question":"For the average 15 hand horse, how high should the outside pasture fence be?","answer":"Minimum of 5 feet (also accept several inches above the horse's withers) (FYI:  Divider fences should be at least 4 ½ feet tall.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4675","question":"Give ONE reason why the top of a corral or paddock fence should be at the eye level of the horse’s head, when the horse's head is held in a natural position.","answer":"To discourage fighting over the fence; so the horse can’t hang his head over the fence (which could cause the fence to sag)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4676","question":"If possible, pastures should have rounded corners for safety.  What is a big problem with square corners in pastures?","answer":"One horse can trap another."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4677","question":"Give TWO meanings of the word paddock.","answer":"Small fenced area smaller than a pasture and larger than a run; area where race horses are saddled and viewed before a race"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4678","question":"Name 3 types of fencing for horses.","answer":"Board, post and rail, wire (hot, barbless, high tensile, stock, 5 diamond V mesh), pipe, panels, PVC, vinyl, chain link (used for small pens and paddocks), cable, rubber (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4679","question":"Name ONE type of horse fence that has a short life expectancy.","answer":"Board, post and rail, or plastic"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4680","question":"Name 3 DISADVANTAGES of metal fence posts.","answer":"Not attractive; can bend; can rust; can injure horse"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4681","question":"Name ONE kind of wood that is good for fence posts.","answer":"Black locust, cedar, osage orange, or western juniper "},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4682","question":"Wooden fence posts should be at least what diameter?","answer":"4 inches in diameter"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4683","question":"What is the biggest DISADVANTAGE of PVC or vinyl fencing?","answer":"It's expensive."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4684","question":"Give TWO advantages of using high tensile vinyl fencing.","answer":"Safe; strong; durable; low maintenance; long-lasting; cost effective"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4685","question":"What is a characteristic of wire mesh, high tensile wire, and electric fences that can result in injury to horses confined by them?","answer":"They're hard for horses to see."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4686","question":"Give 3 examples of wire fencing.","answer":"Diamond mesh; woven wire; stock wire; high tensile wire; barbed wire; barbless wire; electric or hot wire"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4687","question":"Name 3 things that should be considered when installing a wire fence.","answer":"Sight board; board in middle (keeps horses from leaning on/stretching fence); wire attached on inside of post; should be 10 gauge or heavier (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4688","question":"Besides adding a sight board or board to the top of the fence, what can you add to a wire fence to keep horses from leaning on and stretching the fence?","answer":"Board in the middle of the fence (also accept hot wire)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4689","question":"What type of fence is strongly DISCOURAGED for use with horses?","answer":"Barbed wire or mesh with large holes (accept either)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4690","question":"Name ONE disadvantage of electric fencing.","answer":"Not very visible; shorts out easily"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4691","question":"What device is used to keep horses off the fence therefore reducing  damage to the fence and injury to the horse?","answer":"Hot wire or electric wire"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4692","question":"Name ONE disadvantage of using electric tape for fencing.","answer":"It can wear, stretch, loosen, or break."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4693","question":"What type of electric fence is considered to be safer because it is more visible, therefore causing less injuries to horses?","answer":"Electric tape"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4694","question":"When fencing  horse pastures, what is the most effective way to use an electric fence?","answer":"In conjunction with another fence (use the electric fence at the top of the fence to keep the horses off of the other fence)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4695","question":"Other than hot wire, what is the most common kind of wire fencing for horses?","answer":"Woven wire or stock wire"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4696","question":"2 part question:  What is the best and safest wire for horse fencing and why?","answer":"Five diamond V mesh or rectangular mesh with small openings; small openings prevent horse’s foot from getting caught"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4697","question":"Name TWO types of wire mesh openings.","answer":"Diamond and rectangular"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4698","question":"2 part question:  On what side of the post should fence boards be nailed and why?","answer":"Inside; so the horse can't knock the boards off"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4699","question":"Name 3 ADVANTAGES of a wood board fence.","answer":"Attractive; rugged; safe; easily seen by horse; good for rolling land"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4700","question":"Name 3 DISADVANTAGES of a wood board fence.","answer":"Expensive; can be chewed; can splinter; can break; can rot"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4701","question":"Give ONE reason why the bottom board on a fence should be approximately 12 inches above the ground level.","answer":"For mowing; to prevent foals from rolling under it"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4702","question":"What size boards should be used for a wood fence?","answer":"1 x 6 or 1 x 8 (1 inch thick by 6 or 8 inches wide) "},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4703","question":"Why should fence boards for corrals and small paddocks be at least two inches thick?","answer":"To decrease injury to the horse and/or fence (FYI: It's harder for horses to stop in a small area so they might run into the fence.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4704","question":"Board fencing is expensive, but practical for several things.  Name 3.","answer":"Stallion paddocks; sale pens; show pens; turn-out areas; arenas; creating good looking effect for front paddocks and along driveways to barns"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4705","question":"You have just finished installing a beautiful white painted fence around your pasture, but you have a problem.  Your horses are leaning on the fence and fighting over it.  What can you do to keep the horses off the fence?","answer":"Put a hot wire on the top board on each side of the fence"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4706","question":"If not properly installed, what can happen with post and rail fencing?","answer":"Rails can slip out of the posts."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4707","question":"Name 3 DISADVANTAGES of a post and rail fence.","answer":"More expensive than boards; posts tend to split; doesn't hold up well"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4708","question":"When comparing the life expectancy of untreated wood fence posts, which of the following types of wood would last the longest:  white oak, black locust, or yellow poplar?","answer":"Black locust"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4709","question":"Which type of posts last longer, pressure treated or untreated?","answer":"Pressure treated (lasts 4 times as long and untreated)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4710","question":"Oak has been the wood traditionally chosen for construction of wood fences on equine facilities.  What is the major advantage of using hardwoods, especially oak, for a fence?","answer":"Oak is too hard for horses to chew."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4711","question":"2 part question:  Which type of wood is LEAST preferred for horse fences and give ONE reason why?","answer":"Soft pines or firs; weak in strength, horses like to chew it"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4712","question":"Name ONE problem that may occur if a hay rack is hung too high for the horse eating from it.","answer":"Hay may get into the horse's eyes; horse may inhale dust (which could lead to respiratory problems)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4713","question":"What is the main factor to consider when storing hay?","answer":"Protecting the hay (from moisture, sun, heat, etc.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4714","question":"Give ONE reason NOT to store hay above horse stalls.","answer":"Dust, mold, fire hazard"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4715","question":"If you store hay above stalls, how much space must be left between the hay and the walls for air passage?","answer":"At least 12 inches (1 foot)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4716","question":"What is meant by the term \"mucking out\"?","answer":"Cleaning a stall (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4717","question":"What term refers to the process of cleaning out a horse stall by removing the manure and soiled bedding?","answer":"Mucking out (also accept stripping, picking out the stall, or other correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4718","question":"Name ONE thing that is destroyed in manure when temperatures reach 131 degrees F for 3 days.","answer":"Parasites, weed seeds, pathogenic bacteria"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4719","question":"Name 3 specific microorganisms that can contaminate water.","answer":"Salmonella; E. coli; Leptospira; Cryptosporidium; Giardia; blue-green algae"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4720","question":"Name 3 SPECIFIC microorganisms that may be transmitted between horses and humans through fecal material.","answer":"E. Coli; Giardia; Salmonella"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4721","question":"How is manure usually managed in a pasture?","answer":"Spread"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4722","question":"Name TWO recommended methods for manure management.","answer":"Compost (remove and compost); stockpile (remove and store in piles); land application (remove daily and spread on cropland)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4723","question":"Give 3 key components of a Manure Management Plan (MMP).","answer":"Considerations of stocking; density of horses; amount of manure produced; knowledge of levels of nutrients in manure; appropriate manure storage and manure management (land application, hauling off site, etc.); soil testing and records of activities"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4724","question":"To keep fly larvae from developing in the outer layers of stockpiled manure for compost heaps, you should cover the manure pile with what?","answer":"Black plastic"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4725","question":"Why is properly composted manure and bedding safe to spread on pastures without worry about the spread of parasites, pathogenic bacteria, or weed seeds?","answer":"Composted manure will reach a temperature that will destroy these problems."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4726","question":"Name ONE thing that can happen if too much composted manure or bedding is added to the surface of a riding arena.","answer":"It can hold excess moisture and cause horses to slip and fall; it can have excessive dust and odor."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4727","question":"2 part question:  Name TWO  factors that must be optimum for microbes when composting manure.","answer":"Temperature; moisture; carbon to nitrogen ratio"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4728","question":"Composting stall waste for one to two months reduces the volume of waste by what percentage?","answer":"40 - 70 percent (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4729","question":"When properly composted, manure can be used for what?","answer":"Fertilizer or soil conditioner"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4730","question":"What is “compost tea”?","answer":"Compost soaked in water (so the nutrients leach into the water)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4731","question":"What is the method of managing manure that results in biodegradation of organic material?","answer":"Composting"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4732","question":"On what type of land is it suitable to spread uncomposted manure?","answer":"Crop land or other un-grazed, vegetated areas (accept either)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4733","question":"When using a two bin composting system, how long is it before the composted manure in the first bin is ready to use?","answer":"2 - 4 months (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4734","question":"How often should a manure pile be turned for aeration for optimum composting?","answer":"Every 10 days"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4735","question":"Name 3 ways you can use compost at home.","answer":"Gardens; new planting areas; surface mulch; lawn top dressing; potting mix; compost “tea”; spreading on pastures"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4736","question":"Name 3 things to consider when determining the quality of compost.","answer":"pH; nutrient content; organic matter content; moisture content; particle content"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4737","question":"What should be done after rotating horses off pasture in order to spread the manure out in a thin layer for drying?","answer":"Drag or harrow the pasture"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4738","question":"How far should a manure storage area be from a drinking water well?","answer":"100 – 500 feet (accept any number within this range) [200 feet is best; 500 feet from public water sources]"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4739","question":"What can you do to prevent mud holes around gates, water tanks, and feeding areas?","answer":"Fill the areas with gravel (or use geo-textile fabrics)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4740","question":"Which is generally higher, the purchase price of a horse or the  maintenance costs of a horse?","answer":"Maintenance costs"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4741","question":"What health factor must you consider when purchasing paint or stain for horse stalls or fences?","answer":"Must be non-toxic"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4742","question":"When planning a horse facility, what should be the MAIN consideration?","answer":"Safety (also accept cost)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4743","question":"Name 3 things a horse owner needs to consider before deciding to keep a horse at home.","answer":"Space; zoning laws; fencing; shelter; water; hay or pasture; food storage facility; time for animal care; knowledge for animal care; manure management (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4744","question":"In reference to management of horse facilities, what do the initials BMP stand for?","answer":"Best Management Practices"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4745","question":"A complete set of records should be kept on every horse.  Name 3 pieces of information that should be kept.","answer":"Horse ID—name, registration number, sex, breed, color, markings, tattoo, brand, height, weight; boarding info—phone numbers; feeding info; health info—vaccinations, hoof care, worming, dental, castration, illnesses, injuries (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4746","question":"Name 3 functions of housing for horses.","answer":"Provide for welfare of horse; provide for safety of handlers; provide for comfort of handlers; make efficient use of labor; cost effective; shelter; confinement"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4747","question":"Your horse is a living animal that depends upon you for its basic needs.  Name 3 basic needs that have to be provided.","answer":"Food, water, space, shelter, hoof care, health care (shots, worming, etc.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4748","question":"Name TWO important features to consider when constructing a wash rack.","answer":"Good footing when wet (safety); adequate drainage"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4749","question":"Why may putting a blanket on a horse with a winter coat actually make the horse colder rather than warmer?","answer":"Horse's winter coat traps heat between the hair; putting a blanket on may compress the hair (eliminating the air layer and reducing the horse's natural protection against the cold)."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4750","question":"Name 3 things to consider before beginning construction when planning a horse facility.","answer":"Cost; safety; quality; purpose; design; layout; maintenance; number of animals; zoning laws; room for future expansion; geography; topography; climate; environmental impact; landscape; style; utilities (electricity and water); resale value"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4751","question":"In regards to pasture management, name TWO circumstances when you should keep horses off the pasture.","answer":"During pesticide spraying; during fertilizing; after re-seeding; to reduce overgrazing; when pasture is lush; during the winter; when the soil is wet (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4752","question":"Name TWO management practices that one must consider when maintaining pasture for ground cover and to provide quality nutrition for horses.","answer":"Pasture appropriate for the location; grass varieties that will thrive with the soil and climate; stocking capacity; fertilizing (based on soil testing); controlling weeds; creating sacrifice area; properly managed grazing"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4753","question":"Name 3 requirements of a good winter pasture.","answer":"3-sided shelter or natural windbreak; water source that won't freeze; place free from mud or wind where horses can be fed (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4754","question":"You should check your pasture or turnout area for unsafe conditions.  Name 3.","answer":"Junk; holes; poisonous plants; broken fences; loose boards; sharp objects (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"jr bonus","number":"4755","question":"Give 3 characteristics of a good pasture area for horses.","answer":"Forage; water; salt; no weeds or toxic plants; shelter or shade; no junk; no holes; good fence; fence of adequate height; no barbed wire; adequate size (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4756","question":"Give TWO benefits to keeping your pastures clipped or mowed.","answer":"Prevents plants from becoming too mature; helps maintain balance of grasses and legumes; controls weeds; helps spread manure"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4757","question":"Name 3 steps in good pasture management.","answer":"Don't overgraze; rotate pastures; mow pastures; scatter manure piles; no junk; no toxic plants; no noxious weeds; keep horses off wet pasture to avoid turf damage; soil test; fertilize as needed; proper stocking rates (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"intermediate","number":"4758","question":"At least 2 - 3 acres of pasture per horse are needed in order to maintain what?","answer":"Forage productivity (production of enough grass to feed the horses)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4759","question":"Referring to pastures, what is \"carrying capacity\"?","answer":"Number of animals that a habitat can support"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4760","question":"If you have less than 1 ½ acres of pasture per horse, the grass won't be able to do what?","answer":"Grow adequately (won't be able to be productive under constant grazing)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4761","question":"In reference to horse paddocks, what is a “dry lot”?","answer":"Paddock with no plants"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4762","question":"During what season should the last application of nitrogen be applied to the pasture?","answer":"Late summer"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4763","question":"Fertilizing and liming are two important components of the management of what?","answer":"Pastures"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4764","question":"If the soil test indicates, what should be applied to a pasture to improve forage growth and to raise the pH of the soil?","answer":"Lime"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4765","question":"What method is used to determine how much fertilizer your pasture needs in order to maintain it in top condition?","answer":"Soil test"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4766","question":"Yearly fertilizer applications should be applied to pasture at what time of year?","answer":"1 - 3 months before the beginning of the growing season"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4767","question":"Generally, at what grass height should horses be removed from a pasture to prevent overgrazing?","answer":"Less than 4 inches in height (FYI:  Most cool season pastures can be grazed to about 2 – 3 inches, but close grazing severely stunts pasture regrowth.  Horses should then be removed until the pasture regrows to a height of at least 6 – 8 inches.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4768","question":"What height should pasture grasses be for grazing horses?","answer":"4 - 8 inches (accept any number within this range) (FYI:  Grass height recommendations vary from source to source and from species to species.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4769","question":"If you turn too many horses out in a small pasture and allow it to be overgrazed, what will happen to the pasture?","answer":"It will become an exercise lot or dry lot (it won't have enough forage to provide adequate nutrition) (also accept could increase erosion, water runoff, and water pollution)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4770","question":"Name ONE thing that should be prevented in good pasture management to maximize regrowth of pastures and minimize weed invasion.","answer":"Overgrazing; soil compaction"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4771","question":"What TWO things will become a problem when 10% or more of the soil is exposed as a result of overgrazing?","answer":"Weeds and erosion"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4772","question":"What is the primary cause of runoff on horse farms?","answer":"Overgrazing"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4773","question":"Give ONE reason why horses should be rotated to fresh pasture every two weeks.","answer":"To allow the pasture time to regrow or to reduce parasite infestations"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4774","question":"What is rotational grazing?","answer":"Letting horses graze one pasture for a while, then moving them to another pasture (so the first pasture can rest)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4775","question":"What does resting your pasture do?","answer":"Gives grass time to regrow.  (Lets grass develop strong roots to prevent soil erosion.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4776","question":"What is the advantage to rotating horses with cattle or sheep in a pasture?","answer":"Breaks the parasite life cycle"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4777","question":"How does rotational grazing increase pasture productivity?","answer":"Allows time for pasture to re-grow (replaces leaf tissue and replenishes carbohydrate levels)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4778","question":"Give ONE reason why horses are spot grazers.","answer":"Horses choose to graze in preferred areas; horses choose to graze on specific forage species or types of plants; horses will not ordinarily eat grass that’s contaminated with feces."},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4779","question":"Horses are spot grazers.  Give 3 results of repeated grazing in the same area.","answer":"Carbohydrate reserves of plants are depleted; plants are unable to grow new leaves; plants are eliminated from the pasture; get areas of tall grass; weeds will grow in the manure piles"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4780","question":"2 part question:  Besides dragging your pasture, name TWO ways you can get better manure distribution in the pasture and avoid concentration of manure in isolated spots of the pastures.","answer":"Move feeding troughs periodically; have several watering facilities available; split pastures; rotate pastures"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4781","question":"How many times a year should pastures be mowed and chain harrowed or dragged to break up manure piles and expose parasite eggs to the elements?","answer":"2 - 4 times per year (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4782","question":"In general, how often should a pasture be re-seeded?","answer":"Every 3 - 5 years (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4783","question":"How long should pastures be rested after re-seeding?","answer":"2 – 6 weeks (FYI:  Length of rest depends on plant species, weather, and soil type.)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4784","question":"What happens to a pasture if horses are allowed to be in the pasture during very wet weather?","answer":"Turf damage"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4785","question":"Drainage from a 3-sided run-in shed to an absorption pit or grass waterway should have what percent of slope?","answer":"2% (accept any number within the 2% - 6% range)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4786","question":"As opposed to keeping horses in separate stalls, name ONE disadvantage of using open front shelters or run-in sheds for several horses.","answer":"Unable to monitor diet of each individual horse; unable to monitor the amount of exercise of each horse; increased risk of injuries (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4787","question":"Name 3 features that would be desirable in an open front shelter.","answer":"Face away from prevailing winds; 20 feet deep; opening wide enough for all horses to safely run out; roof slopes away from opening; built on high ground; 2% slope (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4788","question":"Name 3 advantages of an open front shelter.","answer":"Inexpensive; no daily stall cleaning; less labor; well ventilated; less fire risk; less space needed per horse; less bedding required; horses have room to move"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4789","question":"When planning a horse facility there are many things to consider that are part of the natural environment.  What term describes the shape and the slope of the land?","answer":"Topography"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4790","question":"You are an equine construction specialist and are preparing a site for a new barn.  In regards to topography, what would be your recommendation for grading the soil to facilitate proper drainage and prevent erosion?","answer":"Slope of 2 - 6%"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4791","question":"As part of an environmental analysis, name 3 natural features that should be considered before building a new horse facility.","answer":"Topography or slope of land; drainage; prevailing winds; solar radiation; precipitation; vegetation; soil characteristics; available water (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4792","question":"Name ONE thing that can cause ground water contamination.","answer":"Improperly constructed wells; fuel spills; pesticides; herbicides; fertilizers; manure (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4793","question":"What are 3 techniques for reducing runoff?","answer":"Divert clean runoff water away from yucky areas; use terraces or water bars to decrease slopes; plant grass in drainage ditches to slow down runoff water; plant a 10+ foot vegetative buffer strip between steep slopes and waterways (accept any correct)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4794","question":"In reference to soil and water management, what is TSS?","answer":"Total Soluble Salts"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4795","question":"What is used as the standard test for bacteriological safety of water?","answer":"Fecal coliform counts"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4796","question":"Give ONE purpose of a buffer strip in watercourse management.","answer":"Filters horse waste and soil from the runoff water; slows the water down for better absorption"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"hard","number":"4797","question":"2 part question:  What does TDS stand for and what does it indicate about water quality?","answer":"Total dissolved solids; high TDS indicates water may be contaminated, unfit for consumption, or may have high salinity (accept any)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4798","question":"2 part question:  Name TWO goals of a water quality management plan.","answer":"Reduce runoff; protect ground water from contamination"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4799","question":"Give 3 purposes of increasing the vegetative cover between steep slopes and waterways.","answer":"Slows down runoff water; increases absorption of runoff water; filters animal wastes; filters soil out; helps prevent soil erosion"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4800","question":"Erosion of your pastures is affected by what 3 environmental or topographical factors?","answer":"Soil type; slope of the land; amount of precipitation; vegetative cover (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"sr bonus","number":"4801","question":"Give 3 ways to protect streams and river banks from trampling, destruction of vegetation, and contamination.","answer":"Deny access with fencing; limit access with fencing; create natural buffer zones; use water tanks instead of allowing stream access; no chemicals near stream; no chemicals in storm drains or sewers; dispose of chemicals properly (accept any correct)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"int bonus","number":"4802","question":"Name 3 DISADVANTAGES of an automatic waterer.","answer":"Initial expense; malfunction; horses may play with it; not cleaned regularly; excessive water intake when horse is hot; no way to monitor water intake; electric shock (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4803","question":"Give ONE way a bucket that's used for watering a horse should be managed to prevent infectious diseases.","answer":"Should be emptied at least once a day; should be cleaned every 2 - 3 days; should be cleaned daily if there's an illness in the barn"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4804","question":"When using herbicides to control weeds, it's important to do what?","answer":"Follow the directions"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4805","question":"Name ONE method of weed control.","answer":"Herbicides (weed killers); pulls weeds; mow pastures; biological control"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4806","question":"Give ONE reason why it's important to identify which weeds are present in your pasture.","answer":"So you can use the right product to control them; so you can identify if any are poisonous; so they won’t crowd out the grass"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4807","question":"Name ONE cost-effective method of weed control.","answer":"Prevention; encourage good grass growth; remove horses from pasture; mow pasture twice a year"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4808","question":"What do you call an unwanted or out of place plant?","answer":"Weed"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"easy","number":"4809","question":"What do weeds and brush in a pasture often indicate?","answer":"Pasture has been overgrazed, poorly managed, or inadequately fertilized(accept any)"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"novice","number":"4810","question":"What unwanted plants can grow in bare areas in pastures? ","answer":"Weeds"},
{"category":"Stable and Pasture Management","level":"medium","number":"4811","question":"Since new weeds often fill in the spaces left after herbicides are used, it's important to do what?","answer":"Correct the conditions that created the weed problem or over-seed pasture when necessary (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4812","question":"What is the general term for all of the leather equipment used to ride and/or drive a horse?","answer":"Tack"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4813","question":"What is the proper name for a storage room where bridles, saddles, and other equipment used in horseback riding are kept?","answer":"Tack room"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4814","question":"Name 3 items you'd see at a tack shop.","answer":"Saddle, bridle, halter, lead rope, brushes, saddle pad, blanket, medicines, hoofpick, apparel (accept any reasonable answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4815","question":"What does it mean to \"tack up\"?","answer":"Put tack on your horse (bridle, saddle, harness, etc.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4816","question":"Why should you sponge your tack after use?","answer":"To remove dirt or sweat"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4817","question":"What should you do if you find a strap that's thin from wear or torn?","answer":"Replace it ASAP."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4818","question":"For what purpose is glycerin soap used?","answer":"To clean tack"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4819","question":"What practice can add to the use and life of any leather article?","answer":"Regular cleaning, conditioning, or oiling (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4820","question":"What is Neatsfoot oil?","answer":"Oil used for conditioning, softening, or preserving leather (accept any)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4821","question":"Name TWO things you should do to take care of your leather tack.","answer":"Protect it from moisture; keep it clean; keep it oiled or conditioned; sponge it after use; don't place it near heat (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4822","question":"What is the main problem with stiff or dried out leather tack?","answer":"It can break.  (It's brittle and will crack easily.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4823","question":"What ONE thing should NEVER be done to leather, no matter how wet it gets?","answer":"Never place it near heat."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4824","question":"Under what conditions should leather and rope halters be stored?","answer":"In a dry place"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4825","question":"Name ONE area where leather tack is most likely to break.","answer":"Around buckles, bends, or attachments"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4826","question":"Name TWO products commonly used to keep leather soft and pliable.","answer":"Leather oil (Neatsfoot oil), saddle soap (Leather New), leather conditioner (Lexol) (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4827","question":"Name 3 things you should inspect leather for, especially when buying used tack.","answer":"Cracked; stiff; dried out; thin or worm; broken stitching; stretched out or enlarged holes (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4828","question":"How does leather conditioner work?","answer":"Puts vital oils back into the leather."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4829","question":"Give ONE reason why a stable is a poor place to store leather.","answer":"Temperature, dampness, rodents, ammonia from urine or manure"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4830","question":"What is another name for an English double bridle?","answer":"Weymouth (WAY-muth) or full bridle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4831","question":"What kind of bridle uses TWO bits?","answer":"Weymouth (WAY-muth), double bridle, or full bridle (accept any)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4832","question":"On an English double bridle, what does the lip strap do?","answer":"Positions the curb chain"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4833","question":"What do you call the noseband on an English bridle?","answer":"Cavesson"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4834","question":"What is the function of a cavesson?","answer":"To keep the horse's mouth closed"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4835","question":"Give TWO meanings of the term cavesson.","answer":"Noseband on an English bridle; headstall used for longe line training"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4836","question":"What noseband is a cross between a cavesson and a figure 8 noseband?","answer":"Flash noseband"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4837","question":"Name 3 types of nosebands or cavesson.","answer":"Plain, longeing, dropped, flash, figure 8, crank (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4838","question":"2 part question:  On a Pelham bridle, which rein functions as the snaffle rein and which rein functions as the curb rein?","answer":"Upper rein is the snaffle; lower rein is the curb rein"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4839","question":"What are the 3 main parts of the bridle?","answer":"Reins, bit, and headstall"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4840","question":"What is the browband on a bridle?","answer":"Part of the bridle that goes across the forehead (above the eyes)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4841","question":"What do you call the strap that goes around the horse's forehead?","answer":"Browband"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4842","question":"What is the purpose of a browband?","answer":"To keep the bridle from sliding down the horse's neck"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4843","question":"What part of the bridle keeps the crownpiece from sliding down the horse's neck?","answer":"Browband"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4844","question":"What is the name of the specific part of the headstall that holds the bit up in the horse's mouth?","answer":"Cheek piece"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4845","question":"In reference to bridles, what are cheek pieces?","answer":"Side pieces of the bridle or sidepieces of the bit (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4846","question":"When bridling your horse, which ear is LAST to be pulled under the crownpiece?","answer":"Left ear"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4847","question":"What part of the bridle lies at the top of the horse's head behind its ears?","answer":"Crownpiece"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4848","question":"Name the TWO pieces of the bridle that apply pressure to the poll and under the chin when using a curb bit.","answer":"Crown piece applies pressure to the poll; curb strap or curb chain apply pressure under the chin."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4849","question":"To what part of the English bridle's headstall does the throatlatch attach?","answer":"Crownpiece"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4850","question":"What is the main function of a headstall?","answer":"To hold the bit in place"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4851","question":"What do you call the leather bridle straps without the bit and reins?","answer":"Headstall"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4852","question":"Name the part of the bridle that's found on an English bridle, but NOT on most Western ones.","answer":"Noseband or cavesson (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4853","question":"What part of the bridle keeps the horse from rubbing the bridle off?","answer":"Throatlatch"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4854","question":"What basic part of the bridle serves as a secondary means of communication as well as allowing you to manipulate the bit?","answer":"Reins"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4855","question":"Give ONE name for the type of reins that are connected to each other with a romal.","answer":"California reins or closed reins"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4856","question":"Name ONE advantage of web, laced, or rubber reins.","answer":"More secure grip; not slippery when wet"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4857","question":"Name 3 types of English reins.","answer":"Laced, plain, web, rubber"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4858","question":"Name TWO equestrian events where rubber reins would be used.","answer":"Racing, steeplechase, eventing, cross country, jumping"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4859","question":"What type of reins are covered with a pebbled surface on the handgrip portions and are used in racing to provide a secure grip?","answer":"Rubber reins"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4860","question":"When riding with romal reins in Stock Seat Equitation, how much distance should there be between the hand holding the reins and the hand holding the romal?","answer":"At least 16 inches"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4861","question":"To what type of reins is a romal attached?","answer":"California or closed reins (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4862","question":"What is the name for the flexible quirt that's attached to California-style reins?","answer":"Romal"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4863","question":"Describe roping reins.","answer":"Reins that are one continuous strap (used by ropers and gymkhana riders so the rider doesn't drop or lose the reins)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4864","question":"Why are roping reins one continuous strap?","answer":"To prevent dropping or losing the reins"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4865","question":"In addition to ropers, what other type of rider would use roping reins?","answer":"Gymkhana (games) riders or barrel racers (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4866","question":"What do you call the type of Western reins that's one continuous strap?  This type helps prevent dropping or losing a rein.","answer":"Roping reins"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4867","question":"What are the most commonly used type of Western reins?","answer":"Split reins"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4868","question":"What is an emergency bridle made of rope called?","answer":"War bridle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4869","question":"What is a war bridle?","answer":"Emergency bridle made of rope (also a \"come along\" which is made of stiff rope and is used for leading unruly horses)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4870","question":"What type of bridle is often made of stiff lariat rope and is used in leading unruly horses by exerting pressure on the poll.  It is sometimes called a “come-along”.","answer":"War bridle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4871","question":"What is the difference between a SLIP ear and a SPLIT ear bridle?","answer":"SLIP ear bridle has a loop added to the crownpiece for the ear to pass through; SLIT ear bridle has a split in the crownpiece for the ear to pass through."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4872","question":"On a Western bridle, on what side of the horse does the throatlatch buckle?","answer":"Left side"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4873","question":"Describe a SLIP ear headstall.","answer":"Small loop is added to the crownpiece to go around the ear."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4874","question":"Describe the following Western headstalls:  split ear, slip ear, and conventional.","answer":"SPLIT ear—crownpiece is split allowing the ear to slip through; SLIP ear—small loop is added to the crownpiece for the ear to slip through; conventional—has a browband"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4875","question":"What is the most important part of the bridle?","answer":"Bit"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4876","question":"In cold weather, what should you do before placing the bit in the horse's mouth?","answer":"Warm the bit"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4877","question":"What do you call the device—normally made of metal or rubber—that attaches to the headstall and is used to regulate the position of the horse's head and to help control the pace and direction of the horse?","answer":"Bit"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4878","question":"When the bridle is correctly adjusted, the bit will rest on what part of the horse's mouth?","answer":"Bars or interdental space (space between the incisors and the premolars)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4879","question":"The corner of the horse's mouth should have how many wrinkles with a properly fitted bit?","answer":"1 or 2 wrinkles"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4880","question":"Name ONE thing that can result if a bit is too wide for a horse's mouth.","answer":"Lack of control, confusing rein signals, or can hurt the horse's mouth"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4881","question":"Name 3 different materials used to make bit mouthpieces.","answer":"Stainless steel, German silver, solid nickel, copper, aluminum, rubber, vulcanite, brass, leather, Happy Mouth, sweet iron (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4882","question":"Which mouthpiece material is very lightweight, brittle, and may cause the horse's mouth to be dry?","answer":"Aluminum"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4883","question":"Why is copper sometimes used in bit mouthpieces?","answer":"Increases salivation or makes the mouth more responsive to the bit (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4884","question":"Which material, when used in a bit mouthpiece, increases salivation?","answer":"Copper (also accept sweet iron)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4885","question":"German silver is NOT made from silver, but is made from a combination of three other metals.  Name ONE of these metals.","answer":"Copper, nickel, and stainless steel"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4886","question":"What is the name of the soft, apple-flavored, rubber mouthpiece that's very gentle and is hypo-allergenic?","answer":"Happy Mouth"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4887","question":"What is the most common material used in making bits?","answer":"Stainless steel"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4888","question":"What is the \"never rust\" material used in making bits?","answer":"Stainless steel (also accept solid nickel)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4889","question":"What is the term for a bit mouthpiece that has a hinge in the middle?","answer":"Broken or jointed mouthpiece (Do NOT accept curb or snaffle; both can have solid or broken mouthpieces.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4890","question":"In reference to bits, what does the term \"mullen mouth\" mean?","answer":"Bit mouthpiece that has a slight bow or curve"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4891","question":"What is the term for the type of solid bit mouthpiece that has a slight bow in the middle instead of a port?","answer":"Mullen mouth"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4892","question":"In general, how do bits operate?","answer":"By applying pressure to certain parts of the mouth or head"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4893","question":"Name 3 areas where a bit or bridle applies pressure.","answer":"Corners of mouth, bars, tongue, roof of mouth, curb groove, nose, poll"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4894","question":"How can you remove rust spots from a bit?","answer":"Use steel wool"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4895","question":"Name 3 factors that affect the severity of a bit.","answer":"Thickness of the mouthpiece; type of mouthpiece; texture of mouthpiece; amount of leverage (length of shanks); position of horse's head; pressure points; pinching of bit; shape of horse’s mouth; quality of rider’s hands (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4896","question":"Name the basic 3 classifications of bits.","answer":"Snaffle, curb, hackamore (bit-less bridle)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4897","question":"Name 3 bits.","answer":"Snaffle (O-ring or loose ring, D-ring, eggbutt, half cheek, full cheek), curb, hackamore, Kimberwicke, Pelham, Weymouth, Liverpool, spade, Tom Thumb, walking horse, bar, roper curved cheek, Baucher, Fulmer (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4898","question":"Explain the differences between a snaffle bit, a curb bit, and a hackamore.","answer":"Snaffle bit has no shanks (reins attach directly to rings on the mouthpiece); curb bit has shanks (that cause leverage); hackamore has no mouthpiece."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4899","question":"What influences the severity of a bosal?","answer":"Stiffness"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4900","question":"What is the name for a bit, used in conjunction with a halter, that has three small rings—two for the cheek pieces and one for a lead rein?  It's used to help control horses that rear.","answer":"Anti-rearing bit or Chifney (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4901","question":"How should a horse respond to a curb bit?","answer":"By flexing at the poll"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4902","question":"Referring to bits, what is a cricket?","answer":"Attachment on a bit's port that spins when the horse moves its tongue (a roller)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4903","question":"What is the name of the attachment on the port of a curb bit that will spin in the horse's mouth as it moves its tongue?","answer":"Cricket or roller (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4904","question":"What is a curb chain?","answer":"Chain strap that goes under a horse’s chin and is attached to a curb bit (FYI: It applies pressure to the underside of horse's jaw.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4905","question":"What is the name of the strap commonly seen on a Western bridle, but not seen on a simple English bridle?","answer":"Curb strap or curb chain (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4906","question":"2 part question:  What is the part of the bit mouthpiece that curves up over the tongue and what is its purpose?","answer":"Port; relieves pressure on the tongue or applies pressure to the roof of the mouth (accept either purpose)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4907","question":"In reference to bits, what is the port?","answer":"Raised curved \"bump\" in the bit mouthpiece (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4908","question":"Name TWO purposes of the port on a curb bit.","answer":"Relieves tongue pressure; applies pressure to the roof of the mouth"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4909","question":"What is created when shanks are added to a bit?","answer":"Leverage"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4910","question":"What is the portion of the bit from the mouthpiece down?","answer":"Shank"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4911","question":"What part of a bit enables it to be classified as a leverage bit?","answer":"Shanks"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4912","question":"In reference to a curb bit, what is the shank?","answer":"Part of the bit from the mouthpiece down"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4913","question":"In reference to tack, where would a “stabilizer” or “roper’s” bar be found?","answer":"On a curb bit (FYI: It is bar that connects the shanks near where the reins attach.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4914","question":"Name TWO other places where a leverage bit applies pressure besides the mouth.","answer":"Poll; under the chin (chin groove or curb groove)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4915","question":"2 part question: Which GENERAL type of curb bit produces the most discomfort for the horse and why?","answer":"Curb bit with a jointed mouthpiece because it affects all the pressure points and creates a nutcracker effect on the bars and tongue."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4916","question":"Leverage bits cause pressure to be applied to the poll and under the chin.  What specific pieces of the bridle cause the poll pressure and the under the chin pressure?","answer":"Poll—crownpiece; under the chin—curb strap, chin strap, curb chain, or polo chain (accept any)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4917","question":"What is a Liverpool bit?","answer":"Curb bit commonly used for driving (FYI: A Liverpool bit has several rein attachment slots.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4918","question":"Name ONE bit that is considered severe.","answer":"Spade, Tom Thumb, gag (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4919","question":"Brace, roller, and a high port are all parts of what bit?","answer":"Spade bit"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4920","question":"What kind of bit is a Tom Thumb?","answer":"Curb bit (with a jointed mouthpiece) (Do NOT accept snaffle bit even though it's often called a \"cowboy snaffle\".  It is a curb bit because it has shanks.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4921","question":"Identify this bit:  it's a curb bit with short, straight, swivel shanks, and a broken mouthpiece; it's sometimes called a “cowboy snaffle”.","answer":"Tom Thumb"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4922","question":"What TWO bits does the double bridle use?","answer":"Snaffle (bridoon) and curb (Weymouth) (WAY-muth)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4923","question":"A bridoon and a curb are typically used with what type of bridle?","answer":"Weymouth, full, or double bridle (WAY-muth) (accept any)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4924","question":"What is the name for the small ring snaffle that when combined with a curb bit makes up a Weymouth or double bridle?","answer":"Bridoon (bradoon)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4925","question":"What is a bridoon?","answer":"Snaffle bit used on a double bridle (also accept another name for a snaffle bit)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4926","question":"What is the name for the strap that holds the snaffle bit in a double bridle?","answer":"Bradoon carrier"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4927","question":"Which bit looks similar to a D-ring snaffle, but has slots for attaching the headstall and hooks for attaching a curb chain? It may also have snaffle and curb rein slots.","answer":"Kimberwicke"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4928","question":"Describe a Kimberwicke bit.","answer":"English bit that looks similar to a D-ring snaffle that has slots for attaching the headstall, hooks for attaching a curb chain, and may have separate slots for attaching snaffle and curb reins.  (Only one rein is used on a Kimberwicke bit.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4929","question":"What bit is capable of acting as two bits in ONE mouthpiece? With TWO sets of reins, you have both snaffle and curb action?","answer":"Pelham (Do NOT accept Kimberwicke which has one set of reins or double/full/Weymouth which has two different bits.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4930","question":"Describe a Pelham bit.","answer":"English bit with shanks and rings for snaffle reins and rings for curb reins.  (It may have a jointed or low port mouthpiece.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4931","question":"Name TWO types of hackamores.","answer":"Bosal, mechanical, sidepull, bitless bridle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4932","question":"What common piece of tack does the term \"jaquima\" refer to?  (HAH-kee-mah)","answer":"Bosal or hackamore"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4933","question":"What is the Spanish word for hackamore?","answer":"Jaquima (HAH-kee-mah)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4934","question":"Where does a properly adjusted hackamore rest on a horse?","answer":"4 inches from the top the of nostril (also accept on the back of the cheek bone)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4935","question":"What is the difference between a bosal hackamore and a mechanical hackamore?","answer":"Bosal has a braided rawhide or rope noseband with a knot-like arrangement under the horse's jaw; mechanical has metal shanks and a curb strap."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4936","question":"In reference to tack, what is a bosal?","answer":"Noseband of a hackamore (often made of braided rawhide)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4937","question":"What is the braided rawhide or rope noseband on a hackamore called?","answer":"Bosal"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4938","question":"What is a throatlatch made of cord that fastens the bottom of the bosal to the headstall?","answer":"Fiador"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4939","question":"What is the \"ball\" that joins the ends of the braided sections of a bosal?  The mecate attaches to this area of the bosal. (meh-CAHT-ay)","answer":"Heel knot or hackamore knot"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4940","question":"In reference to tack, what is a mecate?  (meh-CAHT-ay)","answer":"Combination of lead rope and reins on a hackamore"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4941","question":"What is the term for the combination of lead rope and reins on a hackamore?","answer":"Mecate (meh-CAHT-ay)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4942","question":"Name ONE area to which a hackamore applies pressure","answer":"Nose, chin, face, poll, jaw, cheeks"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4943","question":"Name 3 areas to which a hackamore applies pressure.","answer":"Nose, chin, face, poll, jaw, cheeks"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4944","question":"A rider's pull on the reins of a snaffle causes what kind of pressure?","answer":"Direct"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4945","question":"What is a non-leverage bit?","answer":"Bit without shanks (snaffle)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4946","question":"Why is a snaffle called a direct action bit?","answer":"Reins attach directly to rings on the mouthpiece which causes a direct pulling action."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4947","question":"What are the 3 pressure points affected by a snaffle bit?","answer":"Corners of mouth, bars, and tongue (NOT the roof of the mouth)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4948","question":"Which snaffle bit is more severe, an eggbutt with a mouthpiece as thick as your pinkie or a D-ring with a mouthpiece as thick as your thumb?","answer":"Eggbutt with the thinner mouthpiece"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4949","question":"What is the mildest type of snaffle bit?","answer":"Bar mouthpiece (FYI:  A bar mouthpiece is solid and can be seen in snaffle or curb bits.  A jointed mouthpiece may be seen in snaffle bits or in curb bits such as a Tom Thumb.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4950","question":"2 part question:  The width of a snaffle bit is very important.  Explain what can happen from a bit that's too narrow and a bit that's too wide.","answer":"If the bit’s too narrow it causes pinching; if the bit’s too wide it causes loss of control."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4951","question":"What is the most common bit used for Thoroughbred race horses?","answer":"Snaffle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4952","question":"When using the terms D-ring, round, or full cheek, you are referring to what?","answer":"Snaffle bits (specifically the rings of snaffle bits)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4953","question":"What is the main difference in the design of a D-ring and an egg butt snaffle?","answer":"Shape of the rings"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4954","question":"What is a snaffle key bit?","answer":"Snaffle bit with small metal pieces dangling from the center of the mouthpiece (FYI: It's used in training colts.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4955","question":"What is the main purpose of a saddle?","answer":"To distribute the rider's weight over the horse's back (also accept to give the rider a sense of security)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4956","question":"What is the FIRST step in selecting a saddle?  This should be considered even before measuring your horse for proper saddle fit.","answer":"Deciding which style of riding you prefer"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4957","question":"Give 3 criteria for selecting a saddle.","answer":"Should fit the horse; should fit the rider; should be appropriate for the desired style of riding; should not interfere with performance or ability of horse"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4958","question":"Name 3 types of saddles.","answer":"Western (pleasure, trail, cutting reining, barrel racing, roping), English (dressage, all purpose, forward seat, saddle seat or cut back), Australian,  racing, polo, endurance, pack (sawbuck or crossbuck, Decker) (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4959","question":"A felt saddle with a wood frame was created around 200 BC by whom?","answer":"Asian horsemen"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4960","question":"Identify this saddle:  has high thigh rolls located near the front of the saddle which keeps the rider firmly in place; usually has no horn; is popular with trail riders.","answer":"Australian, Outback, or Poley (accept any)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4961","question":"A pad with a cinch—which may include stirrups—used for exercising the horse is called what?","answer":"Bareback pad, pad saddle, or exercise saddle (accept any)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4962","question":"What is a cinch?","answer":"Girth used on a Western saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4963","question":"What is the term for a wide cord girth used on a Western saddle?","answer":"Cinch"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4964","question":"What is the purpose of a back cinch on a roping saddle?","answer":"To keep the saddle from flipping up when roping or dallying"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4965","question":"Where on the horse should the girth of an English saddle lie?","answer":"Heart girth area (belly area directly behind the front legs)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4966","question":"What English girth style reduces chaffing of your horse's elbows?","answer":"Elastic-end contour leather (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4967","question":"Referring to English tack, what fitting is being described by the terms string, elastic–end contour, threefold, and balding?","answer":"Girths (English girths)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4968","question":"Give TWO definitions of the term \"girth\".","answer":"Circumference of the horse's body back of the withers; piece of equipment that goes around the horse’s body to hold the saddle on"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4969","question":"What is the name of the four-in-hand knot that's tied the same as a knot on a man's tie and is used to secure a saddle in place when a buckle isn't used?","answer":"Cinch knot"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4970","question":"In reference to saddles, what does the term \"rigging\" mean?","answer":"Location of where the cinch is attached to the saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4971","question":"Name 3 types of rigging and give ONE use for each.","answer":"Full double—roping, packing (sawbuck or crossbuck); 7/8 or 3/4 double—reining, cutting, pleasure; in skirt—pleasure, trail; centerfire—packing (Decker), bucking saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4972","question":"What is a Western saddle called that has the cinch hung from the center?","answer":"Centerfire"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4973","question":"In reference to saddles, what is \"centerfire\"?","answer":"Saddle with the cinch hung from the center"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"4974","question":"Which of the following types of Western saddle riggings would accommodate only one cinch:  centerfire, full, or 3/4?","answer":"Centerfire"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4975","question":"What is a double-rigged saddle?","answer":"Saddle with two cinches"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4976","question":"The McClellan saddle is single rigged.  What does this mean?","answer":"Only has one cinch or girth (FYI:  Double rigged means the saddle has two cinches.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4977","question":"Name ONE type of saddle that uses a double-rigged cinch.","answer":"Roping saddle, sawbuck saddle, crossbuck saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"novice","number":"4978","question":"Name ONE thing a poor fitting saddle can cause.","answer":"Saddle rolling during mounting or dismounting; saddle slipping or sliding during use; horse objecting to being cinched; horse bucking; horse tossing head"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4979","question":"By placing two fingers between your horse's withers and the fork of the saddle, you are checking for what?","answer":"Proper fit"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4980","question":"Where on the horse do most saddle fitting problems occur?","answer":"Withers"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4981","question":"How can a saddle pinch your horse?","answer":"By riding too high on the sides of the withers (by not fitting properly)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"4982","question":"Name 3 things that could happen when a poorly fitted saddle is used on a horse.","answer":"Saddle rolling during mounting or dismounting; saddle slipping or sliding during use; horse objecting to being cinched; horse bucking; horse tossing head (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4983","question":"Where do you measure the width of the withers?","answer":"2 (two) inches below the top of withers"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4984","question":"What measurement is necessary to have a properly fitted girth?","answer":"Heartgirth (from girth buckle to girth buckle)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4985","question":"Besides fitting a horse at the withers, name 3 conformation factors that contribute to saddle fit.","answer":"Length of back, slope of shoulder, muscling, spring of rib cage"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4986","question":"Name 3 factors that might contribute to a saddle resting on the horse's withers instead of clearing them.","answer":"Fork of saddle too wide; saddle tree too wide; withers too high; withers too narrow; combination of these"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4987","question":"In reference to saddles what is the difference between an Arabian tree and a Quarter Horse tree?","answer":"Arabian tree is wider."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4988","question":"What part of the Western saddle should you consider FIRST when fitting your horse?","answer":"Tree"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4989","question":"What kind of saddle would you select for a Western horse with low, thick withers?","answer":"Western saddle with a wide tree (Quarter Horse or Arabian tree)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4990","question":"What kind of saddle would you select for a thick-withered English horse?","answer":"English saddle with a wide tree"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4991","question":"Where do you measure the width of a saddle tree?","answer":"Across the bottom of the gullet"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"4992","question":"Name 3 functions of a saddle pad.","answer":"Protect horse's back; absorb sweat; protect saddle; help saddle fit better; absorb shock"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"4993","question":"What is the biggest problem with foam saddle pads?","answer":"They don't breathe (or allow sweat to evaporate)."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"4994","question":"A saddle pad cut to fit the shape of the saddle sometimes has a large colorful roll around the edges.  This roll is called what?","answer":"Corona"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4995","question":"Name 3 different materials that English saddle pads are made of.","answer":"Natural products such as wool, cotton, felt, hair, fleece or sheepskin; synthetic products such as gel, foam, imitation fleece or sheepskin"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"4996","question":"Name 3 materials used to make Western saddle pads.","answer":"Natural products such as wool, felt, cotton, sheepskin; synthetic products such as foam, gel, nylon, rayon, rubber, plastic (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4997","question":"What is the name for a colorful woven blanket made of wool that's used with a Western saddle?","answer":"Navajo blanket"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4998","question":"A TRUE Navajo blanket is made from what material?","answer":"Wool"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"4999","question":"What type saddle would you use with a Navajo blanket?","answer":"Western or stock saddle (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"5000","question":"Name 3 parts of an English saddle that are NOT found on a Western saddle.","answer":"Stirrup irons, stirrup bars, flap, sweat flap (FYI: Billets and D-rings are also on Western saddles, but they are in different locations.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"5001","question":"Name the 3 parts of an English saddle and a Western saddle that are the same.","answer":"Pommel, cantle, seat (also accept skirt) (FYI: Both types also have D-rings and billets, but they are not in the same places.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5002","question":"What is the term for the raised back of the saddle, behind the seat?","answer":"Cantle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5003","question":"Where is the cantle of the saddle located?","answer":"Back of the saddle (just behind the seat)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5004","question":"How many billets are usually found on an English saddle?","answer":"3 (three) billets (on each side of the saddle)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5005","question":"On an English saddle, the billets attach what to the saddle?","answer":"Girth"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5006","question":"In reference to tack, what are billets?","answer":"Straps used to tighten the girth on an English saddle (also accept straps used to attach the front and back cinches on a Western saddle)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5007","question":"In reference to tack, what are \"fittings\"?","answer":"Stirrup leathers, stirrup irons, and girth for English saddles"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5008","question":"Referring to an English saddle, what is the collective term for stirrup leathers, stirrup irons, and girth?","answer":"Fittings"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5009","question":"What is the term for the wide piece of leather on an English saddle that's similar to the fender on a Western saddle?","answer":"Flap"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"5010","question":"Name 3 types of English girths.","answer":"String; elastic-end contour leather; 3 fold leather; Balding leather; web; neoprene; fleece; wool back; memory foam; gel"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5011","question":"In reference to an English saddle, what is the name for the channel that runs down the center of the underside of the saddle between the panels?","answer":"Gullet"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5012","question":"What part of an English saddle rests on the horse's back?","answer":"Panel"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5013","question":"Where is the pommel on an English saddle?","answer":"Slightly raised part of the saddle in front of the seat (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5014","question":"Why is it a good idea to switch stirrup leathers on an English saddle from side to side on a regular basis?","answer":"Mounting causes the leather to stretch making the stirrup leathers uneven."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5015","question":"You do the math…There should be ¼ inch of room on each side of the hunt seat rider’s foot when it’s in the stirrup.  The total width of the stirrup tread should be how much wider than the width of the boot?","answer":"½ inch"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5016","question":"How much room should there be on each side of the widest part of a rider's foot in an English stirrup?","answer":"¼ inch"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"5017","question":"In reference to saddles, what is a sweat flap?","answer":"Small flap on an English saddle that's under the flap or between the billets and the horse (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5018","question":"Where would you find the twist on an English saddle?","answer":"Between the pommel and the seat"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5019","question":"What do you call the front part of the saddle that's just below the horn?","answer":"Pommel (also accept swells or fork)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5020","question":"What is a saddle nail?","answer":"Rivet  or \"nail\" on the front side of the skirt near the pommel on English saddle (FYI: It's used to measure the size of an English saddle.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5021","question":"The rider sits in the deepest part of the saddle between which TWO parts?","answer":"Pommel and cantle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5022","question":"What does a safety stirrup do?","answer":"Let's the rider's foot come free from the stirrup in case of a fall (A heavy rubber band releases the foot.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5023","question":"Why is a breakaway stirrup important to a beginner rider?","answer":"Foot will be quickly released if the rider falls."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5024","question":"Referring to saddles, what is a tree?","answer":"Frame of the saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5025","question":"Fender, D-ring, skirt, and front jockey are all parts of what?","answer":"Western or stock saddle (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5026","question":"On the Western saddle, what is the term for the outside back of the cantle?","answer":"Cantle drop or Cheyenne roll (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5027","question":"2 part question:  On the Western saddle, what is a D-ring and where is it located?","answer":"Ring that holds the cinch straps; located under or in front of the fender"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5028","question":"Referring to saddles, what are fenders?","answer":"Wide pieces of leather along the stirrup leathers (on a Western saddle)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"5029","question":"Give ONE definition of the fork of a saddle.","answer":"Front part of the saddle that fits over the withers; front raised part of a Western saddle that supports the saddle horn; front of the saddle tree;  part of the swells of a Western saddle that makes up the gullet"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5030","question":"In reference to saddles, what does the term \"slick\" mean?","answer":"Shape of the fork on a Western saddle (forks or swells that are narrow at the top and are wide at the bottom)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5031","question":"Where on a Western saddle would you find the hobble strap?","answer":"At the bottom of the fender above the stirrup (FYI: Hobble straps help prevent the stirrups from falling off.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5032","question":"What was the original purpose of the horn on a Western saddle?","answer":"To hold roped calves or cows (dally)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5033","question":"Referring to tack, what is being described by the following terms:  pelican, gourd, Appleton, dinner plate, and dally?","answer":"Types of saddle horns"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5034","question":"Referring to a saddle, what is a jockey?","answer":"Small flaps on the side of the saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5035","question":"What are the small flaps on the side of the saddle called?","answer":"Jockey or jockey skirt (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5036","question":"2 part question:  Where would you find a latigo and what is its purpose?","answer":"On a Western saddle; it's the strap that's used to tie the cinch knot"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5037","question":"Which part of the Western saddle is used for tying equipment to the saddle?","answer":"Lace strings or saddle strings (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5038","question":"What is the basic foundation of all stock saddles?","answer":"Tree"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5039","question":"What part of the saddle must be fitted to the rider?","answer":"Seat (also accept stirrups)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5040","question":"What does a youth-sized English saddle seat measure?","answer":"12 - 16 inches (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5041","question":"What does an adult-size English saddle seat measure?","answer":"16 - 18 inches (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5042","question":"2 part question:  You are looking to purchase an English saddle for your 6 foot tall father who wants to trail ride.  There is a 14 inch all-purpose saddle advertised in the local paper.  Will this saddle be adequate for your father?  Explain your answer.","answer":"No.  The all-purpose type will work, but the saddle is too small.  An adult that size would need a 16 – 18 inch saddle."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5043","question":"From what TWO points do you measure to determine the size of an English saddle?","answer":"From the saddle nail to the mid-point of the cantle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5044","question":"How is the size of a stock saddle measured?","answer":"From the base of the horn to the top of the cantle (FYI: Youth to small adults use 12 – 14 inch saddles; average to extra-large adults use 15 – 17 inch saddles.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5045","question":"What material are most English saddles made of?","answer":"Leather"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5046","question":"Which type saddle does NOT necessarily require a saddle pad?","answer":"English"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5047","question":"Name TWO kinds of saddles that roughly fit under the heading of English saddles.","answer":"Racing and polo"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5048","question":"Give ONE other name for a hunt seat saddle.","answer":"Forward seat saddle (FYI:  All purpose, close contact or jumping, and dressage are types of hunt seat or forward seat saddles.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5049","question":"Why is a forward seat saddle versatile?","answer":"Allows the rider to be in balance with the horse whether riding on the flat, jumping, or doing a combination of flat riding and jumping"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5050","question":"Close contact and all-purpose are both examples of what type of English saddle?","answer":"Forward seat or hunt seat (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"5051","question":"Name the 3 saddle types in the hunt seat or forward seat category.","answer":"All purpose, close contact, and dressage"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5052","question":"Which of the hunt seat saddle types is the most popular for trail riding?","answer":"All purpose (FYI:  All purpose, close contact or jumping, and dressage are types of hunt seat or forward seat saddles.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5053","question":"What type of English saddle is specially designed with a flat seat, forward short flaps, and NO extra knee roll?","answer":"Close contact saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5054","question":"What is the main purpose of the close contact saddle?","answer":"Jumping"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5055","question":"Which English saddle is designed to give the rider optimum leg contact with the horse?","answer":"Dressage saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5056","question":"Give ONE other name for a saddle seat saddle.","answer":"Cutback, Park, or Lane Fox"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5057","question":"In English riding, what saddle is used to ride \"on the flat\" just behind the center of your horse?","answer":"Saddle seat (also accept park, cutback, or Lane Fox)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5058","question":"The saddle seat saddle is cut back in the pommel to accommodate certain conformational aspects of the breeds used in saddle seat classes.  Name ONE of these conformational aspects.","answer":"High withers, high head carriage, or high neck carriage"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"sr bonus","number":"5059","question":"Give 3 names for the type of saddle used for saddle seat riding.","answer":"Saddle seat, cut back, Park, Lane Fox"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5060","question":"What is the primary goal of the pleasure saddle?","answer":"Comfort"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5061","question":"What is a planchette?","answer":"Wooden step which supported the feet on the early sidesaddles"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5062","question":"Give TWO advantages of a synthetic saddle.","answer":"Less expensive; lightweight; easy to take care of"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5063","question":"Where are most Western saddles made?","answer":"United States"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5064","question":"Which type of saddle was originally developed for ranch work?","answer":"Western or stock saddle (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"jr bonus","number":"5065","question":"Name 3 types of Western saddles.","answer":"Pleasure, trail, endurance, reining, roping, cutting, barrel racing, equitation, gymkhana (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5066","question":"Identify this saddle:  lightweight; gives the rider a straight leg position and a deep seat for security and balance; tall horn gives the rider something to grab onto during turns; skirts are often rounded.","answer":"Barrel racing saddle"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5067","question":"What type saddle should be used for roping?","answer":"Roping saddle (with sturdy horn and front and back cinches)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5068","question":"What equipment should always be treated as a means to an end, used only when needed, and used only as long as needed?","answer":"Training aids such as martingales and draw reins"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"5069","question":"What do you call a combination of bridle, harness pad, and crupper?","answer":"Bitting rig"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5070","question":"What is the purpose a \"bitting rig\"?","answer":"To teach a horse to flex at the poll (FYI: A bitting rig is a combination of bridle, harness pad, and crupper.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5071","question":"Give ONE purpose of a whip, crop, or bat.","answer":"Cues, punishment, appointments, make horse go faster (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5072","question":"In reference to tack and equipment, what is a \"bat\"?","answer":"Short, flat riding whip"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5073","question":"What type of reins are fastened to the girth and then passed through the rings of the snaffle bit into the rider's hands?","answer":"Draw reins"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5074","question":"What is a strap that runs from the girth, between the front legs, to the bridle called?","answer":"Martingale or tiedown (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5075","question":"Name the TWO most common types of martingales.","answer":"Running and standing"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5076","question":"What is the basic purpose of a martingale?","answer":"To keep a horse's head in a desired position"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5077","question":"Name ONE type of martingale that attaches to the reins.","answer":"Running, Irish, or German"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5078","question":"Explain the difference between a standing martingale and a running martingale.","answer":"Standing martingale attaches to the back of the noseband; running martingale has a Y-shaped strap with rings on the ends that the reins pass through."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5079","question":"Which martingale combines the action of both the snaffle rein and a draw rein?","answer":"German martingale"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5080","question":"Which type of martingale has rings through which the reins pass?","answer":"Running"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5081","question":"What piece of equipment needs to be used with a running martingale to prevent the martingale from interfering with the bit?","answer":"Rein stops"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5082","question":"The upper end of a standing martingale connects to what part of the bridle?","answer":"Cavesson or noseband (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5083","question":"What is the Western version of a standing martingale?","answer":"Tiedown"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5084","question":"What is the English term for a tie-down?","answer":"Standing martingale"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5085","question":"Name TWO types of bars found on tack.","answer":"Stirrup bar, bars of saddle tree, bar mouthpiece (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5086","question":"What is the name for the rubber or leather ring that lies between the horse's cheek and the bit that prevents rubbing or pinching of the skin?","answer":"Bit guard"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5087","question":"Referring to outerwear for your horse, what is the purpose of a horse blanket?","answer":"To keep the horse warm in cold weather (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"int bonus","number":"5088","question":"Name 3 different types of outerwear for your horse.","answer":"Turnout blanket, turnout sheet, cooler, mesh sheet, stable blanket, stable sheet, blanket, sheet, sleazie, hood (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5089","question":"What type of blanket assists your horse in drying off after a workout?","answer":"Cooler or mesh sheet (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5090","question":"What is the term for the type of sheet that's used during outdoor exercise in cold weather?  It runs from the withers to the hindquarters.","answer":"Half sheet"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5091","question":"What is the use of a half sheet?","answer":"Used for warmth when exercising horses outdoors in cold weather (FYI: Half sheets and quarter sheets are often used with English saddles and they cover the back half of the horse.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5092","question":"What type of sheet would be used to keep flies away from your horse?","answer":"Mesh (also accept fly sheet)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5093","question":"Give TWO uses of a mesh sheet.","answer":"Aids in cooling out horse; keeps flies away"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5094","question":"What is the purpose of an anti-sweat sheet?","answer":"Wick moisture away from horse's body after a heavy workout"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5095","question":"The lighter weight blanket is specifically used for what TWO purposes?","answer":"Shipping; turnout"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5096","question":"In the winter, what type of blanket should be used to keep your horse's hair coat from growing too long?","answer":"Heavy one"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5097","question":"What part of the horse do bell boots protect?","answer":"Back of the front pasterns, coronets, or heels (accept any)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5098","question":"What is another name for bell boots?","answer":"Overreach boots"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5099","question":"What is the name of the protective boots that fit over the coronet band and the bulbs of the heel?","answer":"Bell boots or overreach boots (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5100","question":"What type boots protect the back of the rear fetlocks from abrasions during sliding movements?","answer":"Skid boots or sliding boots (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5101","question":"What is the purpose of splint boots?","answer":"To support or protect the splint and/or cannon bones"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5102","question":"Which piece of tack is used to keep the saddle from slipping FORWARD when going downhill?","answer":"Breeching or crupper (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5103","question":"Give ONE purpose of chaps.","answer":"To protect the legs from cuts or cold; used for show"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5104","question":"What are chaps?","answer":"Seatless overalls or leggings (usually made of leather; used to protect the legs, keep the legs warm, or for show)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5105","question":"Explain the difference between batwing chaps and shotgun chaps.","answer":"Batwing chaps are flared; shotgun chaps fit close to leg."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5106","question":"What is the type of Western chaps that extends slightly beyond the knees, but does not cover the rider’s shins?","answer":"Chinks (Do NOT accept half chaps which are English chaps that cover the ankle and shin.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5107","question":"How tight should the halter chinstrap be?","answer":"You should be able to put a couple of fingers between the halter and the muzzle; loose enough to prevent binding the face and tight enough to prevent a foot from being caught (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5108","question":"A strap fastening the front legs of a horse together so that he can't stray is called what?","answer":"Hobbles"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5109","question":"In reference to tack, what are hobbles?","answer":"Straps fastened to the front legs of a horse to prevent him from straying"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5110","question":"What is a rope, often made of rawhide, with a running noose that's used for catching cattle?","answer":"Lariat or lasso (accept either)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5111","question":"What is the name for the eye formed on the end of the lariat through which the rope is passed to form a loop?","answer":"Honda"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5112","question":"What type of knot is used on the end of a rope to keep it from unraveling?","answer":"Crown knot"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5113","question":"What is a reata?","answer":"Spanish word for lasso, lariat, or rope (accept any)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5114","question":"What is Spanish for lasso?","answer":"Reata"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5115","question":"A strap or rope 25 - 30 feet long that's used to circle or work a horse is called what?","answer":"Longe line"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5116","question":"How long should a longe line be?","answer":"25 - 30 feet (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5117","question":"What piece of equipment, other than the longe line and halter, might you need when teaching a foal to lunge?","answer":"Whip"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5118","question":"What are the toothed wheels on spurs called?","answer":"Rowels"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5119","question":"What are rowels?","answer":"Toothed wheels on spurs"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"5120","question":"What is a surcingle?  (SIR-sing-el)","answer":"Broad strap around the horse's girth (that may be used along with a bridle for ground training)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"5121","question":"What is the term for a girth-like band passed over the horse's back and around the belly?  It's used with a bridle in ground training horses.","answer":"Surcingle (SIR-sing-el)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"5122","question":"What is the name for the cover on a stirrup?","answer":"Tapadera"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"intermediate","number":"5123","question":"What is a tapadera?","answer":"Stirrup cover"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"easy","number":"5124","question":"What is the name for the restraining device that's put around a horse's upper lip to make him stand still?","answer":"Twitch"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5125","question":"What is the term for the person who makes the metal parts of tack such as bits, curb chains, and stirrup irons?","answer":"Lorimer"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5126","question":"Name TWO types of bits used when driving horses.","answer":"Half-cheek snaffle, Liverpool bit, bar bit, plain snaffle (O ring, D ring, egg-butt, etc.)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5127","question":"In reference to tack, what are blinders or blinkers?","answer":"Solid pieces attached to the headstall alongside each eye so the horse can't see to the side without turning its head (keeps the horse looking forward)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5128","question":"What part of the harness helps the horse hold back the vehicle when there is no brake?","answer":"Breeching  (also accept pole strap, thimbles, shaft cups)"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5129","question":"In general, what is the main design difference between a cart and a carriage?","answer":"Cart has 2 wheels; carriage has 4 wheels."},
{"category":"Tack","level":"hard","number":"5130","question":"What are the steel or wooden arms that are fitted to the collar of a harness?","answer":"Hames"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5131","question":"Terrets are rings on the harness of driving horses.  What passes through these rings?","answer":"Reins or lines"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5132","question":"What does the term \"open bridle\" describe?","answer":"Bridle without blinders or blinkers"},
{"category":"Tack","level":"medium","number":"5133","question":"In driving, what are the parts of the harness that run from the collar to the singletree?","answer":"Traces"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5134","question":"Give ONE other name for a temporary or non-permanent tooth.","answer":"Milk tooth, baby tooth, or deciduous tooth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"jr bonus","number":"5135","question":"Give 3 other names for a foal's baby teeth.","answer":"Temporary teeth, milk teeth, deciduous teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"jr bonus","number":"5136","question":"What are the 3 parts of a temporary tooth?","answer":"Crown, neck, and root (fang)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5137","question":"What is the proper name for the foal's baby teeth?","answer":"Deciduous or temporary teeth (accept either)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5138","question":"What do you call the gum space between the incisors and premolars?","answer":"Interdental space or bars (accept either)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5139","question":"Where is the interdental space?","answer":"Gum space between the incisors and cheek teeth (premolars and molars)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5140","question":"What do the letters ICPM stand for in the dental formula?","answer":"Incisors, canines, premolars, molars"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5141","question":"Name TWO types of teeth in the male horse that only occur as permanent teeth and that never occur as deciduous teeth.","answer":"Molars, canines, wolf teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5142","question":"Give ONE other name for a tush.","answer":"Canine tooth, fang, tusk, bridle tooth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5143","question":"What teeth does a male horse have that a mare seldom has?","answer":"Canine teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5144","question":"Canine teeth are usually NOT present in which sex of the horse?","answer":"Mare (female)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5145","question":"Where in the mouth are the canine teeth located?","answer":"Bars or interdental space (space between the incisors and the premolars/molars)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5146","question":"Teeth that appear in the interdental space on the male horse at 5 years of age, sometimes referred to as tushes, are called what?","answer":"Canine teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5147","question":"Which teeth in older male horses are often tall and/or sharp?","answer":"Canine teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5148","question":"What are canine teeth?","answer":"Teeth that appear in the interdental space on the male horse at 5 years of age (FYI: Some mares may have small canines.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5149","question":"Which teeth can be examined for wear and slant to best estimate the age of a horse?","answer":"Incisors"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5150","question":"What are horses’ front, cutting teeth called?","answer":"Incisors"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5151","question":"How many INCISORS does a yearling have?","answer":"12 (twelve) (FYI: Deciduous incisors erupt by ages 8 days, 8 weeks, and 9 months.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"int bonus","number":"5152","question":"At what ages do the following permanent teeth erupt:  central, intermediate, and corner incisors?","answer":"Centrals—2½ years; intermediates—3½ years; corners—4½ years"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"jr bonus","number":"5153","question":"What are the names of the 3 sets of incisors?","answer":"Centrals, intermediates, and corners"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5154","question":"How many incisors do horses have in each of their upper and lower jaws?","answer":"6 (six) in each jaw"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5155","question":"What are the first centrally located incisors called?","answer":"Centrals"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5156","question":"What do you call the third set of incisors, those closest to the interdental space?","answer":"Corners"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5157","question":"What is the name of the second set of incisors?","answer":"Intermediates"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5158","question":"What is another name for the horse's rear grinding teeth?","answer":"Molars"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5159","question":"In reference to teeth, what are molars?","answer":"Rear grinding teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5160","question":"Which teeth are continuously erupting and wearing?","answer":"Cheek teeth (premolars and molars)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5161","question":"Name ONE type of teeth in horses that erupt only as permanent teeth.","answer":"Molars, canines, or wolf teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5162","question":"2 part question:  How many premolars and how many molars does an adult horse have?","answer":"12 premolars; 12 molars"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5163","question":"How many premolars does a foal of either sex have?","answer":"12 premolars"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5164","question":"The teeth just in front of the upper premolars are called what?","answer":"Wolf teeth (FYI: Wolf teeth are technically the first upper premolars and they're usually removed.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5165","question":"A bit that hits the horse's wolf teeth may cause the horse to do what?","answer":"Throw its head, buck, rear (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5166","question":"In the horse's upper jaw, how many wolf teeth MAY be present?","answer":"None, one, or two (accept any)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5167","question":"In the horse's lower jaw, how many wolf teeth are NORMALLY found?","answer":"None"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5168","question":"Give TWO reasons why wolf teeth are removed.","answer":"Can cause pain; can cause interference with the bit (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5169","question":"Name TWO things about a horse's teeth that can be used to estimate the age of the horse.","answer":"Shape, wear or disappearance of cups, slant or angle of incidence, occurrence of teeth or eruption pattern, Galvayne's groove"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"novice","number":"5170","question":"By looking at a horse’s mouth, how can you guess its age?","answer":"By looking at its teeth (appearance, cups, wear, eruption, slant or angle, and Galvayne’s groove)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5171","question":"Until what age can a horse be accurately identified by its teeth?","answer":"10 - 14 years of age (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"jr bonus","number":"5172","question":"Name 3 ways to estimate age of horses by its teeth.","answer":"Eruption pattern or occurrence of teeth; wear or disappearance of cups; slant or angle of incidence or bite; Galvayne's Groove; shape of the surface of the permanent teeth, dovetail notch, hooks"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5173","question":"If teeth are worn down, name ONE way you can estimate the age of the horse.","answer":"Eruption pattern; slant or angle of incidence; shape of tooth; Galvayne's Groove (Do NOT accept wear or disappearance of cups because the question states the teeth are worn down.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5174","question":"Name 3 factors that may affect the technique of aging a horse by its teeth and that may make the horse appear different than its actual age.","answer":"Prolonged drought, parrot mouth, cribbing, grazing on sandy soil, bishoping (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5175","question":"What is the angle of incidence?","answer":"Angle at which the upper and lower incisors meet (as viewed from the side)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5176","question":"What is the term for the profile view of the angle formed where the upper and lower incisors meet?","answer":"Angle of incidence or angle of bite (accept either)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5177","question":"The angle of incidence is approximately 160 – 180 degrees in young horses and becomes what angle in older ones?","answer":"90 degrees or less"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5178","question":"What is the angle of incidence in young horses?","answer":"160 - 180 degrees (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5179","question":"In general, you can estimate a horse's age from 6 - 11 years old by the order in which cups become smooth.  What is this order?","answer":"Lower centrals, lower intermediates, lower corners, upper centrals, upper intermediates, upper corners"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5180","question":"What are the hollow spaces on the wearing surfaces of the incisors called?","answer":"Cups"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5181","question":"What term refers to the amount of use seen on the biting surfaces of the incisors?","answer":"Wear"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5182","question":"At what age do the cups start disappearing?","answer":"6 (six) years of age"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5183","question":"Referring to teeth, what are cups?","answer":"Hollow spaces on the wearing surfaces of the incisors"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5184","question":"In reference to teeth, how can you use cups to estimate age?","answer":"Cups become smooth or wear down at different times (FYI: Upper ones are deeper than the lower ones so they don't wear evenly.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5185","question":"What do you call a horse whose biting surfaces of the upper and lower incisors are smooth?","answer":"Smooth mouthed (FYI: occurs at 10 - 12 years of age)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5186","question":"2 part question:  What is \"smooth mouth\" and when does it occur?","answer":"When the cups on the incisors have smoothed out; occurs at 10 - 12 years of age (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5187","question":"As the cups on the horse's incisors disappear, what starts to form first as a narrow, elongated yellow mark?","answer":"Dental star"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5188","question":"What marker on the grinding surface of the horse's tooth is revealed when the tooth is worn down to the pulp cavity?","answer":"Dental star"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5189","question":"Which teeth have a dental star?","answer":"Permanent incisors (FYI:  A dental star is the exposed pulp cavity on the wearing surface of a permanent incisor.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5190","question":"On what teeth are dental stars first evident?","answer":"Central incisors (specifically the lower centrals) (FYI:  Dental stars first appear at age 6 and are very visible by age 8.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5191","question":"Most horses have a well-developed dovetail notch by what age?","answer":"7 (seven) years of age (FYI: A dovetail notch forms when the surface of the lower corner incisor is not worn all the way to the back edges of the upper corner incisor as the angle of bite changes; this leaves a hook on the back of the upper corner.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5192","question":"2 part question:  In reference to teeth, what causes a dovetail notch and when does a dovetail notch usually appear?","answer":"Surface of lower corners is not worn all the way to the back edges of the upper ones as the angle of bite changes; this leaves a notch on the upper corners at 7 years of age (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5193","question":"How old would a horse be that has its permanent 1st and 2nd premolars?","answer":"2 ½ years of age"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5194","question":"Name 3 of the 4 periods of tooth eruption and development.","answer":"Birth to 2 ½ years; 2 ½ to 5 years; 5 - 9 years; aged"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5195","question":"Organize the following 4 types of permanent teeth by their age of eruption:  canines, 1st premolars, 2nd premolars, intermediate incisors.","answer":"1st premolars (wolf teeth) erupt at 5 - 6 months; 2nd molars erupt at 2 years; intermediate incisors erupt at 3 ½ years; canines erupt at 4-5 years"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5196","question":"At what age have ALL the milk teeth erupted?","answer":"6 - 9 months (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5197","question":"A young horse 8 months old would have 24 deciduous teeth.  What type of teeth does the young horse NOT have that it will develop later as permanent teeth?","answer":"Molars or canines (accept either)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5198","question":"What is the term for a horse that has all of its permanent teeth?","answer":"Full mouthed (FYI: occurs around 5 years of age)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5199","question":"What is meant by the term \"full mouth\"?","answer":"Horse has all of its permanent teeth. (FYI: occurs around age 5)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5200","question":"By what age does a horse generally have all its teeth and is considered full mouthed?","answer":"5 years of age"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5201","question":"Explain the difference between full mouth and smooth mouth.","answer":"Full mouth is when the horse has all of its teeth (occurs at 5); smooth mouth is when the cups have disappeared from the incisors (occurs at 10 - 12)."},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5202","question":"By what age have the temporary central incisors erupted?","answer":"8 days (erupt from birth to 8 days of age)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5203","question":"Which teeth are present at birth or erupt during the first week of life?","answer":"Deciduous or temporary central incisors"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5204","question":"At what age do the permanent centrals erupt?","answer":"2 ½ years of age"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5205","question":"When do the corner deciduous incisors erupt?","answer":"8 months (accept any number within 6 - 9 months)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5206","question":"At what age do permanent corners erupt?","answer":"4½ - 5 years (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5207","question":"In determining the age of a horse by its teeth, you would know the horse was 4½ to 5 years old if he had just gained which permanent teeth?","answer":"Corner incisors (also accept canines)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5208","question":"When do the intermediate deciduous incisors erupt?","answer":"8 weeks (accept any number within 4 - 8 weeks)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5209","question":"At what age do the permanent intermediates erupt?","answer":"3 ½ - 4 years (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5210","question":"By what age does the FIRST set of the horse's molars erupt?","answer":"By 1 (one) year (FYI:  First molars erupt from 9 – 12 months.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5211","question":"Molars are present in horses only as permanent teeth. By what ages do the first, second, and third sets of molars erupt?","answer":"First by 1 year; second by 2 years; third by 3½ - 4 years"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5212","question":"At what age does the LAST set of the horse's molars erupt?","answer":"3 ½ - 4 years (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5213","question":"At which ages are the following deciduous cheek teeth shed:  1st premolars, 2nd premolars, and 3rd premolars?","answer":"1st premolars after 2½ years; 2nd premolars before 3 years; 3rd premolars around 3 years 8 months"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5214","question":"The foal's temporary premolar teeth appear by what age?","answer":"2 (two) weeks"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5215","question":"At what age do wolf teeth erupt?","answer":"5 - 6 months of age (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5216","question":"By looking at a horse's teeth, how old is a horse whose Galvayne's Groove is halfway down the upper corner incisor?","answer":"15 years of age"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5217","question":"What is Galvayne's Groove?","answer":"Groove that appears at the gum edge of the upper corners at 10 years of age"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5218","question":"What would be the estimated age of a horse if Galvayne's groove extends to the wearing surface of the corner upper incisor?","answer":"20 years of age"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5219","question":"At what age does Galvayne's Groove appear on the upper corner incisors?","answer":"10 years of age"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5220","question":"Excluding wolf teeth, how many TEETH does a yearling have?","answer":"24 (FYI: 12 incisors and 12 premolars)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5221","question":"An adult male horse with NO wolf teeth will usually have how many total teeth?","answer":"40 (FYI: 12 incisors, 12 premolars, 12 molars, and 4 canines)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"int bonus","number":"5222","question":"We know that a mature male horse has 40 teeth total.  How many of each type of teeth does he have?","answer":"12 incisors, 12 premolars, 12 molars, and 4 canines"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5223","question":"Give TWO ways temporary teeth are distinguished from permanent teeth.","answer":"Temporary teeth are small, white, and have a distinct neck; permanent teeth are larger, stronger, more yellow, have no neck; younger horses will have distinct cups on their permanent incisors; older horse's incisors become more triangular"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5224","question":"At what age are a horse's teeth very slanted, triangular shaped, and have large dental stars?","answer":"20 - 21 years of age (accept either)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5225","question":"How does the shape of the chewing surfaces of the teeth change as the horse ages?","answer":"Changes from oval to triangular"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5226","question":"At the age of 20, what is the shape of a horse's permanent central incisor?","answer":"Triangular"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5227","question":"What is the best way to prevent dental problems in your horse?","answer":"Regular dental check-ups"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5228","question":"Large particles of food or un-chewed kernels of grain in the horse's manure may indicate a need for what?","answer":"Floating the teeth (also accept checking the horse's teeth or mouth)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5229","question":"Why would NOT taking care of a horse's mouth add to the expense of keeping a horse?","answer":"You may need to give the horse more food (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5230","question":"What practice can prevent an unopposed tooth from becoming too tall or too long?","answer":"Floating the teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5231","question":"Name ONE benefit of providing regular dental care for your horse.","answer":"Extends life; improves health; improves performance; helps maintain weight; decreases discomfort; decreases pain-related behavioral problems (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5232","question":"Name 3 benefits of shortening and blunting the canine teeth.","answer":"Easier insertion or removal of the bit, less chance of injury due to horse catching canine on object, less injury inflicted in fights, reduced risk of injury to people (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5233","question":"How do you ask a horse to open its mouth?","answer":"Put 1 - 2 fingers in the corner of its mouth (bars or interdental space) and apply pressure if needed."},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5234","question":"How do you examine a horse's MOLAR teeth?","answer":"Grasp the tongue with the right hand and the lower lip with the left hand."},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5235","question":"How do you examine a horse's INCISOR teeth?","answer":"Hold the halter near the chin with one hand and roll the lips back with the other hand."},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5236","question":"Referring to teeth, what is \"floating\"?","answer":"Filing off the sharp edges of the teeth (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5237","question":"How often is it recommended to float horses' teeth?","answer":"Once yearly (or as recommended by your vet)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5238","question":"Filing off the sharp edges of a horse's teeth is known as what?","answer":"Floating the teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5239","question":"What are the TWO movements of horses' jaws?","answer":"Vertical and lateral (up and down and sideways)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5240","question":"Which jaw of the horse is wider?","answer":"Upper jaw (maxilla)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5241","question":"2 part question:  Describe how the upper jaw teeth fit over the lower teeth and vice versa.","answer":"Upper teeth extend over the lower ones on the outside; lower teeth extend on the inside of the upper ones."},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5242","question":"In reference to teeth, what is \"bishoping\"?","answer":"Practice of trying to replace the cups on worn incisors to make the horse appear younger than its actual age (altering the teeth to conceal the horse's age)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5243","question":"The permanent upper and lower teeth are located in what 3 bones?","answer":"Maxilla, mandible, incisive bone"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5244","question":"What is the neck of the tooth?","answer":"Part between the crown and the root (located at the surface of the gum)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5245","question":"What is the crown of the tooth?","answer":"Top part of the tooth (that protrudes above the gum)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5246","question":"What is the part of the tooth between the crown and the root that's located at the surface of the gums?","answer":"Neck"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5247","question":"What is the top part of a tooth, the part that protrudes above the gum?","answer":"Crown"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5248","question":"What is the periodontium? (pair-ee-oh-DAHN-tee-um)","answer":"Tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5249","question":"What is periodontal disease?","answer":"Inflammation of the tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone (gum disease)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5250","question":"What is inflammation of the periodontium which is the tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone?","answer":"Periodontal disease (periodontitis)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5251","question":"Your horse eats with his head sideways or spills much of his grain from his mouth.  What should be checked?","answer":"His teeth (also accept his mouth)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5252","question":"Name ONE thing sharp edges on the teeth can cause the horse to do.","answer":"Chew food slowly, waste food, lose weight, rear, buck, toss head, quid (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5253","question":"If you looked in a horse's mouth and noticed that the top incisors were evenly worn off, what vice would you suspect this horse has?","answer":"Cribbing"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5254","question":"What is a root canal in a horse called?","answer":"Apicoectomy (ay-pee-coh-ECT-o-mee)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5255","question":"Two year old horses might develop sharp points within 4 - 6 weeks of having their teeth floated.  What might the reason for this be?","answer":"Their deciduous premolars are still present and are softer than permanent teeth."},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5256","question":"Why are problems resulting from teeth discomfort common in horses between 2 ½ to 4 ½ years of age?","answer":"Horse is losing and gaining lots of teeth. (All deciduous incisors and premolars are shed and replaced and the molars erupt during this time.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"int bonus","number":"5257","question":"Name 3 dental problems in horses.","answer":"Hooks, points, retained baby teeth (caps), wolf teeth, malaligned teeth, infected teeth, long or tall teeth, long or tall canines, lost tooth, broken tooth (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"int bonus","number":"5258","question":"Name 3 signs that would indicate your horse needs to have his teeth checked.","answer":"Weight loss, slobbering, head tilting, difficulty chewing, dropping feed, quidding, head tossing, bit chewing, tongue lolling, tail wringing, bucking, fussing with bit, refusing bit (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5259","question":"What percent of horses have some degree of overbite?","answer":"30 - 60% (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5260","question":"What can be caused by foreign bodies being wedged between the teeth or lodged in the tongue?","answer":"Excessive salivation or spillage of feed from mouth (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5261","question":"What causes a long or tall tooth to occur in the horse's mouth?","answer":"Missing tooth leaving an unopposed space that lets a tooth grow longer"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5262","question":"In reference to teeth, what are caps?","answer":"Temporary teeth that fail to fall out when replaced by the permanent teeth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5263","question":"Temporary teeth that stay attached to the gum after being pushed out by the erupting permanent teeth are called what?","answer":"Caps (FYI: Caps most commonly occur in the premolars.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5264","question":"Sharp edges on the teeth may cause damage to what part of the horse?","answer":"Tongue and/or cheek"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"easy","number":"5265","question":"Sharp protrusions that develop on the molars due to uneven wear are called what?","answer":"Hooks or points (accept either)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5266","question":"In the horse's mouth, the upper cheek teeth are often positioned slightly forward, toward the nose as compared to the lower ones.  What can this cause?","answer":"Hooks (also accept long or tall teeth because not all of the tooth is in wear)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5267","question":"What causes hooks on the horse's cheek teeth?","answer":"Change in position of the teeth causes the teeth to wear unevenly; the part of the tooth that is not in wear becomes longer or taller."},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5268","question":"On what side of a horse's tooth do points develop?","answer":"Cheek side (outside of upper cheek teeth and inside of lower cheek teeth)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5269","question":"Name ONE cause of an infected tooth in the horse.","answer":"Trapped food, decomposing food, jaw fracture, periodontal disease"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"sr bonus","number":"5270","question":"Give 3 signs that a horse has an infected tooth.","answer":"Slow eating, weight loss (progressive unthriftiness), quidding, tilting head, swelling of face or jaw, nasal drainage or drainage tracts (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5271","question":"In reference to eating, what is a horse doing when he is quidding?","answer":"Dropping partially chewed feed from his mouth"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5272","question":"What term is used when a horse drops partially chewed food from his mouth?","answer":"Quidding"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5273","question":"What part of the horse should be closely examined if the horse is quidding?","answer":"Teeth or mouth (accept either) (FYI: Quidding is when a horse drops partially chewed food from its mouth.)"},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"hard","number":"5274","question":"How does the position of the teeth affect tooth wear?","answer":"Position may cause the teeth to wear unevenly which may cause hooks and points."},
{"category":"Teeth","level":"medium","number":"5275","question":"Under what living conditions would a horse's teeth make him appear older than he actually is?","answer":"When kept on sandy soil pastures (FYI: Sand wears down the teeth at a faster than normal rate.)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"int bonus","number":"5276","question":"Name 3 documents you should carry with you when you travel across state or border lines with your horse.","answer":"Current health certificate, proof of ownership, proof of negative Coggins test, brand inspection, other documents required by your destination or border crossing (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"5277","question":"What TWO things are mandatory when transporting horses across ALL state lines?","answer":"Negative Coggins test and current health certificate (FYI.  Brand inspection is NOT required by all states.)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"5278","question":"Besides a first aid kit, what is another important kit to have with you when travelling?","answer":"Tool kit (also accept emergency road kit)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"5279","question":"In transporting horses, what can you do prevent trouble when hauling a mare and stallion together?","answer":"Rub Vicks Vapor Rub on their nostrils to prevent them from smelling each other (also accept keep them separated)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5280","question":"When trailering, some horses, like people, get sick from motion.  Name ONE thing you can do to prevent this.","answer":"Adjust the feeding schedule to avoid travelling when horse is full; feed smaller amounts more often if necessary; limit grain; give free choice hay; bran mash before travel; tube with oil"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"hard","number":"5281","question":"What is the “twenty-eight hour law”?","answer":"Law in the U.S. that prohibits transporting livestock for a period of longer than 28 consecutive hours without unloading, feeding, watering and resting for at least 5 hours before resuming transportation."},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"5282","question":"Ideally, what is the desirable rest to driving time in hours when trailering your horse?","answer":"1 hour rest for every 3 hours driving"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5283","question":"At minimum, how long before you travel should your horse's vaccinations be brought up to date?","answer":"At least 2 weeks before leaving"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5284","question":"On long trailer trips, how often should you offer your horse a drink of water?","answer":"Every 3 - 4 hours (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5285","question":"When trailering your horse long distances, it's recommended that you offer him water every 3-4 hours.  Since you can't carry enough water for the entire trip, how can you deal with taste changes in the water?","answer":"Use something to mask the taste (like lemonade, Gatorade, electrolyte solutions, soft drinks, Kool-Aid) (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5286","question":"What is the MOST important consideration when trailering a horse?","answer":"Safety"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"int bonus","number":"5287","question":"Give 3 features of a horse trailer that provide added safety for the horse.","answer":"Butt bar or butt chain, chest or wall padding, screened windows, rubber mats, safety ties (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"int bonus","number":"5288","question":"Name 3 things you should check on your trailer regularly.","answer":"Floor boards, door hinges, hitch, safety chains, lights, brakes, tire wear, tire inflation, hitch weld, wheel bearings, sharp projections on trailer (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"5289","question":"What are the 3 types of braking systems for horse trailers?","answer":"Hydraulic, electrical, impulse"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5290","question":"What part of a straight load trailer gives the horse something to brace on rather than the door?","answer":"Butt bar or butt chain (accept either)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5291","question":"What structure acts as a safety feature in that it will help prevent a horse from falling out of the trailer when the door is open?","answer":"Butt bar or butt chain (accept either) (FYI:  Butt bars and chains are used in straight load trailers.)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5292","question":"When unloading a horse from a trailer, what should you do before you release the butt chain or open the door?","answer":"Untie the horse"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5293","question":"Why should you NEVER undo the butt chain or open the trailer door before untying your horse?","answer":"Horse might try to back out as soon as the trailer door opens."},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5294","question":"Besides the hitch, what else is used to attach the trailer to the tow vehicle?","answer":"Safety chains (also accept lights, brakes, stabilizer bars)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"5295","question":"Name 3 connections between your truck and trailer that you should always double check.","answer":"Lights, brakes, hitch, safety chains"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5296","question":"Why should chains be used to attach the horse trailer to the truck?","answer":"To provide added safety (If the hitch comes loose, the truck and trailer will still be attached by the chains.)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5297","question":"When should you check the trailer hitch?","answer":"Before leaving (and at every stop)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5298","question":"Vehicles used to tow trailers must have a safe, sturdy hitch.  The hitch should be attached to what part of your vehicle?","answer":"Frame"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5299","question":"When trailering horses, what is one of the most important things to check?","answer":"Hitch (also accept trailer door or any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"5300","question":"Name 3 driving practices you should follow when pulling a trailer.","answer":"Start and stop slowly; make turns slowly; drive defensively; check hitch; make sure doors are closed (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5301","question":"What GENERAL color trailers may cause profuse sweating or heat stroke in the summer?","answer":"Dark"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5302","question":"To prevent horses from getting too hot, trailers should be what?","answer":"Well ventilated (also accept a light color)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5303","question":"If you tie your horse in a trailer, what kind of knot should you use?","answer":"Quick release knot (FYI: You can also use trailer ties with panic snaps.)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5304","question":"Give ONE reason why rubber mats should be periodically removed from a horse trailer.","answer":"To check for rot; to check for rust; to allow floors to dry; to prevent rot; to prevent corrosion of metal floors (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5305","question":"When trailering your horse, what can you use on the floor to reduce concussion or pounding on your horse's legs?","answer":"Rubber mats or shavings (accept either)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"5306","question":"Name 3 pieces of equipment used to protect your horse when trailering.","answer":"Leg wraps, tail wrap, shipping boots, head bumper, blanket, hock pads, knee pads, hobbles, bell boots (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5307","question":"Name the piece of tack that keeps a horse from injuring its head in a trailer.","answer":"Head bumper"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5308","question":"2 part question:  When would you commonly see a head bumper being used and why would one be used?","answer":"When—during trailering; why—tall horse, bad shipper, horse that throws its head or rears during loading or unloading (also accept when leading a horse into a barn with low ceilings or low doorways)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5309","question":"Leg wraps for shipping should extend from the knees and hocks downward past what part of the horse?","answer":"Coronary band"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5310","question":"What SPECIFIC areas of the horse's leg do shipping boots or wraps protect?","answer":"Knees and hocks downward past the coronary band (also accept lower legs)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5311","question":"Give ONE reason why you would you use leg wraps or bandages on your horse when it is traveling.","answer":"To protect the legs, to prevent swelling, or to prevent fatigue"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5312","question":"What is a good safety measure for your horse's legs when you're trailering him?","answer":"Use leg wraps or shipping boots"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"5313","question":"2 part question:  Give ONE advantage and ONE disadvantage of using a tail wrap during trailering.","answer":"Advantages—keeps hair from rubbing on butt bar, keeps tail clean; disadvantages—if put on too tight, may cut off circulation or cause hair to fall out"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"5314","question":"Name 3 areas you should measure on your horse in order to determine if the trailer stall space is adequate.","answer":"Resting head height; width from stifle to stifle; length from chest to tail; total length from head to tail"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5315","question":"How high should the ceiling of a horse trailer be?","answer":"High enough so the horse doesn't hit its head (10 inches higher than the horse's head in a normal resting position)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5316","question":"How much room should there be on each side of a horse in a trailer stall?","answer":"3 (three) inches"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"5317","question":"If your horse is leaning against the divider in the horse trailer, ideally how many inches would there be between his other side and the trailer wall?","answer":"6 inches (should have 3 inches on each side when standing properly)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"5318","question":"Name 3 factors you should consider when choosing a vehicle to pull a trailer.","answer":"Truck size; engine size; electrical system; single or double axle; ball size; type of hitch; tire size; braking system; towing capacity; cooling system; type, weight, length of trailer; weight capacity of truck; cost (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5319","question":"What is one of the most common mistakes when teaching a horse to load in a trailer?","answer":"Rushing (not taking enough time)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"5320","question":"Name 3 ways horses can ride in a horse trailer.","answer":"Slant, head to head, head to tail, side by side, loose as in a stock trailer (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"jr bonus","number":"5321","question":"Name 3 types of horse trailers.","answer":"Slant, stock, straight load, in-line, horse van, gooseneck (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5322","question":"Which type trailer attaches to the truck bed?","answer":"Gooseneck or 5th wheel (accept either)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"medium","number":"5323","question":"How should gooseneck hitches be attached to the tow vehicle?","answer":"To a ball in truck bed (also to the frame)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5324","question":"Describe a slant load trailer.","answer":"Horses ride side by side on a slant with dividers separating them."},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5325","question":"Which type of trailer is a favorite because of the ease of loading and unloading horses?","answer":"Slant load"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"sr bonus","number":"5326","question":"Give 3 advantages of a slant load trailer.","answer":"Horses ride easier; horses are more stable during turns; horses encounter less stress; horses load and unload easier (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5327","question":"Which type of trailer is a safe and popular way to transport a mare and foal?","answer":"Stock trailer"},
{"category":"Trailering","level":"easy","number":"5328","question":"When shipping one horse in a two horse straight load trailer, on which side should the horse be loaded?","answer":"Left side"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5329","question":"How should a WORKOUT conclude?","answer":"With a cool down period (also accept on a positive note)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"intermediate","number":"5330","question":"Once a horse becomes conditioned or fit, what is one of the biggest challenges for the trainer?","answer":"Maintaining fitness"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5331","question":"Name ONE vital sign that provides a good monitor of how horses respond to exercise.","answer":"Heart rate or pulse; respiratory rate"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5332","question":"Give ONE reason why you should warm up your horse before a workout.","answer":"Loosen up horse's muscles; decrease injury (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5333","question":"Give ONE result of overtraining for a specific event.","answer":"Horse gets sour; horse doesn't want to perform; horse can get injured (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"intermediate","number":"5334","question":"What is the process of building up the horse's cardiovascular system, tendons, and ligaments called?","answer":"Conditioning"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5335","question":"Proper use of what in the horse's diet actually increases the time before fatigue sets in during exercise or conditioning?","answer":"Fat"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5336","question":"What frequently determines how a horse performs in extended competitions?","answer":"How quickly it fatigues (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5337","question":"A cool down period is essential after vigorous exercise to allow your horse to eliminate any accumulated lactic acid.  What will be the consequence for the next 24 - 48 hours if you do not do this?","answer":"Sore muscles"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5338","question":"In some facets of the horse industry, exercise is used for purposes other than improving a horse’s endurance, speed, or athletic potential.  The main goal in fitting halter horses is what?","answer":"To maximize muscular development or to improve body tone (accept either)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5339","question":"How will training for short, intense performances change a horse’s muscle physiology?","answer":"Increases muscle mass and strength"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5340","question":"How quickly a horse’s heart rate decreases and returns to its resting value is an indication of what?","answer":"Fitness of the horse"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5341","question":"Approximately how long will a horse maintain CARDIOVASCULAR fitness after beginning a layoff?","answer":"6 - 8 weeks (accept any number within this range) (FYI: Musculoskeletal fitness declines faster.)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"5342","question":"Prior to a work or exercise period, name 3 ways you can evaluate the fitness and soundness of your horse for training.","answer":"Heart rate, temperature, respiratory rate, capillary refill time, visual observation at walk or trot, soreness or sensitivity of back or loin noted while grooming, soreness or lameness when flexion testing, soreness or lameness during warm-up ride"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"5343","question":"Identify 3 physiological and/or anatomical factors that would indicate a horse’s racing performance or athletic ability.","answer":"Conformation, respiratory capacity, cardiovascular capacity, gait, type of muscle fibers, proportion of muscle fibers"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"5344","question":"Successful conditioning of the equine athlete is dependent on several factors.  Name 3.","answer":"Genetics, training, age, soundness, feeding (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5345","question":"Recovery heart rate can be helpful in determining fitness.  What are the TWO things you should be looking for?","answer":"Speed of recovery; how low the heart rate falls in a specific recovery time"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5346","question":"What is aerobic metabolism?","answer":"Breakdown of energy sources in the PRESENCE of oxygen"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5347","question":"What is anaerobic metabolism?","answer":"Breakdown of energy sources in the ABSENCE of oxygen"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5348","question":"In the horse's muscles, the anaerobic breakdown of glucose during hard exercise is performed in the absence of adequate levels of what specific element?","answer":"Oxygen"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5349","question":"Sprinting and galloping can produce an oxygen deficit within the skeletal muscles and can result in what type of metabolism?","answer":"Anaerobic metabolism"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5350","question":"What is “anaerobic threshold”?","answer":"Point where the body starts breaking down energy in the absence of oxygen"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5351","question":"What is the study of movement called?","answer":"Biomechanics or kinesiology (accept either)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5352","question":"In regards to training, what does the term \"fartlek\" mean?","answer":"Alternating periods of slow and fast work (FYI:  Fartlek comes from the Swedish word meaning \"speed play\".)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5353","question":"Overexertion of a muscle without adequate conditioning can lead to the depletion of what in the muscles?","answer":"Glycogen (also accept ATP)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5354","question":"After performing strenuous exercise, a cool down period is suggested to remove what by-product of metabolism from the muscles?","answer":"Lactic acid"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5355","question":"In reference to training and conditioning, what does “LSD” mean?","answer":"Long, slow distance (conditioning program of increasing distance over an extended time)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5356","question":"Name TWO parts of a fitness program.","answer":"Diet and exercise"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5357","question":"Name ONE way to cool out a hot horse.","answer":"Walk him; spray him with a hose; sponge him down; give him a couple of swallows of water every few minutes (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5358","question":"Why is it a good practice to walk your horse for the last half mile on a ride?","answer":"To cool him out"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5359","question":"What do you call a horse that's neither hot to the touch nor breathing hard after he's been exercised?","answer":"Cooled out"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5360","question":"If you've ridden your horse hard, when should you let him have his fill of water?","answer":"After he's cooled out"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5361","question":"When training horses, why should your cues be consistent?","answer":"So you don’t confuse the horse (so he’ll understand what is being asked)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5362","question":"Explain the general steps you’d use when teaching your horse to respond to cues.","answer":"Give your horse a cue, if he responds to the cue praise him and release the pressure; if he doesn’t respond, give a stronger cue; end training sessions on positive notes; repeat process so the horse learns by repetition (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5363","question":"What system of training horses has its roots in classical Greek horsemanship and became recognized during the Renaissance when the great European riding masters developed it?","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5364","question":"In training, how does a foal learn?","answer":"By repetition"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5365","question":"How much time should a young foal be worked with each day?","answer":"30 minutes"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5366","question":"Using a sack, saddle blanket, or tarp as part of gentling and training a colt is called what?","answer":"Sacking out"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5367","question":"Using a rump rope can help teach a foal to do what?","answer":"Lead"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5368","question":"When teaching foals to lead, what is a rump or tail rope?","answer":"Cotton rope that's wrapped around the foal's hindquarters to teach it to lead"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5369","question":"How do you teach a young foal to lead?","answer":"Have someone lead the mare so the foal can follow and apply light pressure on the foal's halter so he knows he's being led; use a rump rope; pull gently forward or to the side, if he takes a step forward, praise him (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5370","question":"Give ONE reason why you should have short lessons repeated often when working with young foals.","answer":"Young foals have short attention spans, young foals have a limited capacity to absorb new things"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"jr bonus","number":"5371","question":"Name 3 things you should teach a foal.","answer":"To lead; to be groomed; to be clipped; to have feet worked with; to load in the trailer (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5372","question":"What is the difference between longeing and round pen work?","answer":"Round pen work doesn't require a longe line (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"novice","number":"5373","question":"What is ground training?","answer":"Training the horse from the ground"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"int bonus","number":"5374","question":"Name 3 things that can be included in ground training.","answer":"Manners; longeing; line driving; in-hand work (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"5375","question":"Name 3 things you can teach a horse by ground driving.","answer":"Teach horse to get used to bit; control speed; control direction; respond to verbal cues; respond to trainer (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"novice","number":"5376","question":"What is it called when a horse travels around a handler in a large circle on a longe line?","answer":"Longeing"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5377","question":"When your horse is excited or full of steam, what should you do before riding him?","answer":"Longe him or work him in a round pen"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5378","question":"When longeing, where should you stand to keep the horse moving forward?","answer":"Out from the hip (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5379","question":"When longeing, where do you step to signal a horse to stop?","answer":"Step forward (towards the shoulder)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"jr bonus","number":"5380","question":"Name 3 pieces of equipment you need to longe a horse.","answer":"Halter or longeing cavesson, whip, longe line"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"jr bonus","number":"5381","question":"Name 3 voice commands used when longeing.","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, whoa (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"jr bonus","number":"5382","question":"Give TWO reasons to longe horses.","answer":"Letting your horse work off steam, training young horse, teaching horse to respect you (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5383","question":"When riding, what should you do when the horse does well?","answer":"Pat him or praise him (also accept release pressure)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5384","question":"How should you end each TRAINING session?","answer":"On a positive note (also accept with a cool down period)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5385","question":"When first teaching a horse to neck rein, why would you need to use two hands?","answer":"One to pull (direct rein) and one to push (bearing rein)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5386","question":"How must you start any training procedure involving quick motions?","answer":"Slowly"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5387","question":"Why is a hackamore used to start young horses in training?","answer":"Provides control, but doesn’t injure the mouth"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"5388","question":"What 3 things can the handler do to lessen fear and excitement in nervous horses?","answer":"Have a calm attitude; use a soft voice; use slow, easy movements"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5389","question":"All of the horse's physiological senses are important in training.  What is considered to be the most important of these senses for responding to training cues?","answer":"Touch"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5390","question":"In training, communication with the horse seems to be through what TWO senses of the animal?","answer":"Touch and hearing"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"5391","question":"Name 3 factors that are fundamental to the psychology of horse training.","answer":"Stimuli or cues, responses, reinforcements"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5392","question":"What is the acquisition period of training?","answer":"When the horse is learning a task"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5393","question":"What do you call a response that's learned through practice?","answer":"Conditioned response"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5394","question":"What is the difference between conditioned and unconditioned responses?","answer":"Conditioned—response is learned; unconditioned—natural response (accept any correct wording)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5395","question":"When cues are presented without reinforcement, a learned response will gradually diminish to the pre-training level.  What is this called?","answer":"Extinction"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5396","question":"What term is used to describe the process of desensitization of the newborn foal to being handled by humans such as with grooming, working with the feet, etc.?","answer":"Imprint training"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5397","question":"In reference to training, how are punishment, escape, and avoidance similar?","answer":"They all involve aversive or negative stimuli."},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5398","question":"What is the term used when a horse moves away from pressure to avoid a more severe punishment?","answer":"Avoidance"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5399","question":"What is the term used when a horse runs or bolts from an aversive stimulus?","answer":"Escape"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5400","question":"What is the aim of punishment?","answer":"To weaken or eliminate an undesirable behavior"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"int bonus","number":"5401","question":"Name 3 types of rewards that can be used in training horses.","answer":"Food, praise, petting, removal of pressure, discontinuing work, letting horse relax (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5402","question":"In regards to training, what is “power of association”?","answer":"Ability to link an action and a reaction (or stimulus and response) (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5403","question":"Why is the horse's power of association useful in training?","answer":"Horse will try to do as asked to earn a reward or to avoid a punishment (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5404","question":"What is the difference between positive and negative reinforcement?","answer":"Positive reinforcement—animal gets a reward for a correct behavior; negative reinforcement—pressure or discomfort is removed when animal does the right thing"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5405","question":"What is a schedule of reinforcement called when not every response is reinforced?","answer":"Intermittent reinforcement"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5406","question":"Give the common term for positive reinforcement.","answer":"Reward training"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5407","question":"What type of reinforcement is reward training?","answer":"Positive reinforcement"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5408","question":"In reference to training, what is the correct term for the acts or movements a horse makes when given cues or stimuli?","answer":"Responses"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5409","question":"What do you call a stimulus that naturally causes a response?","answer":"Unconditioned stimulus"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5410","question":"What term classifies the following devices:  knee strap, side sling, casting harness, nose twitch, hobbles, and breeding chute?","answer":"Restraints"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"sr bonus","number":"5411","question":"Name 3 methods of restraining a horse.","answer":"Tying, chute, hobbles, high line, picket line, blindfolding, twitch, lifting foot, holding ear or tail (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5412","question":"What is a \"finished\" horse?","answer":"One that's completely trained (or has a lot of training)"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5413","question":"What is a \"green\" horse?","answer":"One with little training"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"medium","number":"5414","question":"What is the general term for teaching a horse what actions are expected in response to the handler's cues?","answer":"Training"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"hard","number":"5415","question":"In reference to training, what does the term \"trial\" mean?","answer":"Practice"},
{"category":"Training and Conditioning","level":"easy","number":"5416","question":"Name TWO things to do when warming up your horse.","answer":"Walk, trot, lateral flexion, vertical flexion"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5417","question":"A horse with no blemishes or unsoundness of the legs is said to have what kind of legs?","answer":"\"Clean legs\""},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5418","question":"Why is soundness in the horse of extreme importance?","answer":"Unsoundness affects his usefulness (if he's not sound, you can't use him)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5419","question":"What does it mean when we say a horse is \"sound\"?","answer":"No injuries, disease, or unsoundness (accept any)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5420","question":"What common term refers to a horse that's free from injuries and flaws?","answer":"Sound"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5421","question":"What is the term used to indicate that a horse may have a structural problem or deviation which may have only limited effect on his ability to perform?","answer":"Serviceably sound"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5422","question":"Explain the difference between working soundness and breeding soundness.","answer":"Working soundness—horse is OK to work, but not breed due to genetic or other issues; breeding soundness—horse is OK to breed, but not work"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5423","question":"What is meant by the term \"serviceably sound\"?","answer":"Horse has abnormalities that have only LIMITED effects on its usefulness."},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5424","question":"What is unsoundness in a horse?","answer":"Any abnormality that interferes with the usefulness of the horse (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5425","question":"Name 3 unsoundnesses that do NOT result in lameness.","answer":"Blindness, cataracts, monkey mouth, parrot mouth, fistulous withers, poll evil, hernia, heaves, roaring, infertility, tipped vulva (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5426","question":"If a horse is said to be \"walking on eggs\", what condition may be affecting it?","answer":"Navicular, laminitis, or founder (accept any)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5427","question":"Why are unsoundnesses that are the result of faulty conformation serious?","answer":"They reoccur or may be inherited (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5428","question":"On what GENERAL part of the horse would the following conditions be found:  quittor, corns, thrush, and gravel?","answer":"Feet"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5429","question":"Both base wide and base narrow stances place weight unevenly on the hoof.  Name TWO unsoundnesses that tend to develop due to this uneven weight distribution.","answer":"Ringbone and sidebone"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5430","question":"What general category of unsoundness makes a horse undesirable for breeding?","answer":"Inherited ones (breeding unsoundness)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5431","question":"2 part question:  What is the hardest part of the horse to keep sound and why?","answer":"Foreleg; it's subjected to the most weight and concussion"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5432","question":"Give 3 general causes of most unsoundness.","answer":"Trauma, stress, strain, faulty conformation (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5433","question":"Name 3 classifications of unsoundness.","answer":"Conformational; health-induced; congenital; acquired; breeding; working; systemic; head-related; body-related"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5434","question":"What unsoundness of the front foot is a horse predisposed to develop if it's camped out?","answer":"Navicular, laminitis, or founder (accept any)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"int bonus","number":"5435","question":"Name 3 unsoundnesses of the front legs.","answer":"Buck knee, calf knee, splint, windpuff, bowed tendon, sidebone, bucked shin, osselets, sesamoiditis, popped knee, navicular (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5436","question":"Name 3 unsoundnesses of the head.","answer":"Cataract, blindness, poll evil, parrot mouth, monkey mouth jaw"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5437","question":"What is the main cause of hind leg unsoundness?","answer":"Trauma (such as sprains, strains, or twists)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"int bonus","number":"5438","question":"Name 3 unsoundnesses of the hind leg.","answer":"Hip down, stifled, stringhalt, curb, thoroughpin, bog spavin, bone or jack spavin, blind or occult spavin, blood spavin (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5439","question":"Name TWO unsoundnesses of the horse's hocks.","answer":"Thoroughpin, bone or jack spavin, bog spavin, blind or occult spavin, capped hock, curb"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5440","question":"Of the 70% unsoundnesses that occur in the front legs, what percentage of them will occur in the knee or below?","answer":"65%"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5441","question":"What percentage of unsoundness in horses occurs in the front legs?","answer":"70% (FYI:  Of those 70%, 65% are at the knees or below.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"jr bonus","number":"5442","question":"Name 3 treatments for both splints and bowed tendons.","answer":"Cold hosing or ice packs, anti-inflammatory drugs such as Bute, support bandages, rest"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5443","question":"Give ONE example of a blemish.","answer":"Scar, rope burn (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5444","question":"What is the term for a mark or deformity that decreases the beauty, but NOT the usefulness of the horse?","answer":"Blemish"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5445","question":"What is a blemish?","answer":"Any mark or deformity that diminishes the beauty, but not the usefulness of a horse"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5446","question":"What is the MAIN treatment for a bowed tendon?","answer":"Rest (FYI: Other treatments include icing or cold hosing, support wraps, and anti-inflammatory drugs such as Bute.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5447","question":"Name TWO tissues that may be involved in a bowed tendon.","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon, superficial flexor tendon, suspensory ligament"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5448","question":"What are bowed tendons?","answer":"Enlarged or stretched flexor tendons (behind cannon bone)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5449","question":"What COMMON term describes swelling of the superficial flexor tendon due to tendonitis?","answer":"Bowed tendon"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5450","question":"Name 3 things that predispose a horse to bowed tendons.","answer":"Calf knee; long pastern; long toe and low heels; improper shoeing, tied in at knee; legs too fine for horse's size; repeated work on hard surfaces; repeated work on soft or boggy surfaces; genetic"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5451","question":"What is bucked shin?","answer":"Inflammation or enlargement of the front of the cannon (FYI: Bucked shins are like shin splints in humans.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5452","question":"What bone does \"bucked shins\" affect?","answer":"Cannon"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5453","question":"Identify the following condition:  more common in young horses in vigorous training; starts as soreness but it can persist and form a swelling on the front of the cannon.","answer":"Bucked shins"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5454","question":"Where would you find a shoe boil?","answer":"On a horse's elbow (FYI: Shoe boil is also called capped elbow and olecranon bursitis)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5455","question":"What is the main cause of shoe boil or capped elbow?","answer":"Elbow being irritated by the shoe or hoof of the front foot (when the horse is lying down)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5456","question":"What is the COMMON name for olecranon bursitis?","answer":"Shoe boil or capped elbow (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5457","question":"What is the term used to describe a bursitis or swelling at the point of the elbow?","answer":"Capped elbow or shoe boil (FYI: It's also called olecranon bursitis.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5458","question":"What is the most common BLEMISH of the hind limbs?","answer":"Capped hock"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5459","question":"What is a soft enlargement on the point of hock called?","answer":"Capped hock (FYI:  Capped hock is often caused by repeated trauma such as stall kicking.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5460","question":"Is capped hock a blemish or an unsoundness?","answer":"Blemish"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5461","question":"What is carpitis?","answer":"Popped knee or enlargement of knee joint (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5462","question":"What do you call an enlargement of the knee joint?","answer":"Carpitis or popped knee (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5463","question":"Is popped knee an unsoundness or blemish?","answer":"Can be either; if horse is lame, then unsoundness, otherwise it’s a blemish"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5464","question":"Name ONE cause of cataracts in horses.","answer":"Inherited, congenital, acquired (may develop after injury, inflammation, or disease)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5465","question":"Cataracts are a condition where a cloudiness or opacity forms in what structure in the horse's eye?","answer":"Lens"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5466","question":"What is a cataract?","answer":"Cloudy or opaque appearance of the eye (more specifically the lens of the eye)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5467","question":"Which condition causes clouding of the eye lens and may result in blindness?","answer":"Cataract"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5468","question":"Is a cataract an unsoundness or a blemish?","answer":"Unsoundness"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5469","question":"What is the name of condition where a horse's lower leg is bent forward due to contracted tendons?","answer":"Cocked ankle (FYI:  Cocked ankle is a partial dislocation of the ankle or fetlock caused by shortened tendons on the back (posterior) side of the leg.  It is usually seen in the hind leg.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5470","question":"Name 3 things that can help prevent cocked ankles in a foal.","answer":"Exercise; don't overfeed; keep heels trimmed so there's plenty of frog pressure"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5471","question":"Name the unsoundness described as a hard swelling below the point of the hock.","answer":"Curb (FYI: A curb is inflammation of the plantar ligament. It's seen in extremely sickle-hocked horses.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5472","question":"A horse that's extremely sickle hocked is prone to what unsoundness of the hock?","answer":"Curb"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5473","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as a curb.","answer":"Hard swelling below the point of the hock (due to thickening of the plantar tarsal ligament)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5474","question":"What is the term for inflammation and thickening of the plantar tarsal ligament below the point of the hock?","answer":"Curb (FYI:  Curbs may occur in extremely sickle-hocked horses.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5475","question":"What GENERAL age of horses is epiphysitis associated with?  (eh-pee-fiss-EYE-tis)","answer":"Young horses (FYI: Epiphysitis is inflammation of the growth plates.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5476","question":"What is the name for inflammation and enlargement of the growth plates of the long bones in rapidly growing horses?","answer":"Epiphysitis (eh-pih-fiss-EYE-tis) (also accept physitis)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5477","question":"Name TWO unsoundnesses of the top line that involve infected or inflamed bursas.","answer":"Poll evil; fistulous withers"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5478","question":"What is poll evil?","answer":"Inflamed swelling between the ears (FYI:  Inflammation of the cranial nuchal bursa that's caused by trauma or infection.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5479","question":"Name the unsoundness that's described as an inflamed swelling between the ears.","answer":"Poll evil"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5480","question":"What is the COMMON name for an infection of the cranial nuchal or supra-atlantal bursa? (NUKE-al)","answer":"Poll evil"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5481","question":"What is the name for a condition in which an infection of the withers leads to an abscess?","answer":"Fistulous withers"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5482","question":"2 part question:  What is fistulous withers and what causes it?","answer":"Chronic inflammation of the (supraspinous) bursa near the withers; caused by trauma or infection (such as Brucella abortus bacteria)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5483","question":"What is a hernia?","answer":"Protrusion of internal organs or tissues through a body wall or cavity (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5484","question":"What is it called when an organ or tissue protrudes through a body wall or cavity?","answer":"Hernia"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5485","question":"Name TWO areas where hernias are most commonly seen.","answer":"Umbilical and scrotal (inguinal) areas"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5486","question":"What type of hernia only occurs in the male horse?","answer":"Scrotal (inguinal)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5487","question":"What is the cause of hip down?","answer":"Trauma (such as a direct blow that causes a fracture)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5488","question":"What is \"hip down\"?","answer":"When one hip is lower than the other (FYI:  Hip Down is usually caused by trauma such as a direct blow.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5489","question":"Name TWO congenital defects of the jaw.","answer":"Parrot mouth (overshot jaw, overbite, or brachygnathism) and monkey mouth (undershot jaw, sow mouth, underbite, or prognathism)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5490","question":"Why is a horse with parrot mouth genetically undesirable?","answer":"Parrot mouth is a dominant trait. (FYI:  Parrot mouth is called brachygnathism.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5491","question":"If a horse is said to be \"favoring\" a foot, what is he doing?","answer":"Limping slightly"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5492","question":"Explain the phrase \"go short\".","answer":"To take short steps (indicative of lameness)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5493","question":"Name ONE way to determine the exact location of a horse's lameness.","answer":"Comparing the sore leg to the opposite leg; looking and feeling for swelling; feeling for tenderness; using hoof testers; radiographs (x-rays); nerve blocks (accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5494","question":"Most lameness can be detected at what gait?","answer":"Trot"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5495","question":"What is lameness?","answer":"Any irregularity of gait resulting from moving with pain or difficulty"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5496","question":"What is the cause of most leg injuries?","answer":"Trauma"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5497","question":"What term is used when, as a sign of lameness, the horse stands with one front foot extended more than normal?","answer":"Pointing"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5498","question":"Where does the most unsoundness from concussion and trauma occur in the horse?","answer":"Front legs (FYI: Front legs carry about 65% of the horse's weight; 70% of unsoundness occur in the front legs.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5499","question":"Referring to horses, concussion or pounding of the feet is the primary cause of what?","answer":"Lameness"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5500","question":"If a horse is lame on a front foot, describe the way he would walk.","answer":"Head bobs when the lame foot strikes the ground."},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5501","question":"What do you call any irregularity in gait that results from moving with pain or difficulty?","answer":"Lameness"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5502","question":"What kind of gait does a horse have if it's lame on both front legs?","answer":"Short, stiff, or stilted stride (with his head carried higher than usual)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5503","question":"In general, what is the most common lameness problem in Standardbred race horses?","answer":"Inflammation of the hocks"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5504","question":"Symptoms such as pointing, a short stubby painful stride, and lameness are found in which disease?","answer":"Navicular, laminitis, or founder (accept any)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"int bonus","number":"5505","question":"Name 3 causes (NOT examples) of lameness.","answer":"Injury; congenital; developmental; conformation flaws; infections; metabolic (such as laminitis); circulatory disorder; nervous disorder; combination"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5506","question":"Why is there less lameness and unsoundness in the hind feet and legs?","answer":"Hind legs support less weight and do less work."},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5507","question":"When a horse is trotting and he lifts his head when his right front foot hits the ground, what leg or legs is he lame in?","answer":"Right front and/or left rear"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5508","question":"How is the horse's head carried when he's lame in both front feet?","answer":"Head is carried higher than usual."},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5509","question":"When the lame foot of a horse touches the ground, what position will the horse's head be in?","answer":"Jerked up"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5510","question":"What condition is defined as an inflammation of the laminae of the foot?","answer":"Laminitis (also accept founder)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5511","question":"What is another name for founder?","answer":"Laminitis"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5512","question":"What condition in horses can be compared to a severe blood blister under your fingernail?","answer":"Laminitis or founder (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5513","question":"What is another name for laminitis?","answer":"Founder"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5514","question":"What is the term for a non-infectious inflammation of the sensitive laminae of one or more hooves?","answer":"Laminitis (also accept founder)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5515","question":"Name TWO causes of laminitis or founder.  DO NOT READ, PART OF THE ANSWER: Feed changes—sudden feed changes, grain overload, lush green pasture","answer":"Colic; feed changes; obesity; foot concussion; weather changes; stress; leg or foot injuries; diseases (EMS); infections (PHF); toxins (Black Walnut, Blister Beetle, Red Maple); surgery; drugs, allergies; endotoxemia; retained placenta; dystocia Name TWO causes of laminitis or founder. DO NOT READ, PART OF THE ANSWER:Feed changes—sudden feed changes, grain overload, lush green pasture"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"int bonus","number":"5516","question":"Name 3 possible causes of laminitis or founder. DO NOT READ, PART OF THE ANSWER: Feed changes—sudden feed changes, grain overload, lush green pasture","answer":"Colic; feed changes; obesity; foot concussion; weather changes; stress; leg or foot injuries; diseases (EMS); infections (PHF); toxins (Black Walnut, Blister Beetle, Red Maple); surgery; drugs, allergies; endotoxemia; retained placenta; dystocia"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5517","question":"How does a diet that’s high in simple carbohydrates, such as too much grain or too much lush pasture, cause laminitis?","answer":"Too many carbohydrates in the hindgut cause lactic acid to be a byproduct of microbial fermentation.  Too much lactic acid can cause laminitis (by affecting the intestinal flora which secrete toxins)."},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5518","question":"In reference to laminitis or founder what is \"dropped sole\"?","answer":"Downward rotation of the coffin bone"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5519","question":"Describe what happens to a horse's hoof when severe founder occurs.","answer":"Dropped sole or downward rotation of the coffin bone (FYI: If not stabilized, the coffin bone may penetrate the sole of the foot and result in the death of the horse.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5520","question":"What do you call the downward rotation of the coffin bone due to chronic founder or laminitis?","answer":"Dropped sole"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5521","question":"In reference to founder, which tendon is involved in the rotation of the coffin bone?","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon (deep flexor tendon)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5522","question":"Why can chronic founder be life threatening?","answer":"Coffin bone sinks or rotates; if left untreated, it can puncture the sole and can lead to death of a horse (due to infection or pain)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5523","question":"Describe a founder ring.","answer":"Visible ridges and grooves in hoof (FYI: Grooves are close together at the toe and are widely separated at the heels)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5524","question":"During which phase of founder does damage to the feet occur?","answer":"Developmental phase"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5525","question":"Lingering lameness and irregular rings in the horse's hoof wall are signs of what phase of founder?","answer":"Chronic"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5526","question":"The developmental phase of founder usually lasts how long?","answer":"24 - 72 hours (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5527","question":"Name 3 of the phases of founder.","answer":"Developmental, acute, sub-acute, and chronic"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5528","question":"Give 3 signs of the acute phase of founder.","answer":"Lameness; reluctance to move; pounding pulse; warm feet; sitting dog stance (leaning back on hind feet to take pressure off front feet)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5529","question":"Name TWO ways of preventing laminitis due to grass founder.","answer":"No pasture; limit pasture; turn out in early am; feed hay before turning out; use grazing muzzle; no lush fast-growing pastures; no spring pasture when it has been sunny and has then gotten cold (accept any correct answers)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"int bonus","number":"5530","question":"Name 3 ways of preventing laminitis due to fructan consumption (grass founder).","answer":"No pasture; limit pasture; turn out in early am; feed hay before turning out; use grazing muzzle; no lush, fast-growing pastures; no spring pasture when it has been sunny and has then gotten cold"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"int bonus","number":"5531","question":"Name 3 symptoms of acute laminitis.","answer":"Lameness (usually in front feet); warm feet; feet sensitive to touch; stiffness; settling back on hind legs to get weight off front feet (sitting dog stance); pain on standing; pounding pulse at back of pasterns"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5532","question":"Give 3 characteristics of a chronically foundered hoof.","answer":"Founder rings (rings are closer together at toe and further apart at heels); dropped sole (downward rotation of coffin bone); widened white line; long toe; curled toe; dished hoof; bulging sole; flattened sole"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5533","question":"In severe cases of founder, how much time do you have to seek treatment before irreparable damage occurs?","answer":"24 hours"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5534","question":"How long can treatment for laminitis last?","answer":"1 (one) year (FYI: Horse may never recover.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5535","question":"What is navicular disease?","answer":"Inflammation or pain of the navicular bone (and/or surrounding areas) (accept any reasonable wording) (FYI: also called navicular syndrome or Caudal Heel Pain Syndrome)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5536","question":"When moving, a horse with navicular disease tends to land on its toe to avoid what?","answer":"Concussion or pressure on the heel area"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5537","question":"An inflammation of the small navicular bone and bursa of the hoof often characterized by lameness, a short, stubby stride and pointing of the affected foot while standing may denote what disease?","answer":"Navicular"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5538","question":"Name 3 signs of navicular disease.","answer":"Shortened stride; going up on toes (to keep weight off heels); pointing; lameness"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5539","question":"Name 3 parts of the foot that are affected in horses with navicular disease.","answer":"Navicular bone, navicular bursa, and deep digital flexor tendon"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5540","question":"Horses with small feet for their body size are predisposed to what?","answer":"Navicular disease"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"int bonus","number":"5541","question":"Name 3 conformational features or horse care practices that can help prevent navicular syndrome.","answer":"Get horse with larger feet; get horse with appropriate shoulder and pastern angles; get horse NOT built downhill; keep toes short and heels elevated; gradually condition horse; work with caution on hard surfaces"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5542","question":"Other than radiographs or x-rays, what's the best method of diagnosing navicular disease?","answer":"Hoof testers"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5543","question":"What is the name of the medication that improves circulation within the foot?  It's often used on horses with navicular disease.","answer":"Isoxsuprine (eye-SOCKS-sue-preen)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5544","question":"What surgical procedure is used as a last resort in treating navicular disease?","answer":"Nerving (neurectomy)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5545","question":"In reference to unsoundness in horses, what is \"nerving\"?","answer":"Cutting a nerve (the posterior digital nerve) as a last resort treatment for navicular disease"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5546","question":"In reference to unsoundness, what are osselets?","answer":"Bony growths on the front of the fetlock (traumatic arthritis of the fetlock)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5547","question":"What are bony growths on the front of the fetlocks that are commonly seen in young racehorses?","answer":"Osselets"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5548","question":"When is lameness due to osselets most pronounced?","answer":"During exercise (especially at the trot)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5549","question":"Where on the horse are osselets found?","answer":"Fetlock (FYI:  Osselets are bony growths on the front of the fetlocks.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5550","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as ringbone.","answer":"Bony growth on the pastern (FYI: Ringbone can affect the pastern or coffin joints.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5551","question":"What is the term for bony growths on the pastern?","answer":"Ringbone"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5552","question":"Name ONE joint that ringbone affects.","answer":"Pastern joint; coffin joint"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5553","question":"What is the difference between low ringbone and high ringbone?","answer":"Low ringbone occurs in the coffin joint (between the coffin and short pastern); high ringbone occurs at the pastern joint (between the short pastern and long pastern) (FYI:  Low ringbone is more serious; high ringbone is more common.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5554","question":"Name 3 conformation faults that predispose a horse to ringbone.","answer":"Base wide; base narrow; pigeon toe; splay foot; short, steep pasterns; long, sloping pasterns"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5555","question":"Give 3 possible causes of ringbone.","answer":"Short steep pasterns; pigeon toe; splay foot; improper trimming (long toes and short heels); improper conditioning; trauma; strain; working on hard, soft, or uneven ground"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5556","question":"Which type of ringbone is more common, high or low?","answer":"High ringbone"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5557","question":"What specific type of ringbone is located at the coffin joint?","answer":"Low ringbone (FYI: High ringbone occurs at the pastern joint.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5558","question":"Low ringbone is new bone growth near the coffin joint.  Why would this be more serious than high ringbone?","answer":"It often affects joint function."},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5559","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as sidebone.","answer":"Ossification of the lateral cartilages of the coffin bone"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5560","question":"During what stage of sidebone is lameness most common?","answer":"Developmental, formative, inflammation, ossification (accept any)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5561","question":"What term is used to describe the unsoundness that is rarely found in ponies and is less common in light horses than in draft horses?  It's a calcification of the lateral cartilages of the coffin bone.","answer":"Sidebone"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5562","question":"What type of pastern conformation may contribute to cocked ankle or sidebone?","answer":"Short, steep pasterns"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5563","question":"2 part question:  Explain where sidebone would most likely develop due to the following conditions:  toe in and toe out.","answer":"Toe in—outside; toe out—inside"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5564","question":"Sidebones are a condition associated with ossification of the collateral cartilages.  What term refers to the condition that occurs when the collateral cartilages become infected?","answer":"Quittor"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5565","question":"Sidebone is the complete ossification of the cartilages of which bone?","answer":"Coffin bone (also called pedal bone, 3rd phalanx, or distal phalanx)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5566","question":"Name 3 predisposing factors for sidebone.","answer":"Poor conformation (pigeon toe or splay foot); improper shoeing; repeated concussion (from working on hard surfaces or from carrying a lot of weight); trauma"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5567","question":"A spavin refers to various abnormalities of what joint?","answer":"Hock (tarsus)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5568","question":"Name 3 types of spavin of the hocks.","answer":"Blind or occult spavin; bog spavin; bone or jack spavin; blood spavin"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5569","question":"What is the term for a spavin where the bone has degenerated and there’s lameness, but there is no visible exostosis?","answer":"Blind spavin or occult spavin (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5570","question":"What is another name for a blind spavin?","answer":"Occult spavin"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5571","question":"What is a blood spavin?","answer":"Swelling of a vein (saphenous) usually below the seat of a bog spavin (on the hock)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5572","question":"What is a swelling of the saphenous vein in the hock that is below the seat of a bog spavin?","answer":"Blood spavin"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5573","question":"What is a soft swelling on the inner front part of the hock that's caused by inflammation of the synovial membrane?","answer":"Bog spavin"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5574","question":"There are 4 different types of spavins involving the horse's hock joint.  Which spavin forms a soft distension of the joint due to synovial membrane inflammation?","answer":"Bog spavin"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5575","question":"What is a bony growth found on the inside lower portion of the hock?","answer":"Bone spavin or jack spavin"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5576","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as a bone spavin or jack spavin.","answer":"Arthritis of the lower joints of the hock (bony growth on the inside lower portion of the hock)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5577","question":"What type of spavin is usually due to arthritis of the lower joints of the hock?","answer":"Bone spavin or jack spavin (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5578","question":"What is the cause of thoroughpin?","answer":"Strain on the flexor tendon (deep digital flexor tendon)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5579","question":"Thoroughpin is a soft, fluid-filled enlargement of the outside of the joint that can be pushed freely from the outside to the inside surface of the joint.  What joint is it found in?","answer":"Hock (tarsus)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5580","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as thoroughpin.","answer":"Puffy swelling on the upper part of the hock (which is a distension of the tendon sheath of the deep digital flexor tendon)  (FYI:  Fluid can be pushed from the outside to the inside.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5581","question":"What is the puffy swelling on the upper part of the hock which is a distention of the tendon sheath of the deep digital flexor tendon?","answer":"Thoroughpin"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5582","question":"Name TWO treatments of splints.","answer":"Ice packs or cold hosing; anti-inflammatory drugs such as Bute; support wraps; rest"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5583","question":"What is one of the most common defects of the front legs?","answer":"Splints"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5584","question":"Are most splints found on the inside or outside of the cannon?","answer":"Inside"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5585","question":"What GENERAL age category of horses is prone to splints?","answer":"Young horses"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5586","question":"In a bench-kneed horse, the cannon bone is set too far to the outside of the knee joint.  What defect is this most likely to cause?","answer":"Splints"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5587","question":"In reference to blemishes and unsoundness, what is a splint?","answer":"Bony growth on the cannon and/or splint bones"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5588","question":"Name the blemish described as abnormal bony growth on the cannon or splint bone.","answer":"Splint"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5589","question":"Name 3 predisposing factors for splints.","answer":"Bench knees; trauma; training on hard ground; improper foot care"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"sr bonus","number":"5590","question":"3 part question:  Just below the inside surface of your horse's knee you feel a swelling that's firm, but not tender.  What bones are involved in this swelling, what is it called, and is it likely to cause serious problems?","answer":"Cannon and splint bones; called a splint; not likely to cause serious lameness"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5591","question":"What is another name for the condition where there is fixation of the horse's patella?","answer":"Stifled (displaced patella)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5592","question":"Describe the unsoundness known as stifled.","answer":"Patella displaces and locks (causing the leg to remain in the extended position) (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5593","question":"What is another name for stifled?","answer":"Displaced patella"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5594","question":"Name the unsoundness described as excessive jerking of the hind leg.","answer":"Stringhalt"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5595","question":"What unsoundness is most noticeable when backing the horse?","answer":"Stringhalt"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5596","question":"What is stringhalt?","answer":"Excessive jerking of the hind legs"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5597","question":"Name TWO maneuvers that cause stringhalt to be especially obvious.","answer":"Backing; turning sharply"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5598","question":"Name ONE area where sweeney is found.","answer":"Shoulder or hip"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5599","question":"In reference to unsoundness and blemishes, what is sweeney?","answer":"Atrophy or decrease in size of a single muscle or muscle group (usually seen in shoulder or hip)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5600","question":"What is the term for atrophy of the shoulder muscle due to nerve paralysis?","answer":"Sweeney"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5601","question":"2 part question:  What is injured in the shoulder that creates the muscle atrophy seen in sweeney and in what type of horse is this normally found?","answer":"Nerve (suprascapular nerve); found in draft breeds or harness horses"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5602","question":"What effect does shoulder sweeney have on a horse's performance?","answer":"Little or no effect on performance"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5603","question":"What is shoulder sweeney?","answer":"Atrophy (decrease in size) of the shoulder muscle"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5604","question":"What is atrophy?","answer":"Decrease in size or wasting away of a body part or tissue"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5605","question":"What is the term for abnormal bone growth from the surface of a bone?","answer":"Exostosis (bone spur) (ex-ahs-TOE-sis)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5606","question":"What is exostosis? (ex-ahs-TOE-sis)","answer":"Formation of new bone on the surface of a bone (bone spur)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"medium","number":"5607","question":"In reference to unsoundness, what is gonitis?","answer":"Inflammation of the stifle joint"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5608","question":"What is ossification? (ah-sih-fih-CAY-shun)","answer":"Cartilage changing into bone or the process of bone formation (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5609","question":"What do you call the changing of cartilage to bone?","answer":"Ossification (specifically endochondral ossification)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5610","question":"What is the name for the practice of applying a hot iron or needle to a blemish or unsoundness as a treatment?","answer":"Firing or pinfiring"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5611","question":"What marking is described as a muscular depression of unknown origin, is usually seen on the neck and sometimes seen on the shoulder?","answer":"Prophet's Thumb"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5612","question":"What is sesamoiditis?","answer":"Inflammation of the proximal sesamoid bones (that results in chronic lameness)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5613","question":"What are soft, puffy, fluid-filled swellings around a joint, usually the fetlock or pastern?","answer":"Windpuffs"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5614","question":"In reference to unsoundness and blemishes, what are windpuffs?","answer":"Soft, fluid-filled swellings on the fetlock or pastern (FYI:  Windpuffs are inflammations of the deep digital flexor tendon sheaths.)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"easy","number":"5615","question":"What is the cause of windpuffs?","answer":"Trauma or heavy work (accept either)"},
{"category":"Unsoundness and Blemishes","level":"hard","number":"5616","question":"What is the term for the condition that results from an excessive amount of synovial fluid in the fetlock joint capsule that is commonly seen in horses that are worked hard?","answer":"Windpuffs"},
];
